<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std"
     ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true" number="8835"
     obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true"
     sortRefs="true" version="3" docName="draft-ietf-rtcweb-transports-17">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.30.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="WebRTC Transports">Transports for WebRTC</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8835"/>
    <author fullname="Harald Alvestrand" initials="H." surname="Alvestrand">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <email>harald@alvestrand.no</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021"/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the data transport protocols used by Web
      Real-Time Communication (WebRTC),
      including the protocols used for interaction with intermediate boxes
      such as firewalls, relays, and NAT boxes.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>WebRTC is a protocol suite aimed at real-time multimedia exchange
      between browsers, and between browsers and other entities.</t>
      <t>WebRTC is described in the WebRTC overview document <xref target="RFC8825" format="default"/>, which also defines terminology used
      in this document, including the terms "WebRTC endpoint" and "WebRTC
      browser".</t>
      <t>Terminology for RTP sources is taken from <xref target="RFC7656" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>This document focuses on the data transport protocols that are used
      by conforming implementations, including the protocols used for
      interaction with intermediate boxes such as firewalls, relays, and NAT
      boxes.</t>
      <t>This protocol suite is intended to satisfy the security considerations
      described in the WebRTC security documents, <xref target="RFC8826" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8827" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>This document describes requirements that apply to all WebRTC
      endpoints. When there are requirements that apply only to WebRTC
      browsers, this is called out explicitly.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="app-transport" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Transport and Middlebox Specification</name>
      <t/>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>System-Provided Interfaces</name>
        <t>The protocol specifications used here assume that the following
        protocols are available to the implementations of the WebRTC
        protocols:</t>
        <dl>
          <dt>UDP <xref target="RFC0768" format="default"/>:</dt><dd>This is the protocol assumed by
            most protocol elements described.</dd>
          <dt>TCP <xref target="RFC0793" format="default"/>:</dt><dd>This is used for HTTP/WebSockets,
            as well as TURN/TLS and
            ICE-TCP.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>For both protocols, IPv4 and IPv6 support is assumed.</t>
        <t>For UDP, this specification assumes the ability to set the
        Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP) of the sockets opened on a per-packet basis, in order to
        achieve the prioritizations described in <xref target="RFC8837" format="default"/> (see <xref target="s-qos" format="default"/> of this document) when
        multiple media types are multiplexed. It does not assume that the DSCPs
        will be honored and does assume that they may be zeroed or
        changed, since this is a local configuration issue.</t>
        <t>Platforms that do not give access to these interfaces will not be
        able to support a conforming WebRTC endpoint.</t>
        <t>This specification does not assume that the implementation will
        have access to ICMP or raw IP.</t>
        <t>The following protocols may be used, but they can be implemented by a
        WebRTC endpoint and are therefore not defined as "system-provided
        interfaces":</t>

        <dl>
          <dt>TURN:</dt><dd>Traversal Using Relays Around NAT <xref target="RFC8656" format="default"/></dd>
          <dt>STUN:</dt><dd>Session Traversal Utilities for NAT <xref target="RFC5389" format="default"/></dd>
          <dt>ICE:</dt><dd>Interactive Connectivity Establishment <xref target="RFC8445" format="default"/></dd>
          <dt>TLS:</dt><dd>Transport Layer Security <xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/></dd>
          <dt>DTLS:</dt><dd>Datagram Transport Layer Security <xref target="RFC6347" format="default"/></dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Ability to Use IPv4 and IPv6</name>
        <t>Web applications running in a WebRTC browser <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be able to
        utilize both IPv4 and IPv6 where available -- that is, when two peers
        have only IPv4 connectivity to each other, or they have only IPv6
        connectivity to each other, applications running in the WebRTC browser
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be able to communicate.</t>
        <t>When TURN is used, and the TURN server has IPv4 or IPv6
        connectivity to the peer or the peer's TURN server, candidates of the
        appropriate types <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported. The "Happy Eyeballs"
        specification for ICE <xref target="RFC8421" format="default"/> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
        supported.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Usage of Temporary IPv6 Addresses</name>
        <t>The IPv6 default address selection specification <xref
        target="RFC6724" format="default"/> specifies that temporary addresses
        <xref target="RFC4941" format="default"/> are to be preferred over
        permanent addresses. This
        is a change from the rules specified by <xref target="RFC3484" format="default"/>. For
        applications that select a single address, this is usually done by the
        IPV6_PREFER_SRC_TMP preference flag specified in <xref target="RFC5014" format="default"/>. However, this rule, which is intended to ensure
        that privacy-enhanced addresses are used in preference to static
        addresses, doesn't have the right effect in ICE, where all addresses
        are gathered and therefore revealed to the application. Therefore, the
        following rule is applied instead:</t>

        <t indent="3">When a WebRTC endpoint gathers all IPv6 addresses on its host, and
        both nondeprecated temporary addresses and permanent addresses of the
        same scope are present, the WebRTC endpoint <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> discard the
        permanent addresses before exposing addresses to the application or
        using them in ICE. This is consistent with the default policy
        described in <xref target="RFC6724" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t indent="3">If some, but not all, of the temporary IPv6 addresses are marked
        deprecated, the WebRTC endpoint <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> discard the deprecated
        addresses, unless they are used by an ongoing connection. In an ICE
        restart, deprecated addresses that are currently in use <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be
        retained.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="s-middlebox" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Middlebox-Related Functions</name>
        <t>The primary mechanism for dealing with middleboxes is ICE, which is an
        appropriate way to deal with NAT boxes and firewalls that accept
        traffic from the inside, but only from the outside if it is in
        response to inside traffic (simple stateful firewalls).</t>
        <t>ICE <xref target="RFC8445" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported. The
        implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a full ICE implementation, not ICE-Lite. A full
        ICE implementation allows interworking with both ICE and ICE-Lite
        implementations when they are deployed appropriately.</t>
        <t>In order to deal with situations where both parties are behind NATs
        of the type that perform endpoint-dependent mapping (as defined in
        <xref target="RFC5128" sectionFormat="comma" section="2.4" />), TURN <xref target="RFC8656" format="default"/>
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported.</t>
        <t>WebRTC browsers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support configuration of STUN and TURN
        servers, from both browser configuration and an application.</t>
        <t>Note that other work exists around STUN and TURN server discovery
        and management, including <xref target="RFC8155" format="default"/> for server discovery,
        as well as <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-return" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>In order to deal with firewalls that block all UDP traffic, the
        mode of TURN that uses TCP between the WebRTC endpoint and the TURN
        server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported, and the mode of TURN that uses TLS over TCP
        between the WebRTC endpoint and the TURN server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported. See
        <xref target="RFC8656" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1"/>, for details.</t>
        <t>In order to deal with situations where one party is on an IPv4
        network and the other party is on an IPv6 network, TURN extensions for
        IPv6 <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported.</t>
        <t>TURN TCP candidates, where the connection from the WebRTC
        endpoint's TURN server to the peer is a TCP connection, <xref target="RFC6062" format="default"/> <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be supported.</t>
        <t>However, such candidates are not seen as providing any significant
        benefit, for the following reasons.</t>
        <t>First, use of TURN TCP candidates would only be relevant in cases
        where both peers are required to use TCP to establish a
        connection.</t>
        <t>Second, that use case is supported in a different way by both sides
        establishing UDP relay candidates using TURN over TCP to connect to
        their respective relay servers.</t>
        <t>Third, using TCP between the WebRTC endpoint's TURN server and the
        peer may result in more performance problems than using UDP, e.g., due
        to head of line blocking.</t>
        <t>ICE-TCP candidates <xref target="RFC6544" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported; this
        may allow applications to communicate to peers with public IP
        addresses across UDP-blocking firewalls without using a TURN
        server.</t>
        <t>If TCP connections are used, RTP framing according to <xref target="RFC4571" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used for all packets. This includes the RTP
        packets, DTLS packets used to carry data channels, and STUN
        connectivity check packets.</t>
        <t>The ALTERNATE-SERVER mechanism specified in <xref
        target="RFC5389" sectionFormat="of" section="11"/> (300 Try Alternate) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        supported.</t>
        <t>The WebRTC endpoint <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> support accessing the Internet through an
        HTTP proxy. If it does so, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the "ALPN" header as
        specified in <xref target="RFC7639" format="default"/>, and proxy authentication as
        described in <xref target="RFC7231"
        sectionFormat="of" section="4.3.6"/> and <xref target="RFC7235" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also be supported.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Transport Protocols Implemented</name>
        <t>For transport of media, secure RTP is used. The details of the
        RTP profile used are described in "Media Transport and Use of RTP in WebRTC" <xref target="RFC8834" format="default"/>, which mandates the use of a
        circuit breaker <xref target="RFC8083" format="default"/>
        and congestion control (see <xref target="RFC8836" format="default"/> for further guidance).</t>
        <t>Key exchange <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be done using DTLS-SRTP, as described in <xref target="RFC8827" format="default"/>.</t>

        <t>For data transport over the WebRTC data channel <xref target="RFC8831" format="default"/>, WebRTC endpoints <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support
        SCTP over DTLS over ICE. This encapsulation is specified in <xref target="RFC8261" format="default"/>. Negotiation of this
        transport in the Session Description Protocol (SDP) is defined in <xref target="RFC8841" format="default"/>. The SCTP extension for I-DATA
        <xref target="RFC8260" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported.</t>
        <t>The setup protocol for WebRTC data channels described in <xref target="RFC8832" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported.</t>
        <aside><t>Note: The interaction between DTLS-SRTP as defined in <xref
        target="RFC5764"/> and ICE as defined in <xref target="RFC8445"
        format="default"/> is described in <xref target="RFC8842" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>. The effect of this specification
        is that all ICE candidate pairs associated with a single component are
        part of the same DTLS association. Thus, there will only be one DTLS
        handshake, even if there are multiple valid candidate pairs.</t></aside>
        <t>WebRTC endpoints <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support multiplexing of DTLS and RTP over the
        same port pair, as described in the DTLS-SRTP specification <xref
        target="RFC5764" sectionFormat="comma" section="5.1.2"/>, with clarifications in <xref target="RFC7983" format="default"/>. All application-layer
        protocol payloads over this DTLS connection are SCTP packets.</t>
        <t>Protocol identification <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supplied as part of the DTLS
        handshake, as specified in <xref target="RFC8833" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Media Prioritization</name>
      <t>In the WebRTC prioritization model, the application tells the
      WebRTC endpoint about the priority of media and data that is controlled
      from the API.</t>
      <t>In this context, a "flow" is used for the units that are given a
      specific priority through the WebRTC API.</t>
      <t>For media, a "media flow", which can be an "audio flow" or a "video
      flow", is what <xref target="RFC7656" format="default"/> calls a "media source", which
      results in a "source RTP stream" and one or more "redundancy RTP
      streams". This specification does not describe prioritization between
      the RTP streams that come from a single media source.</t>
      <t>All media flows in WebRTC are assumed to be interactive, as defined
      in <xref target="RFC4594" format="default"/>; there is no browser API support for
      indicating whether media is interactive or noninteractive.</t>
      <t>A "data flow" is the outgoing data on a single WebRTC data
      channel.</t>
      <t>The priority associated with a media flow or data flow is classified
      as "very-low", "low", "medium", or "high". There are only four priority
      levels in the API.</t>
      <t>The priority settings affect two pieces of behavior: packet send
      sequence decisions and packet markings. Each is described in its own
      section below.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Local Prioritization</name>
        <t>Local prioritization is applied at the local node, before the
        packet is sent. This means that the prioritization has full access to
        the data about the individual packets and can choose differing
        treatment based on the stream a packet belongs to.</t>
        <t>When a WebRTC endpoint has packets to send on multiple streams
        that are congestion controlled under the same congestion control
        regime, the WebRTC endpoint <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> cause data to be emitted in such a
        way that each stream at each level of priority is being given
        approximately twice the transmission capacity (measured in payload
        bytes) of the level below.</t>
        <t>Thus, when congestion occurs, a high-priority flow will have the
        ability to send 8 times as much data as a very-low-priority flow if
        both have data to send. This prioritization is independent of the
        media type. The details of which packet to send first are
        implementation defined.</t>
        <t>For example, if there is a high-priority audio flow sending
        100-byte packets and a low-priority video flow sending 1000-byte
        packets, and outgoing capacity exists for sending &gt; 5000 payload bytes, it
        would be appropriate to send 4000 bytes (40 packets) of audio and 1000
        bytes (one packet) of video as the result of a single pass of sending
        decisions.</t>
        <t>Conversely, if the audio flow is marked low priority and the video
        flow is marked high priority, the scheduler may decide to send 2 video
        packets (2000 bytes) and 5 audio packets (500 bytes) when outgoing
        capacity exists for sending &gt; 2500 payload bytes.</t>
        <t>If there are two high-priority audio flows, each will be able to
        send 4000 bytes in the same period where a low-priority video flow is
        able to send 1000 bytes.</t>
        <t>Two example implementation strategies are:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>When the available bandwidth is known from the congestion
            control algorithm, configure each codec and each data channel with
            a target send rate that is appropriate to its share of the
            available bandwidth.</li>
          <li>When congestion control indicates that a specified number of
            packets can be sent, send packets that are available to send using
            a weighted round-robin scheme across the connections.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Any combination of these, or other schemes that have the same
        effect, is valid, as long as the distribution of transmission capacity
        is approximately correct.</t>
        <t>For media, it is usually inappropriate to use deep queues for
        sending; it is more useful to, for instance, skip intermediate frames
        that have no dependencies on them in order to achieve a lower bitrate.
        For reliable data, queues are useful.</t>
        <t>Note that this specification doesn't dictate when disparate streams
        are to be "congestion controlled under the same congestion control
        regime". The issue of coupling congestion controllers is explored
        further in <xref target="RFC8699" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="s-qos" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Usage of Quality of Service -- DSCP and Multiplexing</name>
        <t>When the packet is sent, the network will make decisions about
        queueing and/or discarding the packet that can affect the quality of
        the communication. The sender can attempt to set the DSCP field of the
        packet to influence these decisions.</t>
        <t>Implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> attempt to set QoS on the packets sent,
        according to the guidelines in <xref target="RFC8837" format="default"/>. It is appropriate to depart from
        this recommendation when running on platforms where QoS marking is not
        implemented.</t>
        <t>The implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> turn off use of DSCP markings if it detects
        symptoms of unexpected behavior such as priority inversion or blocking
        of packets with certain DSCP markings. Some examples of such behaviors
        are described in <xref target="ANRW16" format="default"/>. The detection of these
        conditions is implementation dependent.</t>
        <t>A particularly hard problem is when one media transport uses
        multiple DSCPs, where one may be blocked and another may be
        allowed. This is allowed even within a single media flow for video in
        <xref target="RFC8837" format="default"/>. Implementations need to
        diagnose this scenario; one possible implementation is to send initial
        ICE probes with DSCP 0, and send ICE probes on all the DSCPs
        that are intended to be used once a candidate pair has been
        selected. If one or more of the DSCP-marked probes fail, the sender
        will switch the media type to using DSCP 0. This can be carried out
        simultaneously with the initial media traffic; on failure, the initial
        data may need to be resent. This switch will, of course, invalidate any
        congestion information gathered up to that point.</t>
        <t>Failures can also start happening during the lifetime of the call;
        this case is expected to be rarer and can be handled by the normal
        mechanisms for transport failure, which may involve an ICE
        restart.</t>
        <t>Note that when a DSCP causes nondelivery, one has to
        switch the whole media flow to DSCP 0, since all traffic for a single
        media flow needs to be on the same queue for congestion control
        purposes. Other flows on the same transport, using different DSCPs, don't need to change.</t>
        <t>All packets carrying data from the SCTP association supporting the
        data channels <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use a single DSCP. The code point used
        <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be that recommended by <xref target="RFC8837" format="default"/> for the highest-priority data
        channel carried. Note that this means that all data packets, no matter
        what their relative priority is, will be treated the same by the
        network.</t>
        <t>All packets on one TCP connection, no matter what it carries, <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        use a single DSCP.</t>
        <t>More advice on the use of DSCPs with RTP, as well as the
        relationship between DSCP and congestion control, is given in <xref target="RFC7657" format="default"/>.</t>

        <t>There exist a number of schemes for achieving quality of service
        that do not depend solely on DSCPs. Some of these schemes
        depend on classifying the traffic into flows based on 5-tuple (source
        address, source port, protocol, destination address, destination port)
        or 6-tuple (5-tuple + DSCP). Under differing conditions, it
        may therefore make sense for a sending application to choose any of
        the following configurations:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Each media stream carried on its own 5-tuple</li>
          <li>Media streams grouped by media type into 5-tuples (such as
            carrying all audio on one 5-tuple)</li>
          <li>All media sent over a single 5-tuple, with or without
            differentiation into 6-tuples based on DSCPs</li>
        </ul>
        <t>In each of the configurations mentioned, data channels may be
        carried in their own 5-tuple or multiplexed together with one of the
        media flows.</t>
        <t>More complex configurations, such as sending a high-priority video
        stream on one 5-tuple and sending all other video streams multiplexed
        together over another 5-tuple, can also be envisioned. More
        information on mapping media flows to 5-tuples can be found in <xref target="RFC8834" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>A sending implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be able to support the following
        configurations:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Multiplex all media and data on a single 5-tuple (fully
            bundled)</li>
          <li>Send each media stream on its own 5-tuple and data on its own
            5-tuple (fully unbundled)</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The sending implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to support other
          configurations, such as
        bundling each media type (audio, video, or data) into its own 5-tuple
        (bundling by media type).</t>
        <t>Sending data channel data over multiple 5-tuples is not
        supported.</t>
        <t>A receiving implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be able to receive media and data
        in all these configurations.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>WebRTC security considerations are enumerated in <xref target="RFC8826" format="default"/>.</t>

      <t>Security considerations pertaining to the use of DSCP are enumerated
      in <xref target="RFC8837" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
<displayreference target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-return" to="RETURN"/>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0768.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4571.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4594.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4941.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5389.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5764.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6062.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6347.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6544.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6724.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7231.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7235.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7639.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7656.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8260.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8261.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8656.xml"/>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview (RFC 8825) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8825" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8825">
  <front>
    <title>Overview: Real-Time Protocols for Browser-Based Applications</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="Harald T. Alvestrand">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021" />
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8825" />
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8825"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-rmcat-cc-requirements (RFC 8836) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8836" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8836">
  <front>
    <title>Congestion Control Requirements for Interactive Real-Time Media</title>
    <author initials="R" surname="Jesup" fullname="Randell Jesup">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="Z" surname="Sarker" fullname="Zaheduzzaman Sarker" role="editor">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8836" />
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8836"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-security (RFC 8826) -->
 <reference anchor="RFC8826" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8826">
 <front>
 <title>Security Considerations for WebRTC</title>
 <author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='Eric Rescorla'>
   <organization/>
 </author>
 <date month='January' year='2021'/>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8826"/>
 <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8826"/>
 </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-rtp-usage (RFC 8834) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8834" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8834">
  <front>
    <title>Media Transport and Use of RTP in WebRTC</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Perkins" fullname="Colin Perkins">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Westerlund" fullname="Magnus Westerlund">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Ott" fullname="Jörg Ott">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021" />
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8834" />
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8834"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-data-channel (RFC 8831) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8831" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8831">
<front>
<title>WebRTC Data Channels</title>
<author initials="R" surname="Jesup" fullname="Randell Jesup">
  <organization/>
</author>
<author initials="S" surname="Loreto" fullname="Salvatore Loreto">
  <organization/>
</author>
<author initials="M" surname="Tüxen" fullname="Michael Tüxen">
  <organization/>
</author>
<date month='January' year='2021'/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8831"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8831"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol (RFC 8832) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8832" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8832">
<front>
<title>WebRTC Data Channel Establishment Protocol</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Jesup' fullname='Randell Jesup'>
  <organization/>
</author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Loreto' fullname='Salvatore Loreto'>
  <organization/>
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Tüxen' fullname='Michael Tüxen'>
  <organization/>
</author>
<date month='January' year='2021'/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8832"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8832"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-security-arch (RFC 8827) -->
 <reference anchor="RFC8827" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8827">
 <front>
 <title>WebRTC Security Architecture</title>
 <author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='Eric Rescorla'>
   <organization/>
 </author>
 <date month='January' year='2021'/>
 </front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8827"/>
 <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8827"/>
 </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-tsvwg-rtcweb-qos (RFC 8837) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8837" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8837">
  <front>
    <title>Differentiated Services Code Point (DSCP) Packet Markings for
    WebRTC QoS</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Jones" fullname="Paul Jones">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Dhesikan" fullname="Subha Dhesikan">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Jennings" fullname="Cullen Jennings">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Druta" fullname="Dan Druta">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8837" />
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8837"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp (RFC 8841) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8841" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8841">
  <front>
    <title>Session Description Protocol (SDP) Offer/Answer Procedures for
    Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) over Datagram Transport Layer
    Security (DTLS) Transport</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Shpount" fullname="Roman Shpount">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Loreto" fullname="Salvatore Loreto">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <author initials="G." surname="Camarillo" fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021" />
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8841" />
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8841"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-alpn (RFC 8833) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8833" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8833">
  <front>
    <title>Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) for WebRTC</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021" />
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8833" />
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8833"/>
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-mmusic-dtls-sdp (RFC 8842) -->
<reference anchor="RFC8842" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8842">
  <front>
    <title>Session Description Protocol (SDP) Offer/Answer Considerations for
Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) and Transport Layer Security (TLS)</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Shpount" fullname="Roman Shpount">
      <organization />
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021" />
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8842" />
  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8842"/>
</reference>
 
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7983.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8083.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8445.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8421.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5128.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5014.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3484.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7657.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8155.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8699.xml"/>

<!-- draft-ietf-rtcweb-return (Expired) -->
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-return.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="ANRW16" target="https://irtf.org/anrw/2016/anrw16-final17.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>How to say that you're special: Can we use bits in the IPv4
          header?</title>
            <author fullname="R. Barik" initials="R." surname="Barik"/>
            <author fullname="M. Welzl" initials="M." surname="Welzl"/>
            <author fullname="A. Elmokashfi" initials="A." surname="Elmokashfi"/>
            <date month="July" year="2016"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>ANRW '16: Proceedings of the 2016 Applied Networking
          Research Workshop, pages 68-70</refcontent>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/2959424.2959442"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This document is based on earlier draft versions embedded in <xref
      target="RFC8825"/>, which were the result of contributions from many RTCWEB Working Group
      members.</t>
      <t>Special thanks for reviews of earlier draft versions of this document go to
      <contact fullname="Eduardo Gueiros"/>, <contact fullname="Magnus
        Westerlund"/>, <contact fullname="Markus Isomaki"/>, and <contact fullname="Dan Wing"/>; the
      contributions from <contact fullname="Andrew Hutton"/> also deserve special mention.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
