<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-huitema-rfc-eval-project-07" number="8963" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="independent" category="info" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.4.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RFC Evaluation  2018">Evaluation of a Sample of RFCs Produced in 2018</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8963"/>
    <author initials="C." surname="Huitema" fullname="Christian Huitema">
      <organization>Private Octopus Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>427 Golfcourse Rd</street>
          <city>Friday Harbor</city><region>WA</region>
          <code>98250</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>huitema@huitema.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2021" month="January" />

<keyword>RFC Series</keyword>
<keyword>Independent Submissions Editor</keyword>
<keyword>documents</keyword>
<keyword>publications</keyword>
<keyword>publication delays</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document presents the author's effort to understand the delays involved
in publishing an idea in the IETF or through the Independent Stream, from the
first individual draft to the publication of the RFC.
We analyze a set of randomly chosen RFCs approved in 2018, looking for history
and delays. We also use two randomly chosen sets of RFCs published in 2008 and 1998
for comparing delays seen in 2018 to those observed 10 or 20 years ago. 
The average RFC in the 2018 sample was produced in 3 years and 4 months,
of which 2 years and 10 months were spent in the working group,
3 to 4 months for IETF consensus and IESG review, and 3 to 4 months in RFC
production. The main variation in RFC production delays comes from
the AUTH48 phase.</t>
      <t>We also measure the number of citations of the chosen RFC using Semantic
Scholar, and compare citation counts with what we know about deployment.
We show that citation counts indicate academic interest, but
correlate only loosely with deployment or usage of the specifications.
Counting web references could complement that.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>As stated on the organization's web site, "The IETF is a large open international
community of network designers, operators, vendors, and researchers concerned with
the evolution of the Internet architecture and the smooth operation of the Internet."
   The specifications
   produced by the IETF are published in the RFC series, along with
   documents from the IAB, IRTF, and Independent streams (as per RFC 8729). 

In this memo, the author attempts to understand the delays involved
in publishing an idea in the IETF or through the Independent Stream, from the first
individual draft to the publication of the RFC. This is
an individual effort, and the author's conclusions presented here are personal.
There was no attempt to seek IETF consensus.</t>
      <t>The IETF keeps records of documents and process actions
in the IETF Datatracker <xref target="TRKR" format="default"/>. 
The IETF Datatracker provides information about RFCs and drafts, from which we can
infer statistics about the production system. We can measure how
long it takes to drive a proposition from initial draft to final publication,
and how these delays can be split between working group discussions, IETF reviews,
IESG assessment, RFC Editor delays and final reviews by the authors -- or, for
Independent Stream RFCs, draft production, reviews by the Independent Submissions Editor,
conflict reviews, RFC Editor delays and final reviews. 
Tracker data is available for all RFCs, not just IETF Stream RFCs.</t>

      <t>Just measuring production delays may be misleading. If the IETF or the other streams simply rubber-stamped
draft proposals and published them, the delays would be short but the quality and
impact might suffer. We hope that most of the RFCs that are published are useful,
but we need a way to measure that usefulness. We try to do that by measuring the
number of references of the published RFCs in Semantic Scholar <xref target="SSCH" format="default"/>, and
also by asking the authors of each RFC in the sample
whether the protocols and technologies defined in the RFCs were implemented and used on
the Internet. The citations measured by the Semantic Scholar include citations in
other RFCs and in Internet-Drafts. We also measure the number of
references on the web, which provides some results but would be hard to automate.</t>
      <t>In order to limit the resources required for this study, we selected at random 20
RFCs published in 2018, as explained in <xref target="sample-selection" format="default"/>. The statistical
sampling picked both IETF Stream and Independent Stream documents.
For comparison purposes,
we also selected at random 20 RFCs published in 1998 and 20 published in 2008.
Limiting the sample to 20 out of 209 RFCs published in 2018 allows for in-depth
analysis of each RFC, but readers should be reminded that the this is a small sample.
The sample is too small to apply general statistical techniques and
quantify specific ratios, and discussions of correlation techniques would be inappropriate.
Instead, the purpose is to identify trends, spot issues, and document future
work.</t>
      <t>The information gathered for every RFC in the sample is presented in
<xref target="sample-rfc-analysis" format="default"/>. In <xref target="process-analysis" format="default"/>, we analyze the production process
and the sources of delays, comparing the 2018 sample to the selected samples for 1998
and 2018. In <xref target="citation-numbers" format="default"/>, we present citation counts for the RFCs in the samples,
and analyze whether citation counts could be used to evaluate the quality of RFCs.</t>
      <t>The measurement of delays could be automated by processing dates and
events recorded in the Datatracker. The measurement of published
RFCs could be complemented by statistics on abandoned drafts, which
would measure the efficiency of the IETF triaging process. More instrumentation would
help understanding how large delays happen during working group processes.
These potential next steps are developed in <xref target="conclusion" format="default"/>.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="methodology" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Methodology</name>
      <t>The study reported here started with a simple idea: take a sample of RFCs, and
perform an in-depth analysis of the path from the first presentation of the idea
to its publication, while also trying to access the success of the resulting
specification. This requires defining the key milestones that we want to track,
and drawing a random sample using an unbiased process.</t>
      <section anchor="milestones" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Defining the Important Milestones</name>
        <t>The IETF Datatracker records a list of events for each document processed by IETF
working groups. This has a high granularity, and also a high variability. Most documents
start life as an individual draft, are adopted by a working group, undergo a
Working Group Last Call, are submitted to the IESG, undergo an IETF Last Call
and an IESG review, get eventually approved by the IESG, and are processed
for publication by the RFC Editor, but there are exceptions. Some documents
are first submitted to one working group and then moved to another. Some documents
are published through the Independent Stream, and are submitted to the
Independent Submissions Editor instead of the IESG.</t>

        <t>In order to simplify tabulation, 
we break the period from the submission of the first
draft to the publication of the RFC into three big components:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The working group processing time, from the first draft to the start of the IETF
last call;</li>
          <li>The IETF processing time, which lasts from the beginning of the IETF last call to
the approval by the IESG, including the reviews by
various directorates;</li>
          <li>The RFC production, from approval by the IESG to publication, including
the AUTH48 reviews.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>For submissions to the Independent Stream, we don't have a working group.
We consider instead the progression of the individual draft until the
adoption by the Independent Submissions Editor (ISE) as the equivalent of the "Working Group" period, 
and the delay from adoption by the ISE until submission to the RFC Editor
as the equivalent of the IETF processing time.</t>
        <t>We measure the starting point of the process using the date of submission
of the first draft listed on that RFC page in the IETF Datatracker. In most
cases, this first draft is an individual draft that then resubmitted as a
working group draft, or maybe resubmitted with a new name as the draft was
searching for a home in an IETF working group, or before deciding for
submission on the Independent Stream.</t>
        <t>The IETF Datatracker entries for RFCs and drafts do not <em>always</em> list working group events like Working Group Last Call. 

The only intermediate event that we list
between the first draft and the submission to the IESG is the working group
adoption, for which we use the date of submission of version 00 of the
draft eventually published as RFC. We also use that date (of submission of version 00) for drafts
submitted to the Independent Stream.</t>

      </section>
      <section anchor="sample-selection" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Selecting a Random Sample of RFCs</name>
        <t>Basic production mechanisms could be evaluated by processing data from
the IETF Datatracker, but subjective data requires manual assessment of results,
which can be time-consuming. Since our resources are limited, we will only
perform this analysis for a small sample of RFCs, selected at random
from the list of RFCs approved in 2018. Specifically, we will pick
20 RFC numbers at random between:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>RFC 8307, published in January 2018, and</li>
          <li>RFC 8511, published December 2018.</li>
        </ul>

	<t>
   The list of 20 selected RFCs is: RFC 8411, RFC 8456, RFC 8446, RFC
   8355, RFC 8441, RFC 8324, RFC 8377, RFC 8498, RFC 8479, RFC 8453, RFC
   8429, RFC 8312, RFC 8492 , RFC 8378, RFC 8361, RFC 8472, RFC 8471,
   RFC 8466, RFC 8362, and RFC 8468.</t>
        <t>When evaluating delays and impact, we will compare the year 2018 to 2008 and
1998, 10 and 20 years ago. To drive this comparison, we pick 20 RFCs at random
among those published in 2008, and another 20 among those published in 1998.</t>
        <t>The list of the 20 randomly selected RFCs from 2008 is: RFC 5227, RFC 5174, RFC 5172, RFC 5354,
RFC 5195, RFC 5236, RFC 5348, RFC 5281, RFC 5186, RFC 5326, RFC 5277, RFC 5373, RFC 5404,
RFC 5329, RFC 5283, RFC 5358, RFC 5142, RFC 5271, RFC 5349, and RFC 5301.</t>
        <t>The list of the 20 randomly selected RFCs from 1998 is: RFC 2431, RFC 2381, RFC 2387, RFC 2348,
RFC 2391, RFC 2267, RFC 2312, RFC 2448, RFC 2374, RFC 2398, RFC 2283, RFC 2382, RFC 2289,
RFC 2282, RFC 2404, RFC 2449, RFC 2317, RFC 2394, RFC 2297, and RFC 2323.</t>
      </section>

<section>
<name>Conventions Used in This Document</name>
<t>The following abbreviations are used in the tables:</t>
<dl spacing="compact" indent="6">
<dt>BCP</dt>    <dd>Best Current Practice</dd>
<dt>Exp</dt>    <dd>Experimental</dd>
<dt>Info</dt>   <dd>Informational</dd>
<dt>PS</dt>     <dd>Proposed Standard</dd>
<dt>DS</dt>     <dd>Draft Standard [This maturity level was retired by RFC 6410.]</dd>
</dl>

<t>In addition, Status is as defined in RFC 2026, and 
Stream is as defined in RFC 8729.</t>
</section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sample-rfc-analysis" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Analysis of 20 Selected RFCs</name>
      <t>We review each of the RFCs listed in <xref target="sample-selection" format="default"/> for the year 2018, trying 
both to answer the known questions and to gather insight for further analyses.
In many cases, the analysis of the data is complemented by direct feedback
from the RFC authors.</t>

      <section anchor="section" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8411</name>
        <t>"IANA Registration for the Cryptographic Algorithm Object Identifier Range" <xref target="RFC8411" format="default"/>:</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (5 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>4 individual drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2017-05-08</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-10-09</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2017-12-28</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-02-26 (draft 03)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-04-20</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-07-17</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-08-06</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>create table</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This RFC was published from the individual draft, which was not resubmitted
as a working group draft.</t>
        <t>The draft underwent minor copy editing before publication.</t>
        <t>Some but not all of the long delay in AUTH48 is due to clustering with <xref target="RFC8410" format="default"/>.
MISSREF state concluded on 2018-05-09 and the document re-entered AUTH48 at
once. AUTH48 lasted over two months after that. (For state definitions, see 
<eref brackets="angle" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/about/queue/#state_def"/>.)</t>
        <t>The time after AUTH48 and before publication (3 weeks) partly
overlaps with travel for IETF 102 and is partly due to coordinating the
cluster.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8456</name>
        <t>"Benchmarking Methodology for Software-Defined Networking (SDN) 
Controller Performance" <xref target="RFC8456" format="default"/>:</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (64 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>2 individual drafts; 9 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2015-03-23</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2015-10-18</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-01-19</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-02-27</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-05-25</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-08-31</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-10-16</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-10-30</dd>
 </dl>

<t>
   The draft underwent extensive copy editing, covering use of
   articles, syntax, and word choice. The changes are enough to cause pagination differences. The "diff" tool marks pretty
much every page as changed. Some diagrams see change in protocol elements like message names.</t>
        <t>According to the author, the experience of producing this document mirrors a typical one in the
Benchmarking Methodologies Working Group (BMWG). There were multiple authors in multiple time
zones, which slowed down the AUTH48 process somewhat, although the AUTH48 delay of 46 days is only
a bit longer than the average draft.</t>
        <t>The RFC was part of cluster with <xref target="RFC8455" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>BMWG publishes Informational RFCs centered around benchmarking,
and the methodologies in RFC 8456 have been implemented in benchmarking products.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8446</name>
        <t>"The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.3" <xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/>, as the title
indicates, defines the new version of the TLS protocol. From the IETF Datatracker, we extract
the following:</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (160 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>29 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2014-04-17</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-02-15</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-03-02</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-03-21 (draft 28)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-06-14</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-08-10</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-08-10</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This draft started as a WG effort.</t>
        <t>The RFC was a major effort in the IETF. Working group participants developed and tested
several implementations. Researchers analyzed the specifications and performed 
formal verifications. Deployment tests outlined issues that caused extra work
when the specification was almost ready. This complexity largely explains the
time spent in the working group.</t>
        <t>Comparing the final draft to the published version, we find relatively light copy
editing. It includes explaining acronyms on first use, clarifying some definitions 
standardizing punctuation and capitalization, and spelling out some numbers in text.
This generally fall in the category of "style", although some of the clarifications
go into message definitions. However, that simple analysis does not explain why
the AUTH48 phase took almost two months.</t>
        <t>This document's AUTH48 process was part of the "GitHub experiment", which tried to
use GitHub pull requests to track the AUTH48 changes and review comments. The
RFC Production Center (RPC) staff had to learn using GitHub for that process, and this required more work
than the usual RFC. The author and AD thoroughly reviewed each proposed 
edit, accepting some and rejecting some. The concern there was that
any change in a complex specification might affect a protocol that was extensively
reviewed in the working group, but of course these reviews added time to the
AUTH48 delays.</t>
        <t>There are 21 implementations listed
in the Wiki of the TLS 1.3 project <xref target="TLS13IMP" format="default"/>. It has been deployed on major browsers, and
is already used in a large fraction of TLS connections.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8355</name>
        <t>"Resiliency Use Cases in Source Packet Routing in Networking (SPRING) Networks" <xref target="RFC8355" format="default"/> is an Informational RFC.
It originated from an informational use-case draft; it was mostly used for the BOF creating the WG, and then to
drive initial work and evolutions from the WG.</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (13 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>2 individual drafts; 13 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2014-01-31</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2014-05-13</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-04-20</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2017-05-04 (draft 09)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2017-12-19 (draft 12)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-03-12</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-03-27</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-03-28</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>Minor set of copy edits, mostly for style.</t>
        <t>No implementation of the RFC itself, but the technology behind it (such as
Segment Routing Architecture <xref target="RFC8402"/> and TI-LFA <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-segment-routing-ti-lfa"/>) is widely implemented
and deployment is ongoing.</t>
        <t>According to participants in the discussion, the process of adoption of the source packet routing
standards was very contentious. The establishment of consensus at both the working group level
and the IETF level was difficult and time-consuming.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-4" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8441</name>
        <t>"Bootstrapping WebSockets with HTTP/2" <xref target="RFC8441" format="default"/></t>

<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (8 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>3 individual drafts; 8 WG drafts; Updates RFC 6455</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2017-10-15</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2017-12-19</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-05-07 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-05-29 (draft 06)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-06-18 (draft 07)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-08-13</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-09-15</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-09-18</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>table entries</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This RFC defines the support of WebSockets in HTTP/2, which is different
from the mechanism defined for HTTP/1.1 in <xref target="RFC6455" format="default"/>. The process was
relatively straightforward, involving the usual type of discussions, some
on details and some on important points.</t>
        <t>Comparing the final draft and published RFC shows a minor set of copy edits,
mostly for style. However, the author recalls a painful process. The RFC
includes many charts and graphs that were very difficult to format
correctly in the author's production process that involved conversions
from markdown to XML, and then from XML to text. The author had to
get substantial help from the RFC Editor.</t>
        <t>There are several implementations, including Firefox and Chrome,
making RFC 8441 a very successful specification.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="analyse-8324" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8324</name>
        <t>"DNS Privacy, Authorization, Special Uses, Encoding, Characters, Matching, and Root Structure:
Time for Another Look?" <xref target="RFC8324" format="default"/>. This is an opinion piece on DNS development,
published on the Independent Stream.</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (29 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>5 individual drafts; Independent Stream</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2017-06-02</dd>
   <dt>ISE review start:</dt>  <dd>2017-07-10 (draft 03)</dd>
   <dt>IETF conflict review start:</dt> <dd>2017-10-29</dd>
   <dt>Approved:</dt>         <dd>2017-12-18 (draft 04)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-01-29 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-02-26</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-02-27</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This RFC took only 9 months from first draft to publication, which is the shortest in
the 2018 sample set. In part, this is because the text was privately circulated
and reviewed by the ISE's selected experts before the first draft was published.
The nature of the document is
another reason for the short delay. It is an opinion piece and does not require
the same type of consensus building and reviews as a protocol specification.</t>
        <t>Comparing the final draft and the published version shows only minor copy edits, mostly
for style. According to the author, this is because he knows how to write in RFC
style with the result that his documents often need a minimum of editing. He also
makes sure that the document on which the
RFC Production Center starts working already has changes discussed
and approved during Last Call and IESG review incorporated,
rather than expecting the Production Center to operate off of
notes about changes to be made.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-5" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8377</name>
        <t>"Transparent Interconnection of Lots of Links (TRILL): Multi-Topology" <xref target="RFC8377" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (20 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>3 individual drafts; 7 WG drafts; Updates RFCs 6325 and 7177</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2013-09-03</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2015-09-01</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-02-19 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-03-06 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-03-12 (draft 06)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-04-20 (draft 06)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-07-31</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-07-31</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>table entries</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>Minor set of copy edits, mostly for style, also clarity.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-6" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8498</name>
        <t>"A P-Served-User Header Field Parameter for an Originating Call Diversion (CDIV)
Session Case in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)" <xref target="RFC8498" format="default"/>.</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (15 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>5 individual drafts; 9 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2016-03-21</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2017-05-15</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-10-12 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-11-28 (draft 07)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-12-11 (draft 08)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2019-01-28</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2019-02-13</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2019-02-14</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>table rows added.</dd>
 </dl>


        <t>Copy edits for style, but also clarification of ambiguous sentences.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-7" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8479</name>
        <t>"Storing Validation Parameters in PKCS#8" <xref target="RFC8479" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (8 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>5 individual drafts; Independent Stream</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2017-08-08</dd>
   <dt>ISE review start:</dt>  <dd>2018-12-10 (draft 00)</dd>
   <dt>IETF conflict review start:</dt> <dd>2018-03-29</dd>
   <dt>Approved:</dt>         <dd>2018-08-20 (draft 03)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-09-20 (draft 04)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-09-25</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-09-26</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>The goal of the draft was to document what the
gnutls implementation was using for storing provably generated RSA keys.
This is a short RFC that was published relatively quickly, although
discussion between the author, the Independent Submissions Editor, and the
IESG lasted several months. In the initial conflict review, the IESG asked
the ISE to not publish this document before IETF working groups had
an opportunity to pick up the work. The author met that requirement by
a presentation to the SECDISPATCH WG during IETF 102. Since no WG was
interested in picking up the work, the document progressed on the
Independent Stream.</t>
        <t>Very minor set of copy edits, moving some references from normative to informative.</t>
        <t>The author is not aware of other implementations than gnutls relying on this RFC.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-8" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8453</name>
        <t>"Framework for Abstraction and Control of TE Networks (ACTN)" <xref target="RFC8453" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (42 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>3 individual drafts; 16 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2015-06-15</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2016-07-15</dd>
   <dt>Out of WG:</dt>      <dd>2018-01-26 (draft 11)</dd>
   <dt>Expert review requested:</dt>      <dd>2018-02-13</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-04-16 (draft 13)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-05-16 (draft 14)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-06-01 (draft 15)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-08-13</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-08-20</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-08-23</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>table rows added.</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>Minor copy editing.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-9" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8429</name>
        <t>"Deprecate Triple-DES (3DES) and RC4 in Kerberos" <xref target="RFC8429" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>BCP (10 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>6 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2017-05-01</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-07-16 (draft 03)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2017-08-18 (draft 04)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-05-25 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-07-24</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-10-31</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-10-31</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>table rows added.</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This draft started as a working group effort.</t>
        <t>This RFC recommends deprecating two encryption algorithms that are now considered
obsolete and possibly broken. The document was sent back to the WG after the first Last Call,
edited, and then there was a second Last Call. The delay from first draft to Working Group
Last Call was relatively short, but the number may be misleading. The initial draft was a
replacement of a similar draft in the KITTEN Working Group, which stagnated for some time
before the CURDLE Working Group took up the work. 
The deprecation of RC4 was somewhat contentious, but the WG had already debated this
prior to the production of this draft, and the draft was not delayed by this debate.</t>
        <t>Most of the 280 days between IETF LC and IESG approval were
because the IESG had to talk about whether this document should obsolete RFC 4757 or
move it to Historic status, and no one was really actively pushing that
discussion for a while.</t>
        <t>The 99 days in AUTH48 are mostly because one of the authors was a sitting AD, and those
duties ended up taking precedence over reviewing this document.</t>
        <t>Minor copy editing, for style.</t>
        <t>The implementation of the draft would be the actual removal of support for 3DES and RC4
in major implementations. This is happening, but very slowly.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-10" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8312</name>
        <t>"CUBIC for Fast Long-Distance Networks" <xref target="RFC8312" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (18 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>2 individual drafts; 8 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2014-09-01</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2015-06-08</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-09-18 (draft 06)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2017-10-04</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2017-11-14 (draft 07)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-01-08</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-02-07</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-02-07</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>table rows added.</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>Minor copy editing, for style.</t>
        <t>The TCP congestion control algorithm Cubic was first defined in 2005, was implemented
in Linux soon after, and was implemented in major OSes after that. After some debates
from 2015 to 2015, the TCPM Working Group adopted the draft, with a goal of
documenting Cubic in the RFC Series. According to the authors, this was not
a high-priority effort, as Cubic was already implemented in multiple OSes
and documented in research papers. At some point, only one of the authors
was actively working on the draft. This may explain why another two years was spent
progressing the draft after adoption by the WG.</t>
        <t>The RFC publication may or may not have triggered further implementations. On
the other hand, several OSes picked up bug fixes from the draft and the RFC.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-11" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8492</name>
        <t>"Secure Password Ciphersuites for Transport Layer Security (TLS)" <xref target="RFC8492" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (40 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>10 individual drafts; 8 WG drafts; Independent Stream</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2012-09-07</dd>
   <dt>Targeted to ISE:</dt>  <dd>2016-08-05</dd>
   <dt>ISE review start:</dt>  <dd>2017-05-10 (draft 01)</dd>
   <dt>IETF conflict review start:</dt> <dd>2017-09-04</dd>
   <dt>Approved:</dt>         <dd>2017-10-29 (draft 02)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-10-19 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2019-02-19</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2019-02-21</dd>
   <dt>IANA action:</dt>      <dd>table rows added.</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This RFC has a complex history. The first individual draft was submitted to the
TLS Working Group on September 7, 2012. It progressed there, and was adopted
by the WG after 3 revisions. There were then 8 revisions in the TLS WG,
until the WG decided to not progress it. 

The draft was parked in 2013 by
the WG chairs after failing to get consensus in WG Last Call. The AD finally
pulled the plug in 2016, and the draft was then resubmitted to the ISE.</t>
        <t>At that point, the author was busy and was treating this RFC with a 
low priority because, in his words, it would not be a "real RFC".
There were problems with the draft that only came up late. In particular,
it had to wait for a change in registry policy that only came about with
the publication of TLS 1.3, which caused the draft to be published
after RFC 8446, and also required adding references to TLS 1.3.
The author also got a very late comment while in AUTH48 that 
caused some rewriting. Finally, there was some IANA issue with the extension
registry where a similar extension was added by someone else. The draft
was changed to just use it.</t>
        <t>Changes in AUTH48 include adding a reference to TLS 1.3, copy editing for style,
some added requirements, added paragraphs, and changes in algorithms specification.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-12" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8378</name>
        <t>"Signal-Free Locator/ID Separation Protocol (LISP) Multicast" <xref target="RFC8378" format="default"/> is
an Experimental RFC, defining how to implement Multicast in the LISP
architecture.</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Experimental (21 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>5 individual drafts; 10 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2014-02-28</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2015-12-21</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-02-13 (draft 07)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-02-28 (draft 08)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-03-12 (draft 09)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-04-23</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-05-02</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-05-02</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>Preparing the RFC took more than 4 years. According to the authors, they were
not aggressively pushing it and just let the working group process decide to pace
it. They also did implementations during that time.</t>
        <t>Minor copy editing, for style.</t>
        <t>The RFC was implemented by lispers.net and Cisco,
and it was used in doing IPv6 multicast over IPv4 unicast/multicast at the Olympics
in PyeungChang. The plan is to work on a Proposed Standard once the
experiment concludes.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-13" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8361</name>
        <t>"Transparent Interconnection of Lots of Links (TRILL):
Centralized Replication for Active-Active Broadcast,
Unknown Unicast, and Multicast (BUM) Traffic" <xref target="RFC8361" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (17 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>3 individual drafts; 14 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2013-11-12</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2014-12-16</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-11-28 (draft 10)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2017-12-18 (draft 11)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-01-29 (draft 13)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-03-09</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-04-09</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-04-12</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>According to the authors, the long delays in producing this RFC were
due to a slow uptake of the technology in the industry.</t>
        <t>Minor copy editing, for style.</t>
        <t>There was at least one partial implementation.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-14" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8472</name>
        <t>"Transport Layer Security (TLS) Extension for Token Binding Protocol Negotiation" <xref target="RFC8472" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (8 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>1 individual draft; 15 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2015-05-29</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2015-09-11</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-11-13 (draft 10)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-03-19</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-07-20 (draft 14)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-09-17</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-09-25</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-10-08</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This is a pretty simple document, but it took over 3 years from individual draft to RFC. According to
the authors,the biggest setbacks occurred at the start: it took a while to find a home for this draft.
It was presented in the TLS WG (because it's a TLS extension) and UTA WG (because it has to do with
applications using TLS). Then the ADs determined that a new WG was needed, so the authors had to work
through the WG creation process, including running a BOF.</t>
        <t>Minor copy editing, for style, with the addition of a reference to TLS 1.3.</t>
        <t>Perhaps partially due to the delays, some of the implementers lost interest in supporting this RFC.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-15" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8471</name>
        <t>"The Token Binding Protocol Version 1.0" <xref target="RFC8471" format="default"/></t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (18 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>1 individual draft; 19 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2014-10-13</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2015-03-15</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-11-13 (draft 16)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-03-19</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-07-20 (draft 19)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-09-17</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-09-25</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-10-08</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>This document presents a Token Binding Protocol for TLS. 
   We can notice a
   period of 5 months before adoption of the draft by the WG.  That
   explains in part the overall time of almost 4 years from first draft
   to publication.
	</t>
        <t>Minor copy editing, for style.</t>
        <t>The web references indicate adoption in multiple development projects.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-16" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8466</name>
        <t>"A YANG Data Model for Layer 2 Virtual Private Network (L2VPN) Service Delivery" <xref target="RFC8466" format="default"/></t>

<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (158 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>5 individual drafts; 11 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2016-09-01</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2017-02-26</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-02-21 (draft 07)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-03-14 (draft 08)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-06-25 (draft 10)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-09-17</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-10-09</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-10-12</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>Copy editing for style and clarity, with also corrections to the YANG model.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-17" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8362</name>
        <t>"OSPFv3 Link State Advertisement (LSA) Extensibility" <xref target="RFC8362" format="default"/> is a major extension to the
OSPF protocol. It makes OSPFv3 fully extensible.</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Proposed Standard (33 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>4 individual drafts; 24 WG drafts</dd>                          
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2013-02-17</dd>                                                 
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2013-10-15</dd>                                                 
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2017-12-19 (draft 19)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-01-18 (draft 20)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-01-29 (draft 23)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-03-19</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-03-30</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-04-03</dd>
</dl>
        <t>The specification was first submitted as an individual draft in the IPv6 WG, then moved to the OSPF WG.
The long delay of producing this RFC is due to the complexity of the problem,
and the need to wait for implementations. It is a very important change to OSPF
that makes OSPFv3 fully extensible. Since it was a non-backward compatible change,
the developers started out with some very complex migration scenarios but ended up
with either legacy or extended OSPFv3 LSAs within an OSPFv3 routing domain. The initial attempts
to have a hybrid mode of operation with both legacy and extended LSAs also delayed implementation
due to the complexity.</t>
        <t>Copy editing for style and clarity.</t>
        <t>This specification either was or will be implemented by all the router vendors.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-18" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC 8468</name>
        <t>"IPv4, IPv6, and IPv4-IPv6 Coexistence: Updates for the IP
Performance Metrics (IPPM) Framework" <xref target="RFC8468" format="default"/>.</t>
<dl indent="20" spacing="compact">
   <dt>Status (Length):</dt>  <dd>Informational (15 pages)</dd>
   <dt>Overview:</dt>         <dd>3 individual drafts; 7 WG drafts</dd>
   <dt>First draft:</dt>      <dd>2015-08-06</dd>
   <dt>WG adoption:</dt>      <dd>2016-07-04</dd>
   <dt>Last Call start:</dt>  <dd>2018-04-11 (draft 04)</dd>
   <dt>IESG eval. start:</dt> <dd>2018-05-24 (draft 05)</dd>
   <dt>IESG approved:</dt>    <dd>2018-07-10 (draft 06)</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 start:</dt>     <dd>2018-09-13</dd>
   <dt>AUTH48 complete:</dt>  <dd>2018-11-05</dd>
   <dt>Published:</dt>        <dd>2018-11-14</dd>
 </dl>

        <t>RFC 8468 was somehow special in that
there was not a technical reason or interest that triggered it, but
rather a formal requirement.
While writing RFC  7312, the IP Performance
Metrics (IPPM) Working Group realized that RFC 2330, the IP Performance
Metrics Framework supported IPv4 only
and explicitly excluded support for IPv6. Nevertheless, people used
the metrics that were defined on top of RFC 2330 (and, therefore, IPv4
only) for IPv6, too. Although the IPPM WG agreed that the work was needed, the
interest of IPPM attendees in progressing (and reading/reviewing) the
IPv6 draft was limited. Resolving the IPv6 technical part was
straightforward, but subsequently some people asked for a broader scope
(topics like header compression, 6LoWPAN, etc.), and it took some time to
figure out and later on convince people that these topics are out of scope.
The group also had to resolve contentious topics, for example, how to
measure the processing of IPv6 extension headers, which is sometimes nonstandard.</t>
        <t>The time in AUTH48 state for this document was longer than average. According to the authors,
the main reasons include:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Workload and travel caused by busy work periods of all coauthors</li>
          <li>Time zone difference between coauthors and editor (at least US,
	  Europe, and India, not considering travel)</li>
	  <li>
      RFC Production Center proposed and committed some unacceptable
      modifications that needed to be reverted
	  </li>
          <li>Lengthy discussions on a new document title (required high effort and
took a long time, in particular reaching consensus between coauthors
and editor was time-consuming and involved the AD)</li>
          <li>RFC Production Center correctly identified some nits (obsoleted personal websites of
coauthors) and coauthors attempting to fix them.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The differences between the final draft and the published RFC show copy editing for style
and clarity, but do not account for the back and forth between authors and editors
mentioned by the authors.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="process-analysis" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Analysis of Process and Delays</name>
      <t>We examine the 20 RFCs in the sample, measuring various characteristics such
as delay and citation counts, in an attempt to identify patterns in the
IETF processes.</t>
      <section anchor="first-draft-to-rfc-delays" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Delays from First Draft to RFC</name>
        <t>We look at the distribution of delays between the submission of the first
draft and the publication of the RFC, using the three milestones defined
in <xref target="milestones" format="default"/>: processing time in the working group, IETF processing time,
and RFC production time. The following table
shows the number of days in each phase for the 20 RFCs in the sample:</t>

        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="right">RFC</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Pages</th>
              <th align="right">Overall</th>
              <th align="right">WG</th>
              <th align="right">IETF</th>
              <th align="right">Edit</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8411</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">455</td>
              <td align="right">154</td>
              <td align="right">140</td>
              <td align="right">161</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8456</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">64</td>
              <td align="right">1317</td>
              <td align="right">1033</td>
              <td align="right">126</td>
              <td align="right">158</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8446</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">160</td>
              <td align="right">1576</td>
              <td align="right">1400</td>
              <td align="right">34</td>
              <td align="right">142</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8355</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">13</td>
              <td align="right">1517</td>
              <td align="right">1175</td>
              <td align="right">243</td>
              <td align="right">99</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8441</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">327</td>
              <td align="right">204</td>
              <td align="right">31</td>
              <td align="right">92</td>
            </tr>


            <tr>
              <td align="right">8324</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">29</td>
              <td align="right">270</td>
              <td align="right">38</td>
              <td align="right">161</td>
              <td align="right">71</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8377</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">1792</td>
              <td align="right">1630</td>
              <td align="right">21</td>
              <td align="right">141</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8498</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
              <td align="right">1059</td>
              <td align="right">935</td>
              <td align="right">59</td>
              <td align="right">65</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8479</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">414</td>
              <td align="right">233</td>
              <td align="right">144</td>
              <td align="right">37</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8453</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">42</td>
              <td align="right">1165</td>
              <td align="right">1036</td>
              <td align="right">46</td>
              <td align="right">83</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8429</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">548</td>
              <td align="right">76</td>
              <td align="right">313</td>
              <td align="right">159</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">18</td>
              <td align="right">1214</td>
              <td align="right">1113</td>
              <td align="right">16</td>
              <td align="right">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8492</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">40</td>
              <td align="right">2358</td>
              <td align="right">1706</td>
              <td align="right">172</td>
              <td align="right">480</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8378</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">21</td>
              <td align="right">1524</td>
              <td align="right">1446</td>
              <td align="right">27</td>
              <td align="right">51</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8361</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">17</td>
              <td align="right">1612</td>
              <td align="right">1477</td>
              <td align="right">62</td>
              <td align="right">73</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8472</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">1228</td>
              <td align="right">899</td>
              <td align="right">249</td>
              <td align="right">80</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8471</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">18</td>
              <td align="right">1228</td>
              <td align="right">899</td>
              <td align="right">249</td>
              <td align="right">80</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8466</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">158</td>
              <td align="right">771</td>
              <td align="right">538</td>
              <td align="right">124</td>
              <td align="right">109</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8362</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">33</td>
              <td align="right">1871</td>
              <td align="right">1766</td>
              <td align="right">41</td>
              <td align="right">64</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8468</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
              <td align="right">1196</td>
              <td align="right">979</td>
              <td align="right">90</td>
              <td align="right">127</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" align="left">average</td>
              <td align="right">35</td>
              <td align="right">1172</td>
              <td align="right">948</td>
              <td align="right">117</td>
              <td align="right">118</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" align="left">average (not ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">36</td>
              <td align="right">1200</td>
              <td align="right">999</td>
              <td align="right">110</td>
              <td align="right">104</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

        <t>The average delay from first draft to publication is about 3 years and 3 months, but this
varies widely. Excluding the RFCs from the Independent Stream, the average
delay from start to finish is 3 years and 4 months, of which on average
2 years and 9 months are spent getting consensus in the working group,
and 3 to 4 months each for IETF consensus and for RFC production.</t>
        <t>The longest delay is found for <xref target="RFC8492" format="default"/>, 6.5 years from start to finish.
This is however a very special case -- a draft that was prepared for
the TLS Working Group and failed to reach consensus. After that, it was
resubmitted to the ISE, and incurred atypical production delays.</t>
        <t>On average, we see that 80% of the delay is incurred in WG processing,
10% in IETF review, and 10% for edition and publication.</t>
        <t>For IETF Stream RFCs, it appears that the delays for Informational documents
are slightly shorter than those for protocol specifications, maybe six months
shorter on average. However, there are lots of differences between
individual documents. The delays range from less than a year to more than 5 years for
protocol specifications, and from a year and 3 months to a bit more than 4 years for
Informational documents.</t>
        <t>We can compare the delays in the 2018 samples to those observed 10 years ago and 20 years
before:</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC (2008)</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Pages</th>
              <th align="right">Delay</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5326</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">54</td>
              <td align="right">1584</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5348</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">58</td>
              <td align="right">823</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5281</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">51</td>
              <td align="right">1308</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5354</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">23</td>
              <td align="right">2315</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5227</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">21</td>
              <td align="right">2434</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5329</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">12</td>
              <td align="right">1980</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5277</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">35</td>
              <td align="right">912</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5236</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">26</td>
              <td align="right">1947</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5358</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">884</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5271</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">22</td>
              <td align="right">1066</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5195</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">974</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5283</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">12</td>
              <td align="right">1096</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5186</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">6</td>
              <td align="right">2253</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5142</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">13</td>
              <td align="right">1005</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5373</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">24</td>
              <td align="right">1249</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5404</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">27</td>
              <td align="right">214</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5172</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">305</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5349</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">1096</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5301</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">6</td>
              <td align="right">396</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5174</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">427</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC (1998)</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Pages</th>
              <th align="right">Delay</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2289</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">25</td>
              <td align="right">396</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2267</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">unknown</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2317</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">485</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2404</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">488</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2374</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">12</td>
              <td align="right">289</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2449</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">19</td>
              <td align="right">273</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2283</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">9</td>
              <td align="right">153</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2394</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">6</td>
              <td align="right">365</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2348</td>
              <td align="left">DS</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">699</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2382</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">30</td>
              <td align="right">396</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2297</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">109</td>
              <td align="right">28</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2381</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">43</td>
              <td align="right">699</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">20</td>
              <td align="right">365</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2387</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">122</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2398</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
              <td align="right">396</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2391</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">122</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2431</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">457</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2282</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">14</td>
              <td align="right">215</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2323</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">unknown</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2448</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">92</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>We can compare the median delay, and the delays observed by the fastest and
slowest quartiles in the three years:</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Year</th>
              <th align="right">Fastest 25%</th>
              <th align="right">Median</th>
              <th align="right">Slowest 25%</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2018</td>
              <td align="right">715</td>
              <td align="right">1221</td>
              <td align="right">1537</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2008</td>
              <td align="right">869</td>
              <td align="right">1081</td>
              <td align="right">1675</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">1998</td>
              <td align="right">169</td>
              <td align="right">365</td>
              <td align="right">442</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>The IETF takes three to four times more to produce an RFC in 2018
than it did in 1998, but about the same time as it did in 2008.
We can get a rough estimate of how this translates in terms of
"level of attention" per RFC by comparing the number of participants
in the IETF meetings of 2018, 2008, and 1998 <xref target="IETFCOUNT" format="default"/> to the number of RFCs
published these years <xref target="RFCYEAR" format="default"/>.</t>

        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Year</th>
              <th align="left">Number of RFCs</th>
              <th align="right">Spring P.</th>
              <th align="right">Summer P.</th>
              <th align="right">Fall P.</th>
              <th align="right">Average P.</th>
              <th align="left">Attendees/RFC</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2018</td>
              <td align="right">208</td>
              <td align="right">1235</td>
              <td align="right">1078</td>
              <td align="right">879</td>
              <td align="right">1064</td>
              <td align="left">5.1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2008</td>
              <td align="right">290</td>
              <td align="right">1128</td>
              <td align="right">1181</td>
              <td align="right">962</td>
              <td align="right">1090</td>
              <td align="left">3.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">1998</td>
              <td align="right">234</td>
              <td align="right">1775</td>
              <td align="right">2106</td>
              <td align="right">1705</td>
              <td align="right">1862</td>
              <td align="left">8.0</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>The last column in the table provides the ratio of average number
of participants to the number of RFCs published. If the IETF were a centralized
organization, and if all participants and documents were equivalent, this
ratio would be the number of participants dedicated to produce an RFC
on a given year. This is of course a completely abstract figure because
none of the hypotheses above are true, but it still gives a vague
indication of the "level of attention" applied to documents. We see
that this ratio has increased from 2008 to 2018, as the number of
participants was about the same for these two years but the number of
published RFCs decreased. However, this ratio was much higher in 1998.
The IETF had many more participants, and there were probably
many more eyes available to review any given draft. If we applied the
ratios of 1998, the IETF would be producing 119 documents in 2018
instead of 208.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="working-group-processing-time" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Working Group Processing Time</name>
        <t>The largest part of the delays is spent in the working groups, before
the draft is submitted to the IESG for IETF review. As mentioned in
<xref target="milestones" format="default"/>, the only intermediate milestone that we can extract
from the IETF Datatracker is the date at which the document was
adopted by the working group, or targeted for independent submission.
The breakdown of the delays for the documents in our sample is:</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">WG</th>
              <th align="right">Until adoption</th>
              <th align="right">After adoption</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8411</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">154</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">154</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8456</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1033</td>
              <td align="right">209</td>
              <td align="right">824</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8446</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1400</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">1400</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8355</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1175</td>
              <td align="right">102</td>
              <td align="right">1073</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8441</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">204</td>
              <td align="right">65</td>
              <td align="right">139</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8324</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">38</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">38</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8377</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1630</td>
              <td align="right">728</td>
              <td align="right">902</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8498</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">935</td>
              <td align="right">420</td>
              <td align="right">515</td>
            </tr>


            <tr>
              <td align="left">8479</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">233</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">233</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8453</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1036</td>
              <td align="right">396</td>
              <td align="right">640</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8429</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">76</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">76</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1113</td>
              <td align="right">280</td>
              <td align="right">833</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8492</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">1706</td>
              <td align="right">1428</td>
              <td align="right">278</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8378</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">1446</td>
              <td align="right">661</td>
              <td align="right">785</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8361</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1477</td>
              <td align="right">399</td>
              <td align="right">1078</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8472</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">899</td>
              <td align="right">105</td>
              <td align="right">794</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8471</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1127</td>
              <td align="right">153</td>
              <td align="right">794</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8466</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">538</td>
              <td align="right">178</td>
              <td align="right">360</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8362</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1766</td>
              <td align="right">240</td>
              <td align="right">1526</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8468</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">979</td>
              <td align="right">333</td>
              <td align="right">646</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="2">Average</td>
              <td align="right">948</td>
              <td align="right">285</td>
              <td align="right">663</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>The time before working group adoption averages to a bit more than 9 months,
compared to 1 year and almost 10 months for processing time after adoption.
We see that RFC 8492 stands out, with long delays spent attempting publication through
a working group before submission to the Independent Submissions Editor. If we remove RFC
8492 from the list, the average time until adoption drops to just over 7 months,
and becomes just 25% of the total processing time in the WG.</t>
        <t>There are a few
documents that started immediately as working group efforts, or were immediately targeted
for publication in the Independent Stream. Those documents tend to see short processing times,
with the exception of RFC 8446 on which the TLS Working Group spent a long time working.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="preparation-and-publication-delays" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Preparation and Publication Delays</name>

<!-- [rfced] For the ease of the reader, we have added "referred to as" 
in parentheses to indicate the corresponding columns in Table 7. 
Please let us know if you prefer otherwise.

Current:
   *  the delay from submission to the RFC Editor to beginning of
      AUTH48, during which the document is prepared (referred to as "RFC
      edit" below);

   *  the AUTH48 delay, during which authors review and eventually
      approve the changes proposed by the editors (referred to as
      "AUTH48" below);

   *  the publication delay, from final agreement by authors and editors
      to actual publication (referred to as "RFC Pub" below).
-->
        <t>The preparation and publication delays include three components:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>the delay from submission to the RFC Editor to beginning of AUTH48, during 
which the document is prepared (referred to as "RFC edit" below);</li>
          <li>the AUTH48 delay, during which authors review and eventually approve the
changes proposed by the editors (referred to as "AUTH48" below);</li>
          <li>the publication delay, from final agreement by authors and editors to
actual publication (referred to as "RFC Pub" below).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The breakdown of the publication delays for each RFC is shown in the
following table.</t>

        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="right">RFC</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Pages</th>
              <th align="right">RFC edit</th>
              <th align="right">AUTH48</th>
              <th align="right">RFC Pub</th>
              <th align="right">Edit (total)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8411</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">53</td>
              <td align="right">88</td>
              <td align="right">20</td>
              <td align="right">161</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8456</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">64</td>
              <td align="right">98</td>
              <td align="right">46</td>
              <td align="right">14</td>
              <td align="right">158</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8446</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">160</td>
              <td align="right">85</td>
              <td align="right">57</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">142</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8355</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">13</td>
              <td align="right">83</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">99</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8441</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">56</td>
              <td align="right">33</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">92</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8324</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">29</td>
              <td align="right">42</td>
              <td align="right">28</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">71</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8377</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">39</td>
              <td align="right">102</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">141</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8498</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
              <td align="right">48</td>
              <td align="right">16</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">65</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8479</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">31</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">37</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8453</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">42</td>
              <td align="right">73</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">83</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8429</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">10</td>
              <td align="right">60</td>
              <td align="right">99</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">159</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">18</td>
              <td align="right">55</td>
              <td align="right">28</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8492</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">40</td>
              <td align="right">355</td>
              <td align="right">123</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">480</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8378</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">21</td>
              <td align="right">42</td>
              <td align="right">9</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">51</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8361</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">17</td>
              <td align="right">39</td>
              <td align="right">31</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">73</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8472</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">59</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">13</td>
              <td align="right">80</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8471</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">18</td>
              <td align="right">59</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">13</td>
              <td align="right">80</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8466</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">158</td>
              <td align="right">84</td>
              <td align="right">22</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">109</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8362</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">33</td>
              <td align="right">49</td>
              <td align="right">11</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">64</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8468</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
              <td align="right">65</td>
              <td align="right">53</td>
              <td align="right">9</td>
              <td align="right">127</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" align="left">Average</td>
              <td align="right"></td>
              <td align="right">74</td>
              <td align="right">39</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">118</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="2" align="left">Average (without 8492)</td>
              <td align="right"></td>
              <td align="right">59</td>
              <td align="right">35</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">99</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>On average, the total delay appears to be about four months, but the
average is skewed by the extreme values encountered for <xref target="RFC8492" format="default"/>. If we
exclude that RFC from the computations, the average delay drops to a just a bit
more than 3 months: about 2 months for the preparation, a bit more than one
month for the AUTH48 phase, and 5 days for the publishing.</t>
        <t>Of course, these delays vary from RFC to RFC. To try explain the causes of the
delay, we compute the correlation factor between the observed delays and several
plausible explanation factors:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>the number of pages in the document,</li>
          <li>the amount of copy editing, as discussed in <xref target="copy-editing" format="default"/>,</li>
          <li>whether or not IANA actions were required,</li>
          <li>the number of authors,</li>
          <li>the number of draft revisions,</li>
          <li>the working group delay.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>We find the following values:</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Correlation</th>
              <th align="right">RFC edit</th>
              <th align="right">AUTH48</th>
              <th align="right">Edit(total)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Number of pages</td>
              <td align="right">0.50</td>
              <td align="right">-0.04</td>
              <td align="right">0.21</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Copy-Edit</td>
              <td align="right">0.42</td>
              <td align="right">0.24</td>
              <td align="right">0.45</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">IANA</td>
              <td align="right">-0.14</td>
              <td align="right">-0.21</td>
              <td align="right">0.12</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Number of authors</td>
              <td align="right">0.39</td>
              <td align="right">-0.07</td>
              <td align="right">0.18</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Number of drafts</td>
              <td align="right">0.18</td>
              <td align="right">-0.33</td>
              <td align="right">-0.19</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">WG delay</td>
              <td align="right">0.03</td>
              <td align="right">-0.16</td>
              <td align="right">-0.15</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>We see some plausible explanations for the production delay. It will be somewhat longer for
longer documents or for documents that require a lot of copy editing (see <xref target="copy-editing" format="default"/>).
Somewhat surprisingly, it also tends to increase with the number of authors. It does
not appear significantly correlated with the presence or absence of IANA action.</t>
        <t>The analysis of RFC 8324 in <xref target="analyse-8324" format="default"/> explains its short
editing delays by the experience of the author. This makes sense: if a document
needs less editing, the editing delays would be shorter. This is partially
confirmed by the relation between the amount of copy editing and the
publication delay.</t>
        <t>We see fewer plausible explanations for the AUTH48 delays. These delays
vary much more than the preparation
delay, with a standard deviation of 20 days for AUTH48 versus 10 days for
the preparation delay. In theory, AUTH48 is just a final
verification: the authors receive the document prepared by the RFC production center,
and just have to give their approval, or maybe request a last minute
correction. The name indicates that this is expected to last just two days, but
in average it lasts more than a month.</t>
        <t>We often hypothesize that the
number of authors influences the AUTH48 delay, or that authors who have spent
a long time working on the document in the working group somehow get demotivated
and spend even longer to answer questions during AUTH48. This may happen
sometimes, but our statistics don't show that  - if anything, the numerical
results point in the opposite direction.</t>
        <t>After asking the authors of the RFCs in the sample why the AUTH48 phase took
a long time, we got three explanations:</t>
<ol>
  <li>Some RFCs have multiple authors in multiple time zones. This slows down
   the coordination required for approving changes.</li>
   <li>Some authors found some of the proposed changes unnecessary or
   undesirable, and asked that they be reversed. This required long
   exchanges between authors and editors.</li>
   <li>Some authors were not giving high priority to AUTH48 responses.</li>
</ol>
        <t>As mentioned above, we were not able to verify these hypotheses by looking at
the data. The author's experience with this document suggests another potential
delay for the Independent Stream RFC: processing delay by the Independent
Submissions Editor, discussed in <xref target="independent-stream" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copy-editing" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Copy Editing</name>
        <t>We can assess the amount of copy editing applied to each published RFC by
comparing the text of the draft approved for publication and the text of the
RFC. We do expect differences in the "boilerplate" and in the IANA section,
but we will also see differences due to copy editing. Assessing the amount
of copy editing is subjective, and we do it using a scale of 1 to 4:</t>
<dl indent="4">
  <dt>1:</dt><dd>Minor editing</dd>
  <dt>2:</dt><dd>Editing for style, such as capitalization, hyphens, "that" versus "which",
   and expanding all acronyms at least once.</dd>
  <dt>3:</dt><dd>Editing for clarity in addition to style, such as rewriting ambiguous
   sentences and clarifying use of internal references. For YANG models,
   that may include model corrections suggested by the verifier.</dd>
  <dt>4:</dt><dd>Extensive editing.</dd>
</dl>
        <t>The following table shows that about half of the RFCs required
editing for style, and the other half at least some editing for clarity.</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="right">RFC</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Copy Edit</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8411</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8456</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8446</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8355</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8441</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8324</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8377</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8498</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8479</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8453</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8429</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8492</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8378</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8361</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8472</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8471</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8466</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8362</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="right">8468</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>This method of assessment does not take into account
the number of changes proposed by the editors and eventually rejected
by the authors, since these changes are not present in either the
final draft or the published RFC. It might be possible to get
an evaluation of these "phantom changes" from the RFC Production Center.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="independent-stream" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Independent Stream</name>
        <t>Out of 20 randomly selected RFCs, 3 were published through the Independent Stream.
One is an independent opinion, another a description of a non-IETF protocol
format, and the third was <xref target="RFC8492" format="default"/>, which is a special case. Apart from
this special case, the publication delays were significantly shorter 
for the Independent Stream than for the IETF Stream.</t>
        <t>The authors of these 3 RFCs are regular IETF contributors. This
observation motivated a secondary analysis of all the RFCs
published in the Independent Stream in 2018. There are 14 such RFCs:
8507, 8494, 8493, 8492, 8483, 8479, 8433, 8409, 8374, 8369, 8367, 8351,
8328, and 8324. (RFCs 8367 and 8369 were
published on 1 April 2018.) The majority of
the documents were published by regular IETF participants, but
two of them were not. One describes "The BagIt File Packaging Format (V1.0)"
<xref target="RFC8493" format="default"/>, and the other the "Yeti DNS Testbed" <xref target="RFC8483" format="default"/>. They
document a data format and a system developed outside the IETF and illustrate
the outreach function of the Independent Stream. In both cases, the
authors include one experienced IETF participant, who presumably helped
outsiders navigate the publication process.</t>
        <t>The present document experienced some publication delays due to the Independent Submissions Editor.
The ISE is a bottleneck and is a volunteer resource. Although the ISE as a lone person
operating as a volunteer is still roughly adequate resource for the
job, the delivery will necessarily be best effort with delays caused
by spikes in ISE load, work commitments, and other life events. These
delays may not be fundamentally critical to RFC delivery, but they
are capable of introducing a significant percentage delay into what
might otherwise be a smooth process.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="citations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Citation Counts</name>
      <t>In this exploration, we want to examine whether citation counts provide a
meaningful assessment of the popularity of RFCs. We obtain the citation
counts through the Semantic Scholar API, using queries of the form:
     <eref brackets="angle" target="https://api.semanticscholar.org/v1/paper/10.17487/rfc8446?include_unknown_references=true" />
      </t>

      <t>In these queries, the RFC is uniquely identified by its DOI reference,
which is composed of the RFC Series prefix 10.17487 and the RFC identifier.
The queries return a series of properties, including a list of citations
for the RFC. Based on that list of citations, we compute three numbers:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The total number of citations</li>
        <li>The number of citations in the year of publication and the year after
that</li>
        <li>For the RFC published in 1998 or 2008 that we use for comparison, the
number of citations in the years 2018 and 2019.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>All the numbers were retrieved on October 6, 2019.</t>
      <section anchor="citation-numbers" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Citation Numbers</name>
        <t>As measured on October 6, 2019, the citation counts for the RFC in
our sample set were:</t>

<!--[rfced] Please let us know if you'd like to add titles to any tables 
in this document. For example:

    Table 10: Citation Counts for a Set of RFCs Published in 2018
    Table 11: Citation Counts for a Set of RFCs Published in 2008
    Table 12: Citation Counts for a Set of RFCs Published in 1998
-->

        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC (2018)</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Total</th>
              <th align="right">2018-2019</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8411</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8456</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8446</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">418</td>
              <td align="right">204</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8355</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8441</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8324</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8377</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8498</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8479</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8453</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8429</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">25</td>
              <td align="right">16</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8492</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8378</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8361</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8472</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8471</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8466</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8362</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8468</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>The results indicate that <xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/> is by far the most cited of the 20
RFC in our sample. This is not surprising, since TLS is a key Internet Protocol.
The TLS 1.3 protocol was also the subject of extensive studies by researchers,
and thus was mentioned in a number of published papers. 
Surprisingly, the Semantic Scholar mentions a number of citations that predate
the publication date. These are probably citations of the various draft
versions of the protocol.</t>
        <t>The next most cited RFC in the sample is <xref target="RFC8312" format="default"/> which describes the
Cubic congestion control algorithm for TCP. That protocol was also the
target of a large number of academic publications. The other RFCs in the
sample only have a small number of citations.</t>
        <t>There is probably a small bias when measuring citations at a fixed date.
An RFC published in January 2018 would have more time to accrue citations than
one published in December. That may be true to some extent, as the second most
cited RFC in the set was published in January. However, the effect has to be
limited. The most cited RFC was published in August, and the second most cited
was published in 2019. (That RFC got an RFC number in 2018, but publication
was slowed by long AUTH48 delays.)</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="comparison-to-1998-and-2008" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Comparison to 1998 and 2008</name>
        <t>In order to get a baseline, we can look at the number of references for the
RFCs published in 2008 and 1998. However, we need to take time into account.
Documents published a long time ago are expected to have accrued more references.
We try to address this by looking at three counts for each document: the
overall number of references over the document's lifetime, the number of
references obtained in the year following publication, and the number of
references observed since 2018:</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC (2008)</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Total</th>
              <th align="right">2008-2009</th>
              <th align="right">2018-2019</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5326</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">138</td>
              <td align="right">14</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5348</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">14</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5281</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">69</td>
              <td align="right">15</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5354</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">17</td>
              <td align="right">13</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5227</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">19</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5329</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">24</td>
              <td align="right">6</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5277</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">32</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5236</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">25</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5358</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">21</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5271</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5195</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5283</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5186</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">14</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5142</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5373</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5404</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5172</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5349</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5301</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">5174</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC (1998)</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Total</th>
              <th align="right">1998-1999</th>
              <th align="right">2018-2019</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2289</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2267</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">982</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">61</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2317</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">9</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2404</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">137</td>
              <td align="right">6</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2374</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">42</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2449</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">7</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2283</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">17</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2394</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">13</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2348</td>
              <td align="left">DS</td>
              <td align="right">5</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2382</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">17</td>
              <td align="right">12</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2297</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">36</td>
              <td align="right">11</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2381</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">39</td>
              <td align="right">12</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">14</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2387</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2398</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">17</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2391</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">31</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2431</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2282</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">8</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2323</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">2448</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>We can compare the median number of citations and the numbers of citations
for the least and most popular quartiles in the three years:</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">References</th>
              <th align="right">Lower 25%</th>
              <th align="right">Median</th>
              <th align="right">Higher 25%</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">RFC (2018)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">RFC (2008)</td>
              <td align="right">6.5</td>
              <td align="right">11</td>
              <td align="right">21.75</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">RFC (2008), until 2009</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">2.5</td>
              <td align="right">4.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">RFC (2008), 2018 and after</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">RFC (1998)</td>
              <td align="right">4.75</td>
              <td align="right">13.5</td>
              <td align="right">32.25</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">RFC (1998), until 1999</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">2</td>
              <td align="right">4.25</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">RFC (1998), 2018 and after</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>The total numbers show new documents with fewer citations than the older ones.
This can be explained to some degree by the passage of time. If we
restrict the analysis to the number of citations accrued in the year of
publishing and the year after that, we still see about the same distribution
for the three samples.</t>
        <t>We also see that the number of references to RFCs fades over time. Only the
most popular of the RFC produced in 1998 are still cited in 2019.</t>

<!--[rfced] FYI, regarding using the citation count based on the 
Semantic Scholar API (which seemingly relies on DOIs):
To include a DOI, it seems the referring document must have been 
published (or at least modified) after May 2015. Rationale: 
DOIs were first registered for existing RFCs in May 2015
(https://www.rfc-editor.org/pipermail/rfc-interest/2015-May/008865.html/).  Please consider whether the note below would be helpful to the reader.  


   We also see that the number of references to RFC fades over time.
   Only the most popular of the RFC produced in 1998 are still cited in
   2019.

Note: Because DOIs were made available for the RFC series in 
the year 2015, these citation counts would only be representative
of citations in documents produced in 2015 and afterwards that 
were citing RFCs from 1998.  It's possible that a given RFC might 
have been cited more frequently in documents produced closer to 
its time of publication.
-->
      </section>
      <section anchor="citations-versus-deployments" numbered="true" toc="default">

        <name>Citations versus Deployments</name>
        <t>The following table shows
side by side the number of citations as measured in <xref target="citation-numbers" format="default"/> and
the estimation of deployment as indicated in <xref target="sample-rfc-analysis" format="default"/>.</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC (2018)</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Citations</th>
              <th align="right">Deployment</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8411</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">medium</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8456</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">medium</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8446</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">418</td>
              <td align="right">high</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8355</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">medium</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8441</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">high</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8324</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">N/A</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8377</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">unknown</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8498</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">unknown</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8479</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">one</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8453</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">unknown</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8429</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">some</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">25</td>
              <td align="right">high</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8492</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">one</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8378</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">some</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8361</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">one</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8472</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">medium</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8471</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">medium</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8466</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">unknown</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8362</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">medium</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8468</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">some</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>From looking at these results, it is fairly obvious that citation counts
cannot be used as proxies for the "value" of an RFC. In our sample, the two
RFCs that have high citation counts were both widely deployed, and can certainly be 
described as successful, but we also see many RFCs that saw significant deployment
without garnering a high level of citations.</t>
        <t>Citation counts are driven by academic interest,
but are only loosely correlated with actual deployment. We saw that <xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/>
was widely cited in part because the standardization process involved many
researchers, and that the high citation count of <xref target="RFC8312" format="default"/> is
largely due to the academic interest in evaluating congestion control protocols.
If we look at previous years, the most cited RFC in the 2008 sample is <xref target="RFC5326" format="default"/>, an
experimental RFC defining security extensions to an
experimental delay tolerant transport protocol. This protocol does not
carry a significant proportion of Internet traffic, but has been the object
of a fair number of academic studies.</t>
        <t>The citation process tends to privilege the first expression of a concept.
We see that with the most cited RFC in the 1998 set is <xref target="RFC2267" format="default"/>, an informational
RFC defining Network Ingress Filtering that was obsoleted in May
2000 by <xref target="RFC2827" format="default"/>. It is still cited frequently in 2018 and
2019, regardless of its formal status in
the RFC Series. We see the same effect at work with <xref target="RFC8441" format="default"/>, which
garners very few citations although it updates <xref target="RFC6455" format="default"/> that has
a large number of citations. The same goes for <xref target="RFC8468" format="default"/>, which is
sparsely cited while the <xref target="RFC2330" format="default"/> is widely cited. Just counting citations
will not indicate whether developers still use an old specification or
have adopted the revised RFC.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="citations-versus-web-references" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Citations versus Web References</name>
        <t>Web references might be another indicator of the popularity of an RFC.
In order to evaluate these references, we list here the number of results
returned by searches on Google and Bing, looking for the search term "RFCnnnn"
(e.g., "RFC8411"), and copying the number of results returned by the
search engines. The table below presents the results of these searches,
performed on April 4, 2020.</t>
        <table align="center">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">RFC (2018)</th>
              <th align="left">Status</th>
              <th align="right">Citations</th>
              <th align="right">Google</th>
              <th align="right">Bing</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8411</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">301</td>
              <td align="right">94</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8456</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">266</td>
              <td align="right">8456</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8446</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">418</td>
              <td align="right">25900</td>
              <td align="right">47800</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8355</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">521</td>
              <td align="right">114</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8441</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">2430</td>
              <td align="right">59500</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8324</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">393</td>
              <td align="right">138</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8377</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">264</td>
              <td align="right">10900</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8498</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">335</td>
              <td align="right">10100</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8479</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">564</td>
              <td align="right">11000</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8453</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">3</td>
              <td align="right">817</td>
              <td align="right">11400</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8429</td>
              <td align="left">BCP</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">391</td>
              <td align="right">41600</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8312</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">25</td>
              <td align="right">1620</td>
              <td align="right">2820</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8492</td>
              <td align="left">Info (ISE)</td>
              <td align="right">4</td>
              <td align="right">323</td>
              <td align="right">9400</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8378</td>
              <td align="left">Exp</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">418</td>
              <td align="right">11600</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8361</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">499</td>
              <td align="right">92</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8472</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">496</td>
              <td align="right">169</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8471</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">1510</td>
              <td align="right">11600</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8466</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">0</td>
              <td align="right">766</td>
              <td align="right">173</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8362</td>
              <td align="left">PS</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">67</td>
              <td align="right">147</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">8468</td>
              <td align="left">Info</td>
              <td align="right">1</td>
              <td align="right">453</td>
              <td align="right">127</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>The result counts from Bing are sometimes surprising. Why would RFC 8441 gather
59,500 web references? Looking at the results in detail, we find a mix of data.
Some of them are logs of development projects implementing Web Sockets, which
is exactly what we are looking for, but others appear spurious. For example,
a shop selling rugby jerseys is listed because its phone number ends with "8441".
Other pages were listed because street numbers or product numbers matched the
RFC number.
The same type of collision may explain the large reference counts on Bing for
RFCs 8377, 8498, 8479, 8453, 8429, 8378, and 8471. The result counts on Bing
do not appear to provide a good metric.</t>
        <t>On Google, all RFCs garner at least a 250 references, largely because the whole
RFC catalog is replicated on a large number of web servers. Deviations from that
baseline are largely correlated with the number of citations in the Semantic
Scholar, with a couple of exception: RFC 8441 and RFC 8471 garner more
references than the low citation counts would predict. Looking at the
results, we find many references in development databases explaining
how these protocols are implemented in various code bases and open source
projects. This means that counting Google results would give some indication
about an RFC's popularity, complementing the citation counts.</t>
        <t>There are some practical problems in using the counts of Google
results. Google searches are personalized, the results depend
on the source of the queries, and the counts may vary as well. The
search results depend on the search algorithm, and there is no guarantee
that counts will not change when the algorithm changes. On the other
hand, the results do indicate that some of the RFCs in our sample
are being used by developers or in deployments.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conclusion" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Observations and Next Steps</name>
      <t>The author's goal was to get a personal understanding of the "chain
of production" of the RFCs, and in particular to look at the various
causes of delays in the process. As shown in
<xref target="process-analysis" format="default"/>, the average RFC was produced in 3 years and 4 months, 
which is similar to what was found in the
2008 sample, but more than three times larger than the delays for the
1998 sample.</t>
      <t>The working group process appears to be the main source of delays. 
Efforts to diminish delays should probably focus there, instead of on the
IETF and IESG reviews or the RFC production. For the RFC production
phase, most of the variability originates in the AUTH48 process,
which is influenced by a variety of factors such as number of
authors or level of engagement of these authors.</t>
      <t>Most of the delay is spent in the working group, but the IETF
Datatracker does not hold much information about what happens inside
the working groups. For example, events like Working Group Last Calls
were not recorded in the history of the selected drafts available in the
Datatracker. Such information would have been interesting. Of course,
requiring that information would create an administrative burden, so
there is clearly a trade-off between requiring more work from working
group chairs and providing better data for process analysis. (It appears
that this information can be available in the Datatracker for more recent
drafts, if the WG chairs use the Datatracker properly.)</t>
      <t>The Independent Stream operates as expected. The majority
of the authors of the Independent Stream RFCs appear to be in IETF insiders,
but there is significant amount of engagement by outside parties.</t>
      <t>The analysis of citations in <xref target="citation-numbers" format="default"/> shows that citation
numbers are a very poor indication of the "value" of an RFC. Citation
numbers measure the engagement of academic researchers with specific
topics, but have little correlation with the level of adoption and
deployment of a specific RFC. The result counts of Google searches
do capture references outside academia, such as logs of development
projects. This might be informative, but it is not clear that the counts
would not change over time due to algorithm changes or personalization.</t>
      <t>This document analyses a small sample of RFCs "in depth". This allowed
gathering of detailed feedback on the process and the deployments. On
the other hand, much of the data on delays is available from the
IETF Datatracker. It may be worth considering adding an automated
reporting of delay metrics in the IETF Datatracker.</t>
      <t>This document only considers the RFCs that were published in a given
year. This approach can be criticized as introducing a form of
"survivor bias". There are many drafts proposed to the IETF, and only
a fraction of them end up being published as RFCs. 
On one hand, this is expected,
because part of the process is to triage between ideas that can gather
consensus and those that don't. On the other hand, we don't know
whether that triage is too drastic and has discouraged progress on good
ideas.</t>
      <t>One way to evaluate the triage process would be to 
look at publication attempts that were abandoned -- for
example, drafts that expired without progressing or being replaced. The sampling
methodology could also be used for that purpose. Pick maybe 20 drafts at random,
among those abandoned in a target year, and investigate why they were abandoned.
Was it because better solutions emerged in the working group? Or maybe because
the authors discovered a flaw in their proposal? Or was it because some factional
struggle blocked a good idea? Was the idea pursued in a different venue?
Hopefully, someone will try this kind of investigation.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document does not specify any protocol.</t>
      <t>We might want to analyze whether security issues were discovered after
publication of specific standards.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
      <t>Preliminary analysis does not indicate that IANA is causing any particular
delay in the RFC publication process.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-segment-routing-ti-lfa" to="TI-LFA"/>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>

      <reference anchor="TRKR" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/">
        <front>
          <title>IETF Datatracker</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IETF</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SSCH" target="https://www.semanticscholar.org/">
        <front>
          <title>Semantic Scholar | AI-Powered Research Tool</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Allen Institute for AI</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TLS13IMP" target="https://github.com/tlswg/tlswg-wiki/blob/master/IMPLEMENTATIONS.md">
        <front>
          <title>TLS 1.3 Implementations</title>
          <author>
            <organization>TLS WG</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="14" month="October" year="2019"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="commit" value="dcb7890"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFCYEAR" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfcs-per-year/">
        <front>
          <title>Number of RFC Published per YEAR</title>
          <author>
            <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IETFCOUNT" target="https://www.ietf.org/how/meetings/past/">
        <front>
          <title>Past IETF Meetings</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IETF</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8411.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8410.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8456.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8455.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8355.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8441.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6455.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8324.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8377.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8498.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8479.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8453.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8429.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8312.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8492.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8378.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8361.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8472.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8471.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8466.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8362.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8468.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8493.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8483.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5326.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2267.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2330.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtgwg-segment-routing-ti-lfa.xml"/>
    </references>

    <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Many thanks to the authors of the selected RFCs who were willing to
provide feedback on the process:
<contact fullname="Michael Ackermann"/>,
<contact fullname="Zafar Ali"/>,
<contact fullname="Sarah Banks"/>,
<contact fullname="Bruno Decraene"/>,
<contact fullname="Lars Eggert"/>,
<contact fullname="Nalini Elkins"/>,
<contact fullname="Joachim Fabini"/>,
<contact fullname="Dino Farinacci"/>,
<contact fullname="Clarence Filsfils"/>,
<contact fullname="Sujay Gupta"/>,
<contact fullname="Dan Harkins"/>,
<contact fullname="Vinayak Hegde"/>,
<contact fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/>,
<contact fullname="John Klensin"/>,
<contact fullname="Acee Lindem"/>,
<contact fullname="Nikos Mavrogiannopoulos"/>,
<contact fullname="Patrick McManus"/>,
<contact fullname="Victor Moreno"/>,
<contact fullname="Al Morton"/>,
<contact fullname="Andrei Popov"/>,
<contact fullname="Eric Rescorla"/>,
<contact fullname="Michiko Short"/>,
<contact fullname="Bhuvaneswaran Vengainathan"/>,
<contact fullname="Lao Weiguo"/>, and
<contact fullname="Li Yizhou"/>. 
Many thanks to <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/> for his useful advice, to <contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/> and <contact fullname="Colin Perkins"/> for their guidance on the use of citations, and to <contact fullname="Dave Crocker"/> for a comprehensive
review. Thanks also to <contact fullname="Alice Russo"/> and the RFC Editor team for their work improving this document and checking the accuracy of the data.</t>
    </section>

  </back>

</rfc>
