<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc 
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
number="8729"
updates="" 
obsoletes="4844" 
category="info" 
submissionType="IAB" 
consensus="true"
ipr="trust200902" 
sortRefs="true" 
symRefs="true" 
xml:lang="en" 
docName="draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc4844-bis-05" 
tocInclude="true" 
tocDepth="4" 
version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.35.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The RFC Series and RFC Editor">The RFC Series and RFC Editor</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8729"/>
    <author fullname="Russ Housley" initials="R." surname="Housley" role="editor">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>housley@vigilsec.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Leslie L. Daigle" initials="L." surname="Daigle" role="editor">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>ldaigle@thinkingcat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2020"/>
    <keyword>IASA</keyword>
    <keyword>IASA2</keyword>
    <keyword>technical publisher</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
This document describes the framework for an RFC Series and an RFC Editor
function that incorporate the principles of organized community
involvement and accountability that has become necessary as the Internet
technical community has grown, thereby enabling the RFC Series to
continue to fulfill its mandate. This document obsoletes RFC 4844. 
</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
The first Request for Comments (RFC) document was published in April
of 1969 as part of the effort to design and build
what we now know of as the Internet.  Since then, the RFC Series
has been the archival series dedicated to documenting
Internet technical specifications, including both general
contributions from the Internet research and engineering
community as well as standards documents.
</t>
      <t>
As described in the history of the first 30 years of RFCs
(<xref target="RFC2555" format="default"/>), the RFC Series was created for the purpose
of capturing the research and engineering thought that underlie
the design of (what we now know of as) the Internet.   As the
Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) was formalized to carry out
the discussion and documentation of Internet standards, IETF documents
have become a large part (but not the entirety) of the RFC Series.  
</t>
      <t>
As the IETF has grown up and celebrated its own 30 years of 
history, its requirements for archival publication of its output
have changed and become more rigorous.  Perhaps most significantly,
the IETF must be able to define (based on its own open consensus
discussion processes and leadership directions) and implement
adjustments to its publication processes.
</t>
      <t>
At the same time, the Internet engineering and research community
as a whole has grown and come to require more openness and accountability
in all organizations supporting it.  More than ever, this community
needs an RFC Series that is supported (operationally and in terms of
its principles) such that there is a balance of:
</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
    expert implementation;
    </li>
        <li>
    clear management and direction -- for operations and evolution across
    the whole RFC Series (whether originating in the IETF or not); and 
    </li>
        <li>
    appropriate community input into and review of activities.
    </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
In the past, there has been confusion and therefore sometimes tension over 
where and how to address RFC issues that are particular to
contributing groups (e.g., the IETF, the Internet Architecture Board
(IAB), or independent individuals).  It was not always clear where there should
be community involvement versus RFC Editor control; depending on the
issue, there might be more or less involvement from the IAB, the
Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG), or the
community at large.  There are similar issues with handling RFC
Series-wide issues -- where to discuss and resolve them in a way that
is balanced across the whole series.
</t>
      <t>
For example, there have been discussions about Intellectual Property
Rights (IPR) for IETF-generated documents, but it's not clear when or
how to abstract the portions of those discussions that are relevant
to the rest of the RFC Series.  Discussions of labeling (of
RFCs in general, IETF documents in particular, or some combination
thereof) generally must be applied to the whole RFC Series or
not at all.  Without an agreed-on framework for managing the RFC Series, it is 
difficult to have those discussions in a non-polarized fashion -- 
either the IETF dictating the reality of the rest of the RFC Series, or the 
RFC Series imposing undue restrictions on documents from the IETF.  
</t>
      <t>
As part of its charter (see <xref target="iabcharterhistory" format="default"/>), the IAB has 
a responsibility for the RFC Editor.  Acknowledging the IETF's needs
and the general Internet engineering and research community's evolving
needs, the IAB supports a future for the RFC Series that
continues to meet its original mandate of providing the archival
series for the technical research and engineering documentation that
describes the Internet.  
</t>
      <t>
With this document, the IAB provides the framework for the RFC Series and
an RFC Editor function with the specific purpose of ensuring that the RFC
Series is maintained and supported in ways that are consistent with the
stated purpose of the RFC Series and the realities of today's Internet
research and engineering community.  The framework describes the existing
"streams" of RFCs, draws a roadmap of existing process documents already
defining the implementation, and provides clear direction of how to
evolve this framework and its supporting pieces through discussion and
future document revision.
</t>
      <t>
Specifically, this document provides a brief charter for the RFC Series,
describes the role of the RFC Editor, the IAB, and the IETF
Administrative Support Activity (IASA) in a framework for managing the
RFC Series, and discusses the streams of input to the RFC Series from the
various constituencies it serves.
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="charter" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>RFC Series Mission</name>
      <t>
The RFC Series is the archival series dedicated to documenting Internet 
technical specifications, including general
contributions from the Internet research and engineering
community as well as standards documents.
</t>
      <t>
RFCs are available free of charge to anyone via the Internet. 
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="roles" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Roles and Responsibilities</name>
      <t>
As this document sets out the framework for supporting the
RFC Series mission, this section reviews the updated roles and 
responsibilities of the entities that have had, and will have, 
involvement in continued support of the mission.
</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC Editor</name>
        <t>
Originally, there was a single person acting as editor of the RFC
Series (the RFC Editor).  The task has grown, and the work now 
requires the organized activity of several experts, so there are
RFC Editors, or an RFC Editor organization.  In time, there may be
multiple organizations working together to undertake the work required
by the RFC Series.  For simplicity's sake, and without attempting
to predict how the role might be subdivided among them, this document 
refers to this collection of experts and organizations as the "RFC Editor".
</t>
        <t>
The RFC Editor is an expert technical editor and series editor, acting to 
support the mission of the RFC Series.  As such, the RFC Editor
is the implementer handling the editorial management of the RFC 
Series, in accordance with the defined processes.  In addition, the
RFC Editor is expected to be the expert and prime mover in discussions
about policies for editing, publishing, and archiving RFCs.
</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iab" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>IAB</name>
        <t>
In this model, the role of the IAB is to ensure that the RFC Series
mission is being appropriately fulfilled for the whole community for
which it was created.  The IAB does not, organizationally, have
comprehensive publishing or editorial expertise.  Therefore, the role of
the IAB is focused on ensuring that principles are met, the appropriate
bodies and communities are duly informed and consulted, and the RFC
Editor has what it needs in order to execute on the material that is in
their mandate.
</t>
        <t>
It is the responsibility of the IAB to approve the
appointment of the RFC Editor and to approve the general
policy followed by the RFC Editor.
</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ops" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Operational Oversight</name>
        <t>
The IETF Administration Limited Liability Company (IETF LLC), as part
of the IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA), is responsible
for administrative and financial matters for the IETF, the IAB, and
the Internet Research Task Force (IRTF)
<xref target="RFC8711" format="default"/>.  The IASA is tasked with
providing the funding for the RFC Editor.  The IASA, through the
IETF Executive Director, provides contractual and financial oversight
of the RFC Editor.  Additionally, as described in 
<xref target="RFC8728" section="3.1" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>, the RFC Series Oversight
Committee (RSOC), acting with authority delegated from the IAB, is
responsible for ensuring that the RFC Series is run in a transparent
and accountable manner, including design and execution of the
RFC Series Editor selection process.
</t>
        <t>
The IETF Executive Director works with the IAB to identify suitable
persons or entities to fulfill the mandate of the RFC Production
Center and the RFC Publisher roles as defined in
<xref target="RFC8728" format="default"/>.
</t>
        <t>
The IETF Executive Director establishes appropriate
contractual agreements with the selected persons or entities
to carry out the work that will satisfy the technical publication requirements
defined for the various RFC input streams (see <xref target="reqs" format="default"/>).
The IETF Executive Director may define additional operational requirements
and policies for management purposes to meet the requirements defined
by the various communities.    
</t>
        <t>
The IETF Administration LLC Board approves a budget for operation of
the RFC Editor activity, and the IETF Executive Director establishes and
manages the necessary operational agreements for the RFC Editor activity.
</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="policyoversight" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Policy Oversight</name>
        <t>
The IAB monitors the effectiveness of the policies in force and
their implementation to ensure that the RFC Editor activity
meets the editorial management and document publication needs
as referenced in this document.  In the event of serious non-conformance,  
the IAB, either on its own initiative or at the request of the IETF
Administration LLC Board, may require the IETF Executive Director to vary
or terminate and renegotiate the arrangements for the RFC Editor activity. 
</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="framework" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Framework</name>
      <t>
With the RFC Series mission outlined above, this document describes a
framework for supporting 
</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
    the operational implementation of the RFC Series, 
    </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
based on
</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
    public process and definition documents, 
    </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
for which there are 
</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
    clear responsibilities and mechanisms for update and change.
    </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
Generally speaking, the RFC Editor is responsible for the 
operational implementation of the RFC Series.  As outlined
in <xref target="ops" format="default"/>, the IETF Executive Director provides
the oversight of this operational role.
</t>
      <t>
The process and definition documents are detailed below, including
responsibility for the individual process documents (maintenance and
update).  The RFC Editor works with the appropriate community to ensure
that the process documents reflect current requirements.  The IAB is
charged with the role of verifying that appropriate community input has
been sought and that any changes appropriately account for community
requirements.
</t>
      <t>
There are three categories of activity, and a fourth category of series-wide 
rules and guidelines, described for implementing the RFC Series to support 
its mission:
</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
    Approval of documents.
    </li>
        <li>
    Editing, processing, and publication of documents.
    </li>
        <li>
    Archiving and indexing the documents and making them accessible.
    </li>
        <li>
    Series rules and guidelines.
    </li>
      </ul>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Document Approval</name>
        <t>
The RFC Series mission implicitly requires that documents be
reviewed and approved for acceptance into the series.  
</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Definition</name>
          <t>
<xref target="approval" format="default"/> describes the different streams of documents
that are put to the RFC Editor for publication as RFCs today.  While
there may be general policies for approval of documents as RFCs (to
ensure the coherence of the RFC Series), there are also policies defined
for the approval of documents in each stream.  Generally speaking, there
is a different approving body for each stream.  The current definitions
are catalogued in <xref target="approval" format="default"/>.
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Operational Implementation</name>
          <t>
Each stream has its own documented approval process.  The RFC Editor is
responsible for the approval of documents in one of the streams
(Independent Submission stream, see <xref target="independent-approval" format="default"/>)
and works with the other approving bodies to ensure smooth passage of
approved documents into the next phases, ultimately to publication and
archiving as an RFC.
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Process Change</name>
          <t>
From time to time, it may be necessary to change the approval processes
for any given stream, or even add or remove streams.  This may occur
when the RFC Editor, the IAB, the body responsible for a given stream of 
documents, or the community determines that there are issues to be
resolved in general for RFC approval or for per-stream approval processes.
</t>
          <t>
In this framework, the general approach is that the IAB will work with
the RFC Editor and other parties to get community input, and it will verify
that any changes appropriately account for community requirements. 
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Existing Approval Process Documents</name>
          <t>
The existing documents describing the approval processes for each 
stream are detailed in <xref target="approval" format="default"/>.
</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Editing, Processing, and Publication of Documents</name>
        <t>
Producing and maintaining a coherent, well-edited document series 
requires specialized skills and subject matter expertise.  This is
the domain of the RFC Editor.  Nevertheless, the community served
by the RFC Series and the communities served by the individual
streams of RFCs have requirements that help define the nature of the
series.
</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Definition</name>
          <t>
General and stream-specific requirements for the RFC Series are documented
in community-approved documents (catalogued in <xref target="reqs" format="default"/>
below).
</t>
          <t>
Any specific interfaces, numbers, or concrete values required to make the
requirements operational are the subject of agreements between
the IASA and the RFC Editor (e.g., contracts, statements of work, service
level agreements, etc).
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Operational Implementation</name>
          <t>
The RFC Editor is responsible for ensuring that editing, processing, and
publication of RFCs are carried out in a way that is consistent with the
requirements laid out in the appropriate documents.  The RFC Editor works
with the IASA to provide regular reporting and feedback on these operations.
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Process Change</name>
          <t>
From time to time, it may be necessary to change the requirements
for any given stream, or the RFC Series in general.  This may occur
when the RFC Editor, the IAB, the approval body for a given stream of 
documents, or the community determines that there are issues to be
resolved in general for RFCs or for per-stream requirements.
</t>
          <t>
In this model, the general approach is that the IAB will work with the
RFC Editor to get community input, and it will approve changes by
validating appropriate consideration of community requirements.
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Existing Process Documents</name>
          <t>
Documents describing existing requirements for the streams are
detailed in <xref target="reqs" format="default"/>.
</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Archiving, Indexing, and Accessibility</name>
        <t>
The activities of archiving, indexing, and making accessible the RFC
Series can be informed by specific subject matter expertise in general
document series editing.  It is also important that they are informed by
requirements from the whole community.  As long as the RFC Series is to
remain coherent, there should be uniform archiving and indexing of RFCs
across all streams and a common method of accessing the resulting
documents.
</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Definition</name>
          <t>
In principle, there should be a community consensus document describing
the archiving, indexing, and accessibility requirements for the RFC
Series.  In practice, we continue with the archive as built by the
capable RFC Editors since the series' inception.
</t>
          <t>
Any specific concrete requirements for the archive, index, and
accessibility operations are the subject of agreements between the IASA
and the RFC Editor (e.g., contracts, statements of work, service level
agreements, etc).
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Operational Implementation</name>
          <t>
The RFC Editor is responsible for ensuring that the RFC archive and index
are maintained appropriately and that the resulting documents are made
available to anybody wishing to access them via the Internet.  The RFC
Editor works with the IASA for regular reporting and feedback.
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Process Change</name>
          <t>
Should there be a community move to propose changes to the requirements
for the RFC archive and index or accessibility, the IAB will work with 
the RFC Editor to get community input, and it will approve changes 
by validating appropriate consideration of community requirements.
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Existing Process Documents</name>
          <t>
There are no applicable process documents.
</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Series-Wide Guidelines and Rules</name>
        <t>
The RFC Series style and content can be shaped by subject matter
expertise in document series editing.  They are also informed by
requirements by the using community.  As long as the RFC Series is to
remain coherent, there should be uniform style and content for RFCs
across all streams.  This includes, but is not limited to, acceptable
language, use of references, and copyright rules.
</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Definition</name>
          <t>
In principle, there should be a community consensus document (or set of
documents) describing the content requirements for the RFC Series.  In
practice, some do exist, though some need reviewing and more may be
needed over time.
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Operational Implementation</name>
          <t>
The RFC Editor is responsible for ensuring that the RFC Series guidelines
are upheld within the RFC Series. 
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Process Change</name>
          <t>
When additions or changes are needed to series-wide definitions,
the IAB will work with the RFC Editor and stream stakeholders
to get community input and review.  The IAB will approve changes by
validating appropriate consideration of community requirements.  
</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Existing Process Documents</name>
          <t>
Existing series-wide rules and guidelines documents include:
</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
    RFC Style Guide
    <xref target="RFC7322" format="default"/>, 
    </li>
            <li>
    The Use of Non-ASCII Characters in RFCs
    <xref target="RFC7997" format="default"/>,
    </li>
            <li>
    Copyright and intellectual property rules
    <xref target="RFC5378" format="default"/>,
    </li>
            <li>
    Normative references
    <xref target="RFC3967" format="default"/>
    <xref target="RFC4897" format="default"/>,
    <xref target="RFC8067" format="default"/>.
    </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="streams" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>RFC Streams</name>
      <t>
Various contributors provide input to the RFC Series.  These
contributors come from several different communities, each
with its own defined process for approving documents that
will be published by the RFC Editor.  This is nothing new;
however, over time the various communities and document
requirements have grown and separated.  In order to promote
harmony in discussing the collective set of requirements,
it is useful to recognize each in their own space -- and they
are referred to here as "streams".  
</t>
      <t>
Note that by identifying separate streams, there is no intention
of dividing them or undermining their management as one series.  Rather,
the opposite is true -- by clarifying the constituent parts, 
it is easier to make them work together without the friction that
sometimes arises when discussing various requirements.
</t>
      <t>
The subsections below identify the streams that exist today. 
There is no immediate expectation of new streams being created,
and it is preferable that new streams NOT be created.  Creation of
streams and all policies surrounding general changes to the
RFC Series are discussed above in <xref target="framework" format="default"/>.
</t>
      <section anchor="approval" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC Approval Processes</name>
        <t>
Processes for approval of documents (or requirements) for each stream are
defined by the community that defines the stream.  The IAB is charged
with the role of verifying that appropriate community input has been
sought and that the changes are consistent with the RFC Series mission
and this overall framework.
</t>
        <t>
The RFC Editor is expected to publish all documents passed to it
after appropriate review and approval in one of the identified
streams.
</t>
        <section anchor="ietf-approval" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IETF Document Stream</name>
          <t>
The IETF document stream includes IETF WG documents as well as
"individual submissions" sponsored by an IESG area director.  Any
document being published as part of the IETF standards process
must follow this stream -- no other stream can approve
Standards-Track RFCs or Best Current Practice (BCP) RFCs.
</t>
          <t>
Approval of documents in the IETF stream is defined by 
</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
    the IETF standards process
    <xref target="RFC2026" format="default"/> (and its successors).
    </li>
            <li>
    the IESG process for sponsoring individual submissions
    <xref target="SPONSOR" format="default"/>.
    </li>
          </ul>
          <t>
Changes to the approval process for this stream are made by
updating the IETF standards process documents. 
</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iab-approval" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IAB Document Stream</name>
          <t>
The IAB defines the processes by which it approves documents in its
stream.  Consistent with the above, any documents that the IAB wishes to
publish as part of the IETF Standards Track (Standards or BCPs) are
subject to the approval processes referred to in <xref target="ietf-approval" format="default"/>.
</t>
          <t>
The review and approval process for documents in the IAB
stream is described in 
</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
    the IAB process for review and approval of its documents
    <xref target="RFC4845" format="default"/>.
    </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="irtf-approval" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IRTF Document Stream</name>
          <t>
The IRTF is chartered as an activity of the IAB.  With the approval
of the IAB, the IRTF may publish and update a process for
publication of its own, non-IETF Standards-Track, documents.
</t>
          <t>
The review and approval process for documents in the IRTF stream
is described in
</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
    IRTF Research Group RFCs
    <xref target="RFC5743" format="default"/>.
    </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="independent-approval" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Independent Submission Stream</name>
          <t>
The RFC Series has always served a broader Internet technical 
community than the IETF.  The "Independent Submission" stream is
defined to provide review and (possible) approval of documents
that are outside the scope of the streams identified above.  
</t>
          <t>
Generally speaking, approval of documents in this stream falls
under the purview of the RFC Editor, and the RFC Editor seeks
input to its review from the IESG. 
</t>
          <t>
The process for reviewing and approving documents in the Independent
Submission stream is defined by
</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
    Procedures for Rights Handling in the RFC Independent Submission Stream
    <xref target="RFC5744" format="default"/>,
    </li>
            <li>
    Independent Submission Editor Model
    <xref target="RFC8730" format="default"/>,
    </li>
            <li>
    Independent Submissions to the RFC Editor
    <xref target="RFC4846" format="default"/>,
    </li>
            <li>
    The IESG and RFC Editor Documents: Procedures
    <xref target="RFC5742" format="default"/>.
    </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="reqs" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>RFC Technical Publication Requirements</name>
        <t>
The Internet engineering and research community has not only grown,
it has become more diverse, and sometimes more demanding.  The IETF,
as a standards-developing organization, has publication requirements
that extend beyond those of an academic journal.  The IAB does not
have the same interdependence with IANA assignments as the IETF
stream does.  Therefore, there is the need to both codify the
publishing requirements of each stream, and endeavor to harmonize
them to the extent that is reasonable.
</t>
        <t>
Therefore, it is expected that the community of effort behind
each document stream will outline their technical publication 
requirements.
</t>
        <t> 
As part of the RFC Editor oversight, the IAB must agree that the
requirements are consistent with and implementable as part of the
RFC Editor activity.
</t>
        <section anchor="ietf-req" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IETF Documents</name>
          <t>
The requirements for this stream  are defined in <xref target="RFC4714" format="default"/>.
</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iab-req" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IAB Documents</name>
          <t>
Although they were developed for the IETF standards process, the IAB has
identified applicable requirements in <xref target="RFC4714" format="default"/> for its
stream.  In addition, procedures related to IPR for the IAB stream are
captured in <xref target="RFC5745" format="default"/>.
</t>
          <t>
If the IAB elects to define other requirements, they should deviate
minimally from those (in an effort to keep the collective technical
publication requirements reasonably managed by one technical publisher).
</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="irtf-req" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>IRTF Documents</name>
          <t>
The IRTF has identified applicable requirements in <xref target="RFC5743" format="default"/>
for its stream.
</t>
          <t>
If the IRTF elects to define other requirements, they should deviate
minimally from those (in an effort to keep the collective technical
publication requirements reasonably managed by one technical publisher).
</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="independent-req" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Independent Submissions</name>
          <t>
Procedures and processes for the Independent Stream are described in
<xref target="RFC4846" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8730" format="default"/>.
</t>
          <t>
Although they were developed for the IETF standards process, the RFC
Editor has identified applicable requirements in <xref target="RFC4714" format="default"/>
for the Independent Submissions stream.  In addition, procedures related
to IPR for the independent submissions stream are captured in
<xref target="RFC5744" format="default"/>.
</t>
          <t>
If the RFC Editor elects to define other requirements, they should deviate
minimally from those (in an effort to keep the collective technical
publication requirements reasonably managed by one technical publisher).
</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
The processes for the publication of documents must prevent the
introduction of unapproved changes.  Since the RFC Editor maintains the
index of publications, sufficient security must be in place to prevent
these published documents from being changed by external parties.  The
archive of RFC documents, any source documents needed to recreate the RFC
documents, and any associated original documents (such as lists of
errata, tools, and, for some early items, non-machine readable originals)
need to be secured against failure of the storage medium and other
similar disasters.
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="changes" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Changes Since RFC 4844</name>
      <t>
Sections <xref target="ops" format="counter"/>, <xref target="policyoversight" format="counter"/>,
and <xref target="framework" format="counter"/> 
have been updated to align with the restructuring of the
IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA).  Under the new structure, the
IETF LLC performs the tasks related to IASA that were previously assigned to
the IETF Administrative Director and to the Internet Society.
</t>
      <t>
Many references were updated to point to the most recent documents.
</t>
      <t>
Minor editorial changes were made to reflect 10 years of using the framework
provided in RFC 4884.  For example, RFC 4844 said, "... this document sets out
a revised framework  ...", and it is now more appropriate to say, "... this
document sets out the framework ...".
</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC8711" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8711">
          <front>
            <title>Structure of the IETF Administrative Support Activity, Version 2.0</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Haberman">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Hall">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Livingood">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2020" month="February"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8711"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8711"/>
        </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC8730" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8730">
        <front>
          <title>Independent Submission Editor Model</title>
          <author initials="N" surname="Brownlee" fullname="Nevil Brownlee" role="editor">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R" surname="Hinden" fullname="Robert Hinden" role="editor">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8730"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8730"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC8728" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8728">
       <front>
         <title>RFC Editor Model (Version 2)</title>
         <author initials="O" surname="Kolkman" fullname="Olaf Kolkman" role="editor">
           <organization/>
         </author>
         <author initials="J" surname="Halpern" fullname="Joel Halpern" role="editor">
           <organization/>
         </author>
         <author initials="R" surname="Hinden" fullname="Robert Hinden" role="editor">
           <organization/>
         </author>
         <date month="February" year="2020"/>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8728"/>
         <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8728"/>
      </reference>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1358.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1601.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2555.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2850.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5742.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3967.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4714.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4845.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4846.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4897.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5743.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5744.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5745.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7322.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7997.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8067.xml"/>
      <reference anchor="SPONSOR" target="http://www.ietf.org/iesg/statement/ad-sponsoring-docs.html">
        <front>
          <title>Guidance on Area Director Sponsoring of Documents</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IESG</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2007"/>
        </front>
          <refcontent>IESG Statement</refcontent>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="iabcharterhistory" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>A Retrospective of IAB Charters and RFC Editor</name>
      <t>
With this document, the IAB's role with respect to the RFC Series
and the RFC Editor is being adjusted to work more directly with the
RFC Editor and provide oversight to ensure the RFC Series mission
principles and communities' input are addressed appropriately.
</t>
      <t>
This section provides an overview of the role of the IAB with respect
to the RFC Editor as it has been presented in IAB Charter RFCs dating
back to 1992.  The point of this section is that the IAB's role has
historically been substantive -- whether it is supposed to be directly
responsible for the RFC Series' editorial management
(circa 1992, <xref target="circa1992" format="default"/>), or appointment of
the RFC Editor organization and approval of general policy
(circa 2000, <xref target="circa2000" format="default"/>).
</t>
      <section anchor="circa1992" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>1992</name>
        <t>
<xref target="RFC1358" format="default"/> says:</t>
<blockquote>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
[The IAB's] responsibilities shall include:
[...]
    (2)  The editorial management and publication of the Request
         for Comments (RFC) document series, which constitutes the
         archival publication series for Internet Standards and
         related contributions by the Internet research and
         engineering community.
]]></artwork>
</blockquote>
      </section>
      <section anchor="circa1994" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>1994</name>
        <t>
<xref target="RFC1601" format="default"/> says:</t>
<blockquote>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
[The IAB's] responsibilities under this charter include:

(d) RFC Series and IANA

   The IAB is responsible for editorial management and publication 
   of the Request for Comments (RFC) document series, and for
   administration of the various Internet assigned numbers.
]]></artwork></blockquote>

        <t>
Which it elaborates as:
</t>
<blockquote>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 2.4 RFC Series and Assigned Numbers

    The RFC Series constitutes the archival publication channel
    for Internet Standards and for other contributions by the
    Internet research and engineering community.  The IAB 
    shall select an RFC Editor, who shall be responsible for 
    the editorial management and publication of the RFC Series.
]]></artwork>
</blockquote>
      </section>
      <section anchor="circa2000" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>2000</name>
        <t>
The most recent IAB Charter <xref target="RFC2850" format="default"/> says:
</t>
<blockquote>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
(d) RFC Series and IANA

The RFC Editor executes editorial management and publication of
the IETF "Request for Comment" (RFC) document series, which is
the permanent document repository of the IETF.  The RFC Series
constitutes the archival publication channel for Internet 
Standards and for other contributions by the Internet research 
and engineering community.  RFCs are available free of charge to
anyone via the Internet.  The IAB must approve the appointment 
of an organization to act as RFC Editor and the general policy
followed by the RFC Editor.]]></artwork>
</blockquote>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>IAB Members at the Time of Approval</name>
      <t>
The IAB members at the time of approval of RFC 4844 were:
</t>
      <ul empty="true" spacing="compact">
        <li><t><contact fullname="Bernard Aboba"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Loa Andersson"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Brian Carpenter"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Leslie Daigle"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Elwyn Davies"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Kevin Fall"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Olaf Kolkman"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Kurtis Lindqvist"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="David Meyer"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="David Oran"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Eric Rescorla"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Dave Thaler"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Lixia Zhang"/></t></li>
</ul>
      <t>
The IAB members at the time of approval of this document were:
</t>
      <ul empty="true" spacing="compact">
        <li><t><contact fullname="Jari Arkko"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Alissa Cooper"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Wes Hardaker"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Ted Hardie"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Christian Huitema"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Zhenbin Li"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Erik Nordmark"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Mark Nottingham"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Melinda Shore"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Jeff Tantsura"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Martin Thomson"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/></t></li></ul>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
