<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF"
     docName="draft-ietf-pce-wson-rwa-ext-17" number="8780" category="std"
     consensus="true" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en"
     symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" tocInclude="true" version="3">
	<front>

    <title abbrev="PCEP Extension for WSON RWA">The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) Extension for Wavelength Switched Optical Network (WSON) Routing and Wavelength Assignment (RWA)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8780"/>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Young Lee" role="editor">

       <organization>Samsung Electronics</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city> <region></region><code></code>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>younglee.tx@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Casellas" fullname="Ramon Casellas, Editor" role="editor">
      <organization>CTTC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <extaddr>Carl Friedrich Gauss 7</extaddr>
          <street>PMT Ed B4 Av.</street>
          <city>Castelldefels</city><region>Barcelona</region><code>08860</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+34 936452916</phone>
        <email>ramon.casellas@cttc.es</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2020" month="July"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
   This document provides Path Computation Element Communication
   Protocol (PCEP) extensions for the support of Routing and Wavelength
   Assignment (RWA) in Wavelength Switched Optical Networks (WSONs).
   Path provisioning in WSONs requires an RWA process.  From a path computation perspective,
   wavelength assignment is the process of determining which wavelength
   can be used on each hop of a path and forms an additional routing
   constraint to optical path computation.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
 
    <section anchor="sect-3" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
   <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/> specifies the Path Computation Element Communication
   Protocol (PCEP) for communications between a Path Computation Client
   (PCC) and a PCE, or between two PCEs.  Such interactions include
   Path Computation Requests (PCReqs) and Path Computation Replies (PCReps) as well as
   notifications of specific states related to the use of a PCE in the
   context of Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) and Generalized MPLS
   (GMPLS) Traffic Engineering (TE).</t>
      <t>
   A PCC is said to be any network component that makes such a request
   and may be, for instance, an optical switching element within a
   Wavelength Division Multiplexing (WDM) network.  The PCE, itself,
   can be located anywhere within the network and may be within an
   optical switching element, a Network Management System (NMS), or
   an Operational Support System (OSS), or it may be an independent network
   server.</t>
      <t>
   This document provides the PCEP extensions for the support of
   Routing and Wavelength Assignment (RWA) in Wavelength Switched
   Optical Networks (WSONs) based on the requirements specified in
   <xref target="RFC6163" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC7449" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>
   WSON refers to WDM-based optical networks in which switching is performed
   selectively based on the wavelength of an optical signal.  The devices used
   in WSONs that are able to switch signals based on signal wavelength are
   known as Lambda Switch Capable (LSC). WSONs can be transparent or
   translucent. A transparent optical network is made up of optical devices
   that can switch but not convert from one wavelength to another, all within
   the optical domain. On the other hand, translucent networks include 3R
   regenerators (reamplification, reshaping, and retiming) that are sparsely
   placed. The main function of the 3R regenerators is to convert one optical
   wavelength to another.</t>
      <t>
   An LSC Label Switched Path (LSP) may span one
   or several transparent segments, which are delimited by 3R
   regenerators typically with electronic regenerator and optional
   wavelength conversion. Each transparent segment or path in WSON is
   referred to as an optical path. An optical path may span multiple
   fiber links, and the path should be assigned the same wavelength for
   each link. In a case, the optical path is said to satisfy the
   wavelength-continuity constraint. <xref target="fig-1" format="default"/> illustrates the
   relationship between an LSC LSP and transparent segments (optical
   paths).</t>
      <figure anchor="fig-1">
        <name>Illustration of an LSC LSP and Transparent Segments</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
+---+       +-----+       +-----+      +-----+         +-----+
|   |I1     |     |       |     |      |     |       I2|     |
|   |o------|     |-------[(3R) ]------|     |--------o|     |
|   |       |     |       |     |      |     |         |     |
+---+       +-----+       +-----+      +-----+         +-----+
    (X  LSC)     (LSC  LSC)    (LSC  LSC)     (LSC  X)
     <------->   <------->       <----->     <------->
     <-----------------------><---------------------->
      Transparent Segment         Transparent Segment
    <------------------------------------------------->
                           LSC LSP
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
   Note that two transparent segments within a WSON LSP do not need to
   operate on the same wavelength (due to wavelength conversion
   capabilities). Two optical channels that share a common fiber link
   cannot be assigned the same wavelength; otherwise, the two signals
   would interfere with each other. Note that advanced additional
   multiplexing techniques such as polarization-based multiplexing are
   not addressed in this document since the physical-layer aspects are
   not currently standardized. Therefore, assigning the proper
   wavelength on a path is an essential requirement in the optical path
   computation process.</t>
      <t>
   When a switching node has the ability to perform wavelength
   conversion, the wavelength-continuity constraint can be relaxed, and
   an LSP may use different wavelengths on
   different links along its route from origin to destination. It is,
   however, to be noted that wavelength converters may be limited due
   to their relatively high cost, while the number of WDM channels that
   can be supported in a fiber is also limited. As a WSON can be
   composed of network nodes that cannot perform wavelength conversion,
   nodes with limited wavelength conversion, and nodes with full
   wavelength conversion abilities, wavelength assignment is an
   additional routing constraint to be considered in all optical path
   computation.</t>
      <t>
   For example (see <xref target="fig-1" format="default"/>), within a translucent WSON, an LSC
   LSP may be established between interfaces I1 and I2, spanning two transparent
   segments (optical paths) where the wavelength continuity constraint applies
   (i.e., the same unique wavelength must be assigned to the LSP at each TE
   link of the segment). If the LSC LSP induced a Forwarding Adjacency / TE
   link, the switching capabilities of the TE link would be (X X), where X
   refers to the switching capability of I1 and I2.  For example, X can be
   Packet Switch Capable (PSC), Time-Division Multiplexing (TDM), etc.</t>
      <t>
   This document aligns with
 <xref target="RFC8779"
   format="default"/> for generic properties such as label, label set, and
   label assignment, noting that a wavelength is a type of label. Wavelength
   restrictions and constraints are also formulated in terms of labels per
   <xref target="RFC7579" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>
   The optical modulation properties, which are also referred to as signal
   compatibility, are already considered in the signaling in <xref target="RFC7581" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC7688" format="default"/>. In order to improve the
   signal quality and limit some optical effects, several advanced modulation
   processing capabilities are used by the mechanisms specified in this
   document.  

   These modulation capabilities not only contribute to optical signal
   quality checks but also constrain the selection of sender and
   receiver, as they should have matching signal processing
   capabilities.
   This document includes signal compatibility constraints as part of RWA path
   computation. That is, the signal processing capabilities (e.g., modulation
   and Forward Error Correction (FEC)) indicated by means of the Optical Interface
   Class (OIC) must be compatible between the sender and the receiver of the
   optical path across all optical elements.</t>
      <t>
   This document, however, does not address optical impairments as part
   of RWA path computation. See <xref target="RFC6566" format="default"/> for the framework for optical
   impairments.</t>
    </section>

   <section anchor="sect-1" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>
   This document uses the terminology defined in <xref target="RFC4655" format="default"/> and
   <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-2" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sect-4" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Encoding of an RWA Path Request</name>
      <t>
   <xref target="fig-2" format="default"/> shows one typical PCE-based implementation, which is
   referred to as the Combined Process (R&amp;WA). With this architecture,
   the two processes of routing and wavelength assignment are accessed
   via a single PCE. This architecture is the base architecture
   specified in <xref target="RFC6163" format="default"/>, and the PCEP extensions that are specified in
   this document are based on this architecture.</t>
      <figure anchor="fig-2">
        <name>Combined Process (R&amp;WA) Architecture</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                       +----------------------------+
         +-----+       |     +-------+     +--+     |
         |     |       |     |Routing|     |WA|     |
         | PCC |<----->|     +-------+     +--+     |
         |     |       |                            |
         +-----+       |             PCE            |
                       +----------------------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <section anchor="sect-4.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Wavelength Assignment (WA) Object</name>
        <t>
   Wavelength allocation can be performed by the PCE by
   means of:

        </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="(%c)">
          <li>Explicit Label Control <xref target="RFC3471" format="default"/>
          where the PCE allocates which label to use for each interface/node
          along the path.  The allocated labels <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear
          after an interface route subobject.</li>

          <li>A Label Set where the PCE provides a range of potential
   labels to be allocated by each node along the path.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
   Option (b) allows distributed label allocation (performed during
   signaling) to complete wavelength assignment.</t>

        <t>
   Additionally, given a range of potential labels to allocate, a PCReq
   <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> convey the heuristic or mechanism used for the
   allocation.</t>
        <t>
   Per <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>, the format of a PCReq message after incorporating the
   Wavelength Assignment (WA) object is as follows:</t>

<sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
<PCReq Message> ::= <Common Header>

                       [<svec-list>]

                       <request-list>
]]></sourcecode>

  <t> Where:</t>

<sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
      <request-list>::=<request>[<request-list>]

      <request>::= <RP>
                   <END-POINTS>

                   <WA>

                   [other optional objects...]
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>
   If the WA object is present in the request, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be encoded after the
   END-POINTS object as defined in <xref target="RFC8779" format="default"/>. The WA object
   is mandatory in this document. Orderings for the other optional objects are
   irrelevant.</t>
        <t>
   For the WA object, the Object-Class is 42,
   and the Object-Type is 1.</t>
        <t>The format of the WA object body is as follows:</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-3">
          <name>WA Object</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          Reserved             |            Flags            |M|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
//                            TLVs                             //
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

<dl newline="false" spacing="normal">

          <dt>Reserved (16 bits):</dt><dd>Reserved for future use and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be zeroed
           and ignored on receipt.</dd>

          <dt>Flags field (16 bits):</dt><dd><t>One flag bit is allocated as follows:</t>

        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>M (1 bit):</dt><dd>Wavelength Allocation Mode. The M bit is used to indicate the mode of
      wavelength assignment. When the M bit is set to 1, this indicates that the
      label assigned by the PCE must be explicit. That is, the selected way to
      convey the allocated wavelength is by means of Explicit Label Control
      for each hop of a computed LSP.  Otherwise (M bit is set to 0), the
      label assigned by the PCE need not be explicit (i.e., it can be
      suggested in the form of Label Set objects in the corresponding
      response, to allow distributed WA. If M is 0, the PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> return a
      Label Set Field as described in <xref target="RFC7579" sectionFormat="of" section="2.6"/>
      in the response.  See <xref target="sect-5" /> of this document for the encoding
      discussion of a Label Set Field in a PCRep message.</dd>
         </dl>
        <t>All unused flags <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be zeroed. IANA has created
        a new registry to manage the Flags field of the WA object.</t>
 </dd>


         <dt>TLVs (variable):</dt><dd><t>In the TLVs field, the following two TLVs are
	  defined. At least one TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present.</t>

        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Wavelength Selection TLV:</dt><dd>The type of this TLV is 8,
	  and it has a
          fixed length of 32 bits. This TLV indicates the wavelength selection. See
          <xref target="sect-4.2" format="default"/> for details.</dd>
          <dt>Wavelength Restriction TLV:</dt><dd>The type of this
	  TLV is 9, and it has a variable length. This TLV indicates wavelength restrictions. See
	<xref target="sect-4.3" format="default"/> for details.</dd>       
</dl>
</dd>
</dl>

      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-4.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Wavelength Selection TLV</name>
        <t>
   The Wavelength Selection TLV is used to indicate the wavelength
   selection constraint in regard to the order of wavelength assignment
   to be returned by the PCE. This TLV is only applied when the M bit is
   set in the WA object specified in <xref target="sect-4.1" format="default"/>. This TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be
   used when the M bit is cleared.</t>
        <t>

   The encoding of this TLV is specified as the WavelengthSelection sub-TLV
   in <xref target="RFC7689" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2.2"/>. IANA has
   allocated a new TLV type for the Wavelength Selection TLV (Type 8).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-4.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Wavelength Restriction TLV</name>
        <t>
   For any request that contains a wavelength assignment, the requester (PCC)
   <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> specify a restriction on the wavelengths to be
   used. This restriction is to be interpreted by the PCE as a constraint on
   the tuning ability of the origination laser transmitter or on any other
   maintenance-related constraints. Note that if the LSC LSP spans different
   segments, the PCE must have mechanisms to know the tunability restrictions
   of the involved wavelength converters/regenerators, e.g., by means of the
   Traffic Engineering Database (TED) via either IGP or NMS. Even if the PCE
   knows the tunability of the transmitter, the PCC must be able to apply
   additional constraints to the request.</t>
        <t>
   The format of the Wavelength Restriction TLV is as
   follows:</t>
<sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
<Wavelength Restriction> ::=

               (<Action> <Count> <Reserved>

               <Link Identifiers> <Wavelength Constraint>)...
]]></sourcecode>

<t>Where:</t>

<sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
<Link Identifiers> ::= <Link Identifier> [<Link Identifiers>]
]]></sourcecode>

        <t>See <xref target="sect-4.3.1"/> for the encoding of the Link
        Identifier field.</t>
        <t> These fields (i.e., &lt;Action&gt;, &lt;Link Identifiers&gt;, and
	&lt;Wavelength Constraint&gt;, etc.) <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear together more than
	once to be able to specify multiple actions and their
	restrictions.</t>
        <t>
   IANA has allocated a new TLV type for the Wavelength Restriction
   TLV (Type 9).</t>
        <t>The TLV data is defined as follows:</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-4">
          <name>Wavelength Restriction TLV Encoding</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Action        |    Count      |           Reserved            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Link Identifiers                         |
//                          . . .                              //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Wavelength Constraint                      |
//                        . . . .                              //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
~                         . . . .                               ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Action        |    Count      |           Reserved            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Link Identifiers                         |
//                          . . .                              //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Wavelength Constraint                      |
//                        . . . .                              //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

<dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Action (8 bits):</dt><dd>

              <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>0:</dt><dd>Inclusive List. Indicates that one or more
	link identifiers are included in the Link Set. Each identifies a
	separate link that is part of the set.</dd>
              <dt>1:</dt><dd>Inclusive Range. Indicates that the Link Set defines a
           range of links.  It contains two link identifiers. The first
           identifier indicates the start of the range (inclusive). The
           second identifier indicates the end of the range
           (inclusive). All links with numeric values between the
           bounds are considered to be part of the set. A value of zero
           in either position indicates that there is no bound on the
           corresponding portion of the range.</dd>
              <dt>2-255:</dt><dd>Unassigned.</dd>
              </dl>
<t>IANA has created a new registry to manage the Action values of the
Wavelength Restriction TLV.</t>

        <t>
   If a PCE receives an unrecognized Action value, the PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a
   PCEP Error (PCErr) message with a PCEP-ERROR object with Error-Type=27 and 
   an Error-value=3. See <xref target="sect-5.2" format="default"/> for details.</t>
        <t>
   Note that "links" are assumed to be bidirectional.</t>

 </dd>


<dt>Count (8 bits):</dt><dd><t>The number of the link identifiers.</t>
        <t>
   Note that a PCC <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> add a Wavelength restriction that applies to all
   links by setting the Count field to zero and specifying just a set
   of wavelengths.</t>
        <t>
   Note that all link identifiers in the same list <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be of the same
   type.</t>
 </dd>


          <dt>Reserved (16 bits):</dt>
          <dd> Reserved for future use and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
	be zeroed and ignored on receipt.
	</dd>


          <dt>Link Identifiers:</dt>
          <dd> Identifies each link ID for which
	restriction is applied. The length is dependent on the link format and
	the Count field. See <xref target="sect-4.3.1" format="default"/> for
	encoding of the Link Identifier field.
	</dd>

          <dt>Wavelength Constraint:</dt>
          <dd> See <xref target="sect-4.3.2"/> for the encoding of the
	Wavelength Constraint field.
	</dd>
        </dl>

        <t>
   Various encoding errors are possible with this TLV (e.g., not
   exactly two link identifiers with the range case, unknown identifier
   types, no matching link for a given identifier, etc.).

   To indicate
   errors associated with this encoding, a PCEP speaker <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a
   PCErr message with Error-Type=27 and Error-value=3. See <xref target="sect-5.2" format="default"/> for details.</t>
        <section anchor="sect-4.3.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Link Identifier Field</name>
          <t>
   The Link Identifier field can be an IPv4 <xref target="RFC3630"
   format="default"/>, IPv6 <xref target="RFC5329" format="default"/>, or
   unnumbered interface ID <xref target="RFC4203" format="default"/>.</t>
         
<sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
<Link Identifier> ::=

            <IPv4 Address> | <IPv6 Address> | <Unnumbered IF ID>
]]></sourcecode>

          <t>The encoding of each case is as follows.</t>


<figure anchor="fig-4.3.1-1">
<name>IPv4 Address Field</name>
<artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type = 1     |    Reserved  (24 bits)                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| IPv4 address (4 bytes)                                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<figure anchor="fig-4.3.1-2">
<name>IPv6 Address Field</name>
<artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type = 2     |    Reserved  (24 bits)                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| IPv6 address (16 bytes)                                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| IPv6 address (continued)                                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| IPv6 address (continued)                                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| IPv6 address (continued)                                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<figure anchor="fig-4.3.1-3">
<name>Unnumbered Interface ID Address Field</name>

<artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type = 3     |    Reserved (24 bits)                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        TE Node ID (32 bits)                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Interface ID (32 bits)                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
        
          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="3">
            <dt>Type (8 bits):</dt>
            <dd> Indicates the type of the link identifier.</dd>

            <dt>Reserved (24 bits):</dt>
            <dd>Reserved for future use and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
        be zeroed and ignored on receipt.</dd>

            <dt>Link Identifier:</dt>
            <dd>When the Type field is 1, a 4-byte IPv4
	address is encoded; when the Type field is 2, a 16-byte IPv6 address is
	encoded; and when the Type field is 3, a tuple of a 4-byte TE node ID and
	a 4-byte interface ID is encoded.</dd>
       </dl>
          <t>
   The Type field is extensible and matches the "TE_LINK Object Class type
   name space (Value 11)" registry created for the
   Link Management Protocol (LMP) <xref target="RFC4204"
   format="default"/> (see <xref target="LMP-PARAM"/>). IANA has added
   an introductory note before the aforementioned registry stating that the values
   have additional usage for the Link Identifier Type field. See <xref
   target="sect-8.14" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sect-4.3.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Wavelength Constraint Field</name>
          <t>
   The Wavelength Constraint field of the Wavelength Restriction
   TLV is encoded as a Label Set Field as specified in
   <xref target="RFC7579" sectionFormat="of" section="2.6"/> with the base label encoded as a 32-bit LSC
   label, as defined in <xref target="RFC6205" format="default"/>.  The Label Set format is repeated here
   for convenience, with the base label internal structure included.
   See <xref target="RFC6205" format="default"/> for a description of Grid, Channel Spacing (C.S.), Identifier, and n, and see <xref target="RFC7579" format="default"/> for the details of each action.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-7.1">
          <name>Wavelength Constraint Field</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Action|    Num Labels         |          Length               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Grid | C.S.  |    Identifier   |              n                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Additional fields as necessary per action                 |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>

          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">

          <dt>Action (4 bits):</dt><dd>

            <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>0:</dt><dd>Inclusive List</dd>
            <dt>1:</dt><dd>Exclusive List</dd>
            <dt>2:</dt><dd>Inclusive Range</dd>
            <dt>3:</dt><dd>Exclusive Range</dd>
            <dt>4:</dt><dd>Bitmap Set</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

            <dt>Num Labels (12 bits):</dt>
            <dd> It is generally the number of
	labels. It has a specific meaning depending on the action value.</dd>
            <dt>Length (16 bits):</dt>
            <dd> It is the length in bytes of the entire Wavelength
	Constraint field.</dd>
            <dt>Identifier (9 bits):</dt>
            <dd> The Identifier is always set to
	0. If PCC receives the value of the identifier other than 0, it will ignore.</dd>
          </dl>

          <t>
   See Sections <xref target="RFC7579" section="2.6.1" sectionFormat="bare"/>-<xref target="RFC7579" section="2.6.3" sectionFormat="bare"/> of <xref target="RFC7579"/> for details on additional
   field discussion for each action.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-4.4" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Signal Processing Capability Restrictions</name>
        <t>
   Path computation for WSON includes the checking of signal processing
   capabilities at each interface against requested capability; the PCE
   <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have mechanisms to know the signal processing capabilities at
   each interface, e.g., by means of
   (TED) via either IGP or NMS.  Moreover,
   a PCC should be able to indicate additional restrictions to signal
   processing compatibility, on either the endpoint or any given link.</t>
        <t>
   The supported signal processing capabilities considered in the RWA
   Information Model <xref target="RFC7446" format="default"/> are:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Optical Interface Class List</li>
          <li>Bit Rate</li>
          <li>Client Signal</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
   The bit rate restriction is already expressed in the BANDWIDTH object in <xref target="RFC8779"
   format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>
   In order to support the optical interface class information and the client
   signal information, new TLVs are introduced as endpoint restrictions in the
   END-POINTS type Generalized Endpoint:

        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Client Signal Information TLV</li>
          <li>Optical Interface Class List TLV</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
   The END-POINTS type Generalized Endpoint is extended as follows:</t>

<sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
<endpoint-restriction> ::=
                      <LABEL-REQUEST> <label-restriction-list>

<label-restriction-list> ::= <label-restriction>
                             [<label-restriction-list>]

<label-restriction> ::= (<LABEL-SET>|
                        [<Wavelength Restriction>]
                        [<signal-compatibility-restriction>])
]]></sourcecode>

<t>Where:</t>

<sourcecode type="rbnf"><![CDATA[
<signal-compatibility-restriction> ::=
    [<Optical Interface Class List>] [<Client Signal Information>]
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>
   The Wavelength Restriction TLV is defined in <xref target="sect-4.3"/>.</t>

        <t>
   A new Optical Interface Class List TLV (Type 11) is
   defined; the encoding of the value part of this TLV
   is described in <xref target="RFC7581" sectionFormat="of" section="4.1"/>.</t>
        <t>
   A new Client Signal Information TLV (Type 12) is defined;
   the encoding of the value part of this
   TLV is described in <xref target="RFC7581" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2"/>.</t>

        <section anchor="sect-4.4.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Signal Processing Exclusion</name>
          <t>
   The PCC/PCE should be able to exclude particular types of signal
   processing along the path in order to handle client restriction or
   multi-domain path computation. 

   <xref target="RFC5521" format="default"/> defines how the Exclude Route
   Object (XRO) subobject is used. In this document, we add two new XRO
   Signal Processing Exclusion subobjects.</t>
          <t>
   The first XRO subobject type (8) is the Optical Interface Class
   List, which is defined as follows:</t>
          <figure anchor="fig-5">
            <name>Optical Interface Class List XRO Subobject</name>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|X|  Type=8     |     Length    |   Reserved    | Attribute     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//              Optical Interface Class List                   //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
   Refer to <xref target="RFC5521" format="default"/> for the definitions of
   X, Length, and Attribute.</t>
    <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
   <dt>Type (7 bits):</dt><dd>The type of the Signaling Processing Exclusion field.
   IANA has assigned value 8 for the
   Optical Interface Class List XRO subobject type.</dd>
        
   <dt>Reserved bits (8 bits):</dt><dd>These are for future use and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be zeroed and
   ignored on receipt.</dd>
         
   <dt>Attribute (8 bits):</dt><dd><xref target="RFC5521" format="default"/> defines several Attribute
   values; the only permitted Attribute values for this field are 0
   (Interface) or 1 (Node).</dd>

   <dt>Optical Interface Class List:</dt><dd>This field is encoded as
   described in <xref target="RFC7581" sectionFormat="of"
   section="4.1"/>.</dd>
    </dl>

          <t>
   The second XRO subobject type (9) is the Client Signal
   Information, which is defined as follows:</t>
          <figure anchor="fig-6">
            <name>Client Signal Information XRO Subobject</name>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|X|  Type=9     |     Length    |   Reserved    |  Attribute    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//                Client Signal Information                    //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
   Refer to <xref target="RFC5521" format="default"/> for the definitions of
   X, Length, and Attribute.</t>

<dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Type (7 bits):</dt><dd>The type of the Signaling Processing Exclusion field.
   IANA has assigned value 9 for the Client
   Signal Information XRO subobject type.</dd>
          <dt>Reserved bits (8 bits):</dt><dd>These are for future use and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be zeroed and
   ignored on receipt.</dd>
          <dt>Attribute (8 bits):</dt><dd><xref target="RFC5521"
          format="default"/> defines several Attribute values; the only
          permitted Attribute values for this field are 0 (Interface) or 1
          (Node).</dd>

   <dt>Client Signal Information:</dt><dd>This field is encoded as described
   in <xref target="RFC7581" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2"/>.</dd>
</dl>
          <t>
   The XRO needs to support the new Signaling Processing Exclusion XRO
   subobject types:</t>
     <ul empty="true"><li>
   <dl spacing="normal">  

      <dt>8:</dt><dd>Optical Interface Class List</dd>

      <dt>9:</dt><dd>Client Signal Information</dd>
   </dl>
   </li></ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sect-4.4.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Signal Processing Inclusion</name>
          <t>
   Similar to the XRO subobject, the PCC/PCE should be able to include
   particular types of signal processing along the path in order to
   handle client restriction or multi-domain path computation.
   <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/> defines how the Include Route Object (IRO) subobject is used.
   In this document, we add two new Signal Processing Inclusion
   subobjects.</t>
          <t>
   The IRO needs to support the new IRO subobject types (8 and
   9) for the PCEP IRO object <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>:</t>
 <ul empty="true"><li>
   <dl>  

      <dt>8:</dt><dd>Optical Interface Class List</dd>

      <dt>9:</dt><dd>Client Signal Information</dd>
      </dl>
      </li></ul>
          <t>
   The encoding of the Signal Processing Inclusion subobjects is
   similar to the process in <xref target="sect-4.4.1" format="default"/> where the 'X' field is replaced with the 'L'
   field; all the other fields remain the same. The 'L' field is
   described in <xref target="RFC3209" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-5" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Encoding of an RWA Path Reply</name>
      <t>
   This section provides the encoding of an RWA Path Reply for a
   wavelength allocation request as discussed in <xref target="sect-4" format="default"/>.</t>
      <section anchor="sect-5.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Wavelength Allocation TLV</name>
        <t>
   Recall that wavelength allocation can be performed by the PCE by
   means of:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="(%c)">
          <li>Explicit Label Control (ELC) where the PCE allocates
	which label to use for each interface/node along the path.</li>
          <li>A Label Set where the PCE provides a range of potential
   labels to be allocated by each node along the path.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
   Option (b) allows distributed label allocation (performed during
   signaling) to complete wavelength allocation.</t>
        <t>
   The type for the Wavelength Allocation TLV is 10 (see <xref target="sect-8.4" format="default"/>). Note
   that this TLV is used for both (a) and (b) above. The TLV data is defined
   as follows:</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-7.2">
          <name>Wavelength Allocation TLV Encoding</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Reserved           |          Flags              |M|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       Link Identifier                         |
//                          . . .                              //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                    Allocated Wavelength(s)                    |
//                        . . . .                              //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

<dl newline="false" spacing="normal">

          <dt>Reserved (16 bits):</dt><dd>Reserved for future use.</dd>
          <dt>Flags field (16 bits):</dt><dd><t>One flag bit is allocated as follows:</t>

        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>M (1 bit):</dt><dd><t>Wavelength Allocation Mode.</t>
             <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>0:</dt><dd>Indicates the allocation relies on the use of Label Sets.</dd>
              <dt>1:</dt><dd>Indicates the allocation is done using Explicit Label Control.</dd>
             
             </dl>
</dd></dl>
        <t>IANA has created a new registry to manage the Flags field
        of the Wavelength Allocation TLV.</t>
       </dd>
 
          <dt>Link Identifier:</dt><dd>Identifies the interface to which the
          assignment wavelength(s) is applied. See <xref target="sect-4.3.1"
          format="default"/> for encoding of the Link Identifier field.</dd>
          <dt>Allocated Wavelength(s):</dt>
          <dd> Indicates the allocated wavelength(s) to be associated with the
          link identifier. See <xref target="sect-4.3.2" format="default"/>
          for encoding details.</dd>
        </dl>

        <t>
   This TLV is carried in a PCRep message as an Attribute TLV <xref target="RFC5420" format="default"/>
   in the Hop Attribute subobjects <xref target="RFC7570" format="default"/> in the Explicit Route Object (ERO) <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-5.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Error Indicator</name>
        <t>
   To indicate errors associated with the RWA request, a new Error-Type
   27 (WSON RWA Error) and subsequent Error-values are defined as follows for
   inclusion in the PCEP-ERROR object:</t>

        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Error-Type=27; Error-value=1: If a PCE receives an RWA request
          and the PCE is not capable of processing the request due to
          insufficient memory, the PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr
          message with a PCEP-ERROR object with Error-Type=27 and
          Error-value=1.  The PCE stops processing the request.
          The corresponding RWA request <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be canceled at the
          PCC.</li>

          <li>Error-Type=27; Error-value=2: If a PCE receives an RWA request and the PCE
   is not capable of RWA computation, the PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr message
   with a PCEP-ERROR object with Error-Type=27 and
   Error-value=2. The PCE stops processing the request.  The
   corresponding RWA computation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be canceled at the PCC.</li>

          <li>Error-Type=27; Error-value=3: If a PCE receives an RWA request and there
   are syntactical encoding errors (e.g., not exactly two link identifiers
   with the range case, unknown identifier types, no matching link for a
   given identifier, unknown Action value, etc.), the PCE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a PCErr
   message with a PCEP-ERROR object with Error-Type=27 and Error-value=3.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-5.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>NO-PATH Indicator</name>
        <t>
   To communicate the reason(s) for not being able to find RWA for the
   path request, the NO-PATH object can be used in the corresponding
   response.  The format of the NO-PATH object body is defined in
   <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/>.  The object may contain a NO-PATH-VECTOR TLV to provide
   additional information about why a path computation has failed.</t>
        <t>
   This document defines a new bit flag to be carried in the Flags field in the
   NO-PATH-VECTOR TLV, which is carried in the NO-PATH object:</t>


        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="3">
          <dt>Bit 23:</dt>
          <dd> When set, the PCE indicates no feasible
	  route was found that meets all the constraints (e.g., wavelength
	  restriction, signal compatibility, etc.) associated with RWA.
	</dd>
        </dl>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-6" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Manageability Considerations</name>
      <t>
   Manageability of WSON RWA with
   PCE must address the considerations in the following subsections.</t>
      <section anchor="sect-6.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Control of Function and Policy</name>
        <t>
   In addition to the parameters already listed in <xref target="RFC5440" sectionFormat="of" section="8.1"/>, a PCEP implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> allow configuration of the
   following PCEP session parameters on a PCC:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The ability to send a WSON RWA request.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
   In addition to the parameters already listed in <xref target="RFC5440" sectionFormat="of" section="8.1"/>, a PCEP implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> allow configuration of the
   following PCEP session parameters on a PCE:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The support for WSON RWA.</li>
          <li>A set of WSON-RWA-specific policies (authorized sender, request
	  rate limiter, etc).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
   These parameters may be configured as default parameters for any
   PCEP session the PCEP speaker participates in, or they may apply to a
   specific session with a given PCEP peer or a specific group of
   sessions with a specific group of PCEP peers.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-6.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Liveness Detection and Monitoring</name>
        <t>
   Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness
   detection and monitoring requirements, aside from those already
   listed in <xref target="RFC5440" sectionFormat="of" section="8.3"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-6.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Verifying Correct Operation</name>
        <t>
   Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
   verification requirements, aside from those already listed in
   <xref target="RFC5440" sectionFormat="of" section="8.4"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-6.4" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements on Other Protocols and Functional Components</name>
        <t>
   The PCEP Link-State mechanism <xref target="I-D.lee-pce-pcep-ls-optical" format="default"/> may be used to advertise
   WSON RWA path computation capabilities to PCCs.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-6.5" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Impact on Network Operation</name>
        <t>
   Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new network
   operation requirements, aside from those already listed in
   <xref target="RFC5440" sectionFormat="of" section="8.6"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-7" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
   The security considerations discussed in <xref target="RFC5440" format="default"/> are relevant for
   this document; this document does not introduce any new security
   issues. If an operator wishes to keep the information
   distributed by WSON private, PCEPS (Usage of TLS to Provide a Secure Transport for PCEP) <xref target="RFC8253" format="default"/> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be used.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect-8" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
   IANA maintains a registry of PCEP parameters. IANA has made
   allocations from the subregistries as described in the following
   sections.</t>
      <section anchor="sect-8.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New PCEP Object: Wavelength Assignment Object</name>
        <t>
   As described in <xref target="sect-4.1" format="default"/>, a new PCEP
   object is defined to carry wavelength-assignment-related constraints. IANA
   has allocated the following in the "PCEP Objects" subregistry <xref
   target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Object-Class Value</th>
      <th>Name</th>
      <th>Object-Type</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>42</td>
  <td>WA</td>
  <td>0: Reserved</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
  <tr> 
  <td></td>
  <td></td>
  <td>1: Wavelength Assignment</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>WA Object Flag Field</name>
        <t>
   As described in <xref target="sect-4.1" format="default"/>, IANA has
   created the "WA Object Flag Field" subregistry under the "Path Computation
   Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry <xref target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/> to
   manage the Flags field of the WA object. New values are to be assigned by
   Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>. Each bit should
   be tracked with the following qualities:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Bit number (counting from bit 0 as the most significant bit)</li>
          <li>Capability description</li>
          <li>Defining RFC</li>
        </ul>


        <t>The initial contents of this registry are shown below. One bit has been
        allocated for the flag defined in this document:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bit</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>0-14</td>
  <td>Unassigned</td>
  <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr> 
  <td>15</td>
  <td>Wavelength Allocation Mode</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New PCEP TLV: Wavelength Selection TLV</name>
        <t>
   In <xref target="sect-4.2" format="default"/>, a new PCEP TLV is defined to
   indicate wavelength selection constraints. IANA has made the following
   allocation in the "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" subregistry <xref
   target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>8</td>
  <td>Wavelength Selection</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-8.4" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New PCEP TLV: Wavelength Restriction TLV</name>
        <t>
   In <xref target="sect-4.3" format="default"/>, a new PCEP TLV is defined to indicate
   wavelength restrictions. IANA has made the following allocation in
   the "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" subregistry <xref target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:
        </t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>9</td>
  <td>Wavelength Restriction</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.5" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Wavelength Restriction TLV Action Values</name>
        <t>
   As described in <xref target="sect-4.3" format="default"/>, IANA has
   created the new "Wavelength Restriction TLV Action Values"
   subregistry under the "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry
   <xref target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/> to
   manage the Action values of the Action field of the Wavelength
   Restriction TLV. New values are assigned by Standards
   Action <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>. Each value should be tracked with the following
   qualities: </t>
<ul spacing="normal">
<li>Value</li>
<li>Meaning</li>
<li>Defining RFC</li>
</ul>

<t>The initial contents of this registry are shown below:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Meaning</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>0</td>
  <td>Inclusive List</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
<tr> 
  <td>1</td>
  <td>Inclusive Range</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
<tr> 
  <td>2-255</td>
  <td>Unassigned</td>
  <td></td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-8.6" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New PCEP TLV: Wavelength Allocation TLV</name>
        <t>
   In <xref target="sect-5.1" format="default"/>, a new PCEP TLV
   is defined to indicate the allocation of the wavelength(s) by the PCE in
   response to a request by the PCC. IANA has made the following allocation in
   "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" subregistry <xref target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:
        </t>
<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>10</td>
  <td>Wavelength Allocation</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-8.7" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Wavelength Allocation TLV Flag Field</name>
        <t>
   As described in <xref target="sect-5.1" format="default"/>, IANA has
   created a new "Wavelength Allocation TLV Flag Field" subregistry under the
   "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry <xref
   target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/> to
   manage the Flags field of the Wavelength Allocation TLV. New values
   are to be assigned by Standards Action <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>.  Each bit should
   be tracked with the following qualities:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Bit number (counting from bit 0 as the most significant bit)</li>
          <li>Capability description</li>
          <li>Defining RFC</li>
        </ul>

   <t>One bit is defined for the flag defined in this
   document. The initial contents of this registry are shown below:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bit</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>0-14</td>
  <td>Unassigned</td>
  <td></td>
  </tr>
<tr> 
  <td>15</td>
  <td>Wavelength Allocation Mode</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.8" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New PCEP TLV: Optical Interface Class List TLV</name>
        <t>
   In <xref target="sect-4.4" format="default"/>, a new PCEP TLV is defined to
   indicate the Optical Interface Class List. IANA has made the following
   allocation in the "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" subregistry <xref
   target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:
        </t>
<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>11</td>
  <td>Optical Interface Class List</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.9" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New PCEP TLV: Client Signal Information TLV</name>
        <t>
   In <xref target="sect-4.4" format="default"/>, a new PCEP TLV is defined to
   indicate the Client Signal Information. IANA has made the following
   allocation in the "PCEP TLV Type Indicators" subregistry <xref
   target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:
        </t>
<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>12</td>
  <td>Client Signal Information</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-8.10" numbered="true" toc="default">
   	<name>New Bit Flag for NO-PATH-VECTOR TLV</name>
        <t>
   In <xref target="sect-5.3" format="default"/>, a new bit flag is defined to be
   carried in the Flags field in the NO-PATH-VECTOR TLV, which is carried in the
   NO-PATH object. This flag, when set, indicates that no feasible
   route was found that meets all the RWA constraints (e.g., wavelength
   restriction, signal compatibility, etc.) associated with an RWA path
   computation request.</t>
        <t>
   IANA has made the following allocation for this new bit flag in the
   "NO-PATH-VECTOR TLV Flag Field" subregistry <xref target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:
</t>
<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bit</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>23</td>
  <td>No RWA constraints met</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-8.11" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New Error-Types and Error-Values</name>
        <t>
   In <xref target="sect-5.2" format="default"/>, new PCEP error
   codes are defined for WSON RWA errors. IANA has made the following allocations
   in the "PCEP-ERROR Object Error Types and Values" subregistry <xref
   target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Error-Type</th>
      <th>Meaning</th>
      <th>Error-value</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>27</td>
      <td>WSON RWA error</td>
      <td>0: Unassigned</td>
      <td>RFC 8780</td>
    </tr>
     <tr>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
      <td>1: Insufficient memory</td>
      <td>RFC 8780</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
      <td>2: RWA computation not supported</td>
      <td>RFC 8780</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
     <td>3: Syntactical encoding error</td>
     <td>RFC 8780</td>
    </tr>
   <tr>
      <td></td>
      <td></td>
     <td>4-255: Unassigned</td>
     <td>RFC 8780</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-8.12" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New Subobjects for the Exclude Route Object</name>
        <t>The "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry
        contains a subregistry titled "XRO Subobjects" <xref
        target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>. Per <xref target="sect-4.4.1"
        format="default"/>, IANA has added the following subobjects that can
        be carried in the XRO:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>8</td>
  <td>Optical Interface Class List</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 <tr> 
  <td>9</td>
  <td>Client Signal Information</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sect-8.13" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New Subobjects for the Include Route Object</name>
        <t>
The "Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers" registry contains a
subregistry titled "IRO Subobjects" <xref target="PCEP-NUMBERS"/>.  Per <xref
target="sect-4.4.2" format="default"/>, IANA has added the following
subobjects that can be carried in the IRO:</t>

<table align="left">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
 </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
  <tr> 
  <td>8</td>
  <td>Optical Interface Class List</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 <tr> 
  <td>9</td>
  <td>Client Signal Information</td>
  <td>RFC 8780</td>
  </tr>
 </tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sect-8.14" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Request for Updated Note for LMP TE Link Object Class Type</name>
        <t>
   The "TE_LINK Object Class type name space (Value 11)" registry was created
   for the Link Management Protocol (LMP) <xref target="RFC4204"
   format="default"/>. As discussed in <xref target="sect-4.3.1"
   format="default"/>, IANA has added the following note at the top of the
   "TE_LINK Object Class type name space (Value 11)" registry <xref
   target="LMP-PARAM"/>:
</t>

<ul empty="true">
<li>
These values have additional usage for the Link Identifier Type field.
</li>
</ul>

      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

  
<displayreference target="I-D.lee-pce-pcep-ls-optical" to="PCEP-LS"/>

  <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3630.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5329.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5440.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6205.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7570.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7579.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7581.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7689.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7688.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8253.xml"/>

<!-- draft-ietf-pce-gmpls-pcep-extensions-16; C385 companion doc - ready for Pub-->
<reference anchor='RFC8779' target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8779">
<front>
<title>Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) Extensions for GMPLS</title>
<author initials='C' surname='Margaria' fullname='Cyril Margaria' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='O' surname='Gonzalez de Dios' fullname='Oscar Gonzalez de
							  Dios' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='F' surname='Zhang' fullname='Fatai Zhang' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2020' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8779"/>                                                               
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8779"/>     
</reference>

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3471.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4203.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4204.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5420.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5521.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6163.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6566.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7446.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7449.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>

<!--draft-lee-pce-pcep-ls-optical-08; IESG state, I-D Exists -->
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml3/reference.I-D.lee-pce-pcep-ls-optical.xml"/>


<reference anchor="PCEP-NUMBERS"
           target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/pcep/">
  <front>
    <title>Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) Numbers</title>
    <author><organization>IANA</organization></author>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="LMP-PARAM"
           target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/lmp-parameters/">
  <front>
    <title>Link Management Protocol (LMP) Parameters</title>
    <author><organization>IANA</organization></author>
  </front>
</reference>


      </references>
    </references>

  <section anchor="sect-9" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>
   The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/>, <contact fullname="Julien Meuric"/>, <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody" />,
   and <contact fullname="Benjamin Kaduk" /> for many helpful comments that greatly
   improved the contents of this document.</t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="sect-11" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>

<contact fullname="Fatai Zhang">
<organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
    <address>
          <postal>
<street/>
<city/>
<region/><code/>
<country/>
</postal>
<email>zhangfatai@huawei.com</email>
</address>
</contact>

<contact fullname="Cyril Margaria">
<organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
<address>
      <postal>
<street>St. Martin Strasse 76</street>
<city>Munich</city>
<region></region><code>81541</code>
<country>Germany</country>
</postal>
<phone>+49 89 5159 16934</phone>
<email>cyril.margaria@nsn.com</email>
</address>
</contact>

<contact fullname="Oscar Gonzalez de Dios">
<organization>Telefonica Investigacion y Desarrollo</organization>
  <address>
          <postal>
<street>C/ Emilio Vargas 6</street>
<city>Madrid</city>
<region></region><code>28043</code>
<country>Spain</country>
</postal>
<phone>+34 91 3374013</phone>
<email>ogondio@tid.es</email>
</address>
</contact>

<contact fullname="Greg Bernstein">
<organization>Grotto Networking</organization>
<address>
      <postal>
<street/>
<city>Fremont</city>
<region>CA</region><code/>
<country>United States of America</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 510 573 2237</phone>
<email>gregb@grotto-networking.com</email>
</address>
</contact>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
