<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

 <rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF"
      category="std" consensus="true" ipr="trust200902" updates="6442"
      docName="draft-ietf-sipcore-locparam-06" number="8787" obsoletes=""
      xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true"
      sortRefs="true" version="3"> 


   <front>
     <title abbrev="Location Parameter">Location Source Parameter for the SIP
     Geolocation Header Field</title> 
     <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8787"/>
     <author initials="J." surname="Winterbottom" fullname="James Winterbottom">
       <organization>Winterb Consulting Services</organization>
       <address>
	 <postal>
	   <street/>
	   <city>Gwynneville</city>
	   <region>NSW</region>
	   <code>2500</code>
	   <country>Australia</country>
	 </postal>
	 <phone>+61 448 266004</phone>
	 <email>a.james.winterbottom@gmail.com</email>
       </address>
     </author>
     <author initials="R." surname="Jesske" fullname="Roland Jesske">
       <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>
       <address>
	 <postal>
	   <street>Heinrich-Hertz Str, 3-7</street>
	   <city>Darmstadt</city>
	   <code>64295</code>
	   <country>Germany</country>
	 </postal>
	 <phone/>
	 <email>r.jesske@telekom.de</email>
	 <uri>www.telekom.de</uri>
       </address>
     </author>
     <author initials="B." surname="Chatras" fullname="Bruno Chatras">
       <organization>Orange Labs</organization>
       <address>
	 <postal>
	   <street>44, avenue de la Republique</street>
	   <city>Chatillon </city>
	   <code>F-92320</code>
	   <country>France</country>
	 </postal>
	 <phone/>
	 <email>bruno.chatras@orange.com</email>
       </address>
     </author>
     <author fullname="Andrew Hutton" initials="A." surname="Hutton">
       <organization>Atos</organization>
       <address>
	 <postal>
	   <street>Mid City Place</street>
	   <city>London</city>
	   <code>WC1V 6EA</code>
	   <country>United Kingdom</country>
	 </postal>
	 <phone/>
	 <email>andrew.hutton@atos.net</email>
       </address>
     </author>
     <date year="2020" month="May"/>
     <area>ART</area>
     <workgroup>SIPCORE</workgroup>
     <keyword>Emergency</keyword>
     <keyword>Call</keyword>
     <keyword>Location</keyword>
     <abstract>
       <t>There are some circumstances where a Geolocation header field may
       contain more than one locationValue. Knowing the identity of the node
       adding the locationValue allows the recipient more freedom in selecting
       the value to look at first rather than relying solely on the order of
       the locationValues.  This document defines the "loc-src" parameter so
       that the entity adding the locationValue to the Geolocation header
       field can identify itself using its hostname.  This document updates
       RFC 6442.
       </t>
     </abstract>
   </front>
   <middle>


     <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Introduction</name>

       <t>
	  The SIP Geolocation specification <xref target="RFC6442"
	  format="default"/> describes the "Geolocation" SIP header field,
	  which is used to indicate that the SIP message is conveying location
	  information. <xref target="RFC6442" format="default"/> specifies
	  that SIP intermediaries should not add locationValues to a SIP
	  request that already contains a locationValue.  <xref target="RFC6442"
	  format="default"/> also states that if a SIP intermediary adds
	  location, it is fully responsible for addressing the concerns of any
	  424 (Bad Location Information) SIP response it receives.

	  However, some communications architectures, such as 3GPP <xref
	  target="TS23-167" format="default"/> and ETSI <xref target="M493"
	  format="default"/>, prefer to use information provided by edge
	  proxies or acquired through the use of core-network nodes before
	  using information provided solely by user equipment (UE). These
	  solutions don't preclude the use of UE-provided location but require
	  a means of being able to distinguish the identity of the node adding
	  the locationValue to the SIP message from that provided by the UE.
       </t>
       <t>         
	  <xref target="RFC6442" format="default"/> stipulates that the order
	  of locationValues in the Geolocation header field is the same as the
	  order in which they were added to the header field. Whilst this
	  order provides guidance to the recipient as to which values were
	  added to the message earlier in the communication chain, it does not
	  identify which node added the locationValue. Knowing the identity of
	  the entity that added the location to the message allows the
	  recipient to choose which location to consider first rather than
	  relying solely on the order of the locationValues in the Geolocation
	  header field.


       </t>
       <t>
	 This document extends the Geolocation header field of <xref
	 target="RFC6442" format="default"/> by allowing an entity adding the
	 locationValue to identify itself using a hostname. This is done by
	 defining a new geoloc-param header field parameter, "loc-src". How
	 the entity adding the locationValue to the header field obtains the
	 location information is out of scope of this document.  Please note
	 that the "loc-src" parameter field does not alter the subject of the
	 locationValue.
       </t>
     </section>


       <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Terminology</name>


        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are
    to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
    <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals,
    as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="rationale" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Rationale</name>
      <t>The primary intent of the "loc-src" parameter in this specification is for use in
         emergency calling. There are various architectures defined for providing 
         emergency calling using SIP-based messaging. Each has its own characteristics
         with corresponding pros and cons. All of them allow the UE to provide location
         information; however, many also attach other sources of location information to
         support veracity checks, to provide backup information, or to be used as the primary
         location. 
      </t>
      <t> This document does not comment on these various architectures or on
      the rationale for including multiple locationValues. It does recognize
      that these architectures exist and that there is a need to identify the
      entity adding the location information.
      </t>

      <t>The "loc-src" parameter adds the location source generating the
      locationValue to allow recipients to make informed decisions about which
      of the multiple values to use.
      </t>
      <t> The "loc-src" parameter is applicable within a single
         private administrative domain or between different administrative
         domains where there is a trust relationship between the domains.           
           
           
         Thus, it is intended to use this parameter only in trust domains 
         where Spec(T) as described in <xref target="RFC3325" format="default"/> exists.  
      </t>
      <t>The "loc-src" parameter is not included in a SIP message
         sent to another network if there is no trust relationship.  
         The "loc-src" parameter is not applicable if the administrative domain manages
         emergency calls in a way that does not require any  generation of the location.

      </t>
      <t> 
        The functional architecture to support emergency caller location described within ETSI <xref target="M493" format="default"/> is an
    example of an architecture where it makes sense to use this
    parameter.

      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="mechanism" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Mechanism</name>
      <t>     
    The mechanism adds a geoloc-param parameter to the locationValue
    defined in <xref target="RFC6442" format="default"/> that identifies the hostname of the entity
    adding the locationValue to the Geolocation header field.
      
      The Augmented BNF (ABNF) <xref target="RFC5234"
      format="default"/> for this parameter is shown in <xref target="ABNF"
      format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="ABNF">
        <name>Location Source</name>
<sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
       location-source = "loc-src" EQUAL hostname
       hostname = <defined in RFC 3261>
]]></sourcecode>  

      </figure>
      <t> Only a fully qualified host name is valid.  The syntax does not
      support IP addresses, and if an entity conforming to this specification
      receives a Geolocation header field with a "loc-src" parameter
      containing an IP address, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> remove the
      parameter.</t>
      <t>A SIP intermediary conformant to this specification adding a
      locationValue to a Geolocation header field <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> also
      add a "loc-src" header field parameter so that it is clearly identified
      as the node adding the location. A User Agent (UA) <bcp14>MUST
      NOT</bcp14> insert a "loc-src" header field parameter. If a SIP
      intermediary receives a message from an untrusted source with the
      "loc-src" parameter set, then it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> remove the "loc-src"
      parameter before passing the message into a trusted network.
      </t>
    </section>

	<section anchor="example" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Example</name>
      <t>
		The following example shows a SIP INVITE message containing a
		Geolocation header field with two locationValues. The first
		locationValue points to a Presence Information Data Format
		Location Object (PIDF-LO) in the SIP body using a
		content-indirection (cid:) URI per <xref target="RFC4483"
		format="default"/>, and this is provided by the UE. The second
		locationValue is an https URI provided by a SIP intermediary,
		which identifies itself using the "loc-src" parameter.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="locationRequest">
        <name>Example Location Request (in Trust Domain)</name>
<sourcecode>        
   INVITE sip:bob@biloxi.example.com SIP/2.0
   Via: SIP/2.0/TLS pc33.atlanta.example.com;branch=z9hG4bK74bf9
   Max-Forwards: 70
   To: Bob &lt;sip:bob@biloxi.example.com&gt;
   From: Alice &lt;sip:alice@atlanta.example.com&gt;;tag=9fxced76sl
   Call-ID: 3848276298220188511@atlanta.example.com
   Geolocation: &lt;cid:target123@atlanta.example.com&gt;,
        &lt;https://lis.example.com:8222/y77syc7cuecbh&gt;;
                 loc-src=edgeproxy.example.com
   Geolocation-Routing: yes
   Accept: application/sdp, application/pidf+xml
   CSeq: 31862 INVITE
   Contact: &lt;sip:alice@atlanta.example.com&gt;
   Content-Type: multipart/mixed; boundary=boundary1
   Content-Length: ...
   </sourcecode>
      </figure>
    </section>

 

    <section anchor="privacy" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>This document doesn't change any of the privacy considerations described in
         <xref target="RFC6442" format="default"/>. While the addition of the "loc-src"
    parameter identifies the entity that added the location in the
    signaling path, this addition provides little more exposure
    than adding a proxy identity to the Record-Route header field (privacy defined in <xref target="RFC3323" format="default"/>).</t>
    </section>


    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document introduces the ability of a SIP intermediary to insert
        a host name indicating that they added the specific locationValue to the
        Geolocation header field. The intent is for this field to be used by the location
        recipient in the event that the SIP message contains multiple locationValues.
        As a consequence, this parameter should only be used by the location recipient
        in a trusted network. Adding this parameter in an untrusted network serves solely to give location information to untrusted parties and is <bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>.     
      </t>
      <t> As already stated in <xref target="RFC6442" format="default"/>,
      securing the location hop by hop, using TLS, protects the message from
      eavesdropping and modification in transit but exposes the information
      to all SIP intermediaries on the path as well as the endpoint. The
      "loc-src" parameter is applicable within a single private administrative
      domain or between different administrative domains where there is a
      relationship between the domains. If such a trust relationship is not
      given, it is strongly recommended to delete the location information.
      </t>
      <t>
The use of this parameter is not restricted to a specific architecture, but
using multiple locations and loc-src may end in compatibility issues. <xref
target="RFC6442" format="default"/> already addresses the issue of multiple
locations.  To avoid problems of a possible corruption of the location
information including the "loc-src" parameter when using an untrusted
relationship, it is strongly recommended to delete location information when
passed to another domain out of the trust domain.

      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Registration of "loc-src" Parameter for Geolocation Header Field</name>
        <t>IANA has added a new SIP header field parameter for
    the Geolocation header field in the "Header Field Parameters and
    Parameter Values" subregistry (created by <xref target="RFC3968" format="default"/>) of the
    "Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Parameters" registry found at
    <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/sip-parameters/" brackets="angle"/>.

        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Header Field:</dt>
          <dd>Geolocation</dd>
          <dt>Parameter Name:</dt>
          <dd>loc-src</dd>
          <dt>Predefined Values:</dt>
          <dd>No</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt>
          <dd>RFC 8787</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>


  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6442.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3325.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3968.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3323.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4483.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="TS23-167">
          <front>
            <title>Technical Specification Group Services and System Aspects; IP Multimedia Subsystem (IMS) emergency sessions
            </title>

            <author>
              <organization>3rd Generation Partnership Project
              </organization>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="2015"/>
          </front>
	  <refcontent>TS 23.167</refcontent>
	  <refcontent>V12.1.0
	  </refcontent>
    </reference>

        <reference anchor="M493">
          <front>
            <title>Functional architecture to support European requirements 
               on emergency caller location determination and transport</title>
            <author>
              <organization>
                   European Telecommunications Standards Institute
              </organization>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2015"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>ES 203 178</refcontent>
	  <refcontent>V 1.1.1
	  </refcontent>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Dale Worley"/>,
      <contact fullname="Christer Holmberg"/>, and <contact fullname="Jean Mahoney"/> for their
      extensive review of this document.  The authors would like to
      acknowledge the constructive feedback provided by <contact fullname="Paul Kyzivat"/> and
      <contact fullname="Robert Sparks"/>.</t>
    </section>

  </back>

</rfc>
