<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" number="8719" category="bcp"
     seriesNo="226" docName="draft-ietf-mtgvenue-meeting-policy-07"
     ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true" xml:lang="en"
     obsoletes="" updates="" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true"
     sortRefs="true" version="3"> 
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.37.1 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IETF Meeting Policy">High-Level Guidance for the Meeting
    Policy of the IETF</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8719"/>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="226"/>
    <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S." surname="Krishnan">
      <organization>Kaloom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>suresh@kaloom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2020"/>
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Meeting Venue Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>geographic distribution location</keyword>
    <keyword>IASA</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a meeting location policy for the IETF and
      the various stakeholders required to realize this policy.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
The work of the IETF is primarily conducted on working group (WG)
mailing lists, while face-to-face WG meetings mainly provide a high-bandwidth
mechanism for working out unresolved issues. The IETF 
currently strives to have a 1-1-1 meeting policy
where the goal is to distribute the meetings equally between North America,
Europe, and Asia (see "Meeting Location Distribution" (slides 14 and 15) of
<xref target="IETFMEET" format="default"/> for details). These are the
locations from which most of the IETF participants have come in the recent past.
This meeting rotation is mainly aimed at distributing the travel effort for
the existing IETF participants who physically attend meetings and for
distributing the timezone difficulty for those who participate remotely.
This policy has been neither defined precisely nor documented in an
IETF consensus document until now. This BCP RFC is meant to serve as a
consensus-backed statement of this policy. 
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>The 1-1-1-* Meeting Policy</name>
      <t>Given that the majority of the current meeting participants come from
   North America, Europe, and Asia <xref target="CONT-DIST" format="default"/>, the
   IETF policy is that the meetings should primarily be held in those
   regions. That is, the meeting policy (let's call this the "1-1-1"
   policy) is that meetings should rotate between North America,
   Europe, and Asia. Note that the boundaries between those
   regions have been purposefully left undefined. It
   is important to note that such rotation and any effects to
   distributing travel pain should be considered from a long-term
   perspective. While a potential cycle in an IETF year may be a
   meeting in North America in March, a meeting in Europe in July, and
   a meeting in Asia on November, the 1-1-1 policy does not imply
   such a cycle, as long as the distribution to these regions over
   multiple years is roughly equal. There are many reasons why meetings
   might be distributed differently in a given year. Meeting locations in
   subsequent years should seek to rebalance the distribution, if
   possible.</t>
      <t>While this meeting rotation caters to the current set of IETF
   participants, it is important to recognize that due to the dynamic and
   evolving nature of participation, there may be significant changes
   to the regions that provide a major share of participants in the
   future. Therefore, the 1-1-1-* meeting policy is a slightly modified version
   of the aforementioned 1-1-1 meeting policy that allows for
   additional flexibility in the form of an exploratory meeting (denoted with
   an "*"). Exploratory meetings can be used to experiment with
   exceptional meetings without extensively impacting the regular
   meetings. For example, these exploratory meetings can include meetings in
   other geographical regions, virtual meetings, and additional
   meetings beyond the three regular meetings in a calendar year. 
      </t>
      <t>
  The timing and frequency of future exploratory meetings will be based
  on IETF consensus as determined by the IETF chair. Once a meeting 
  proposal is initiated, the IESG will make a decision in consultation with 
  the IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA) <xref target="RFC8711"
  format="default"/> to ensure that the proposal can be realistically
  implemented. The final decision will be communicated back to the
   community to ensure that there is adequate opportunity to comment.
      </t>

      <aside><t>NOTE: There have not been a large number of meetings that would
qualify as exploratory meetings under the 1-1-1 policy (with
IETF 95 in Buenos Aires and IETF 47 in Adelaide being the exceptional
instances). IETF 27 (Amsterdam) and IETF 54 (Yokohama) were earlier
examples of exploratory meetings that pioneered Europe and Asia as
regular IETF destinations.</t></aside>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Implementation of the Policy</name>
      <t>IASA should understand the policy
      written in this document to be the aspiration of the IETF community. Similarly, any
   exploratory meeting decisions will also be communicated to the IASA to
   be implemented. The actual selection of the venue would be
   performed by the IASA following the process described in <xref
   target="RFC8718" format="default"/>. 
      </t>
      <t>As mentioned in <xref target="RFC8718" format="default"/>, the IASA will also be responsible for the following:  
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>assisting the community in the development of detailed meeting
     criteria that are feasible and implementable, and </li>
        <li>providing sufficient transparency in a timely manner
     concerning planned meetings so that community feedback can be
     collected and acted upon.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Given that the geographical location of the venue has a
   significant influence on the venue selection process, it needs to
   be considered at the same level as the other Important Criteria
   specified in <xref target="RFC8718" sectionFormat="of" section="3.2" format="default"/> (including
   potentially trading-off the geographical region to meet other
   criteria and notifying the community if the geographical region
   requirement cannot be met).</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Procedure for Initiating Proposals for Exploratory Meetings</name>
      <t>Someone who is interested in pursuing an exploratory venue
      proposes it on the IETF discussion list or on a future
      discussion list expressly set up and announced for this
      purpose. The community gets to comment on the venue and offer
      their opinions. If the IETF chair determines that there is
      community consensus to pursue the venue further, the venue will
      be put up for discussion on the venue-selection mailing
      list &lt;<eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/venue-selection"/>&gt;. 
      This would allow the interested party(ies) to refine their proposal
      based on insightful feedback regarding the logistics of the venue
      from those tasked with evaluating it. Once the venue selection process
      takes place, the final decision will be communicated back to the
      community to ensure that there is adequate opportunity to comment.
</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Re-evaluation and Changes to This Policy</name>
      <t>Given the dynamic nature of participant distribution in the
      IETF, it is expected that this policy will need to be periodically
      evaluated and revised to ensure that the stated goals continue
      to be met. The criteria that are to be met need to be agreed upon by the
      community prior to initiating a revision of this document (e.g., try to
      mirror draft author distribution over the preceding five years).
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC8711"
		   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8711">
          <front>
            <title>Structure of the IETF Administrative Support Activity, Version 2.0</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Haberman">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Hall">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Livingood">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2020"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8711"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8711"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="RFC8718" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8718">
          <front>
            <title>IETF Plenary Meeting Venue Selection Process</title>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8718"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8718"/>
            <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="226"/>
            <author initials="E" surname="Lear" fullname="Eliot Lear" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2020"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CONT-DIST" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/stats/meeting/continent/">
          <front>
            <title>Number of attendees per continent across meetings</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IETFMEET" target="https://www.ietf.org/proceedings/79/slides/plenaryw-3.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>IAOC Report IETF79</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Hinden" fullname="Bob Hinden">
              <organization>IAOC Plenary Presentation</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="R" surname="Pelletier" fullname="R. Pelletier">
              <organization>IAOC Plenary Presentation</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="November" year="2010"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The author would like to thank 
      <contact fullname="Jari Arkko"/>,
      <contact fullname="Alia Atlas"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Fred Baker"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Brian Carpenter"/>,
      <contact fullname="Alissa Cooper"/>,
      <contact fullname="Dave Crocker"/>,
      <contact fullname="Spencer Dawkins"/>,
      <contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/>,
      <contact fullname="Tobias Gondrom"/>,
      <contact fullname="Eric Gray"/>,
      <contact fullname="Bob Hinden"/>,
      <contact fullname="Ole Jacobsen"/>,
      <contact fullname="Olaf Kolkman"/>,
      <contact fullname="Eliot Lear"/>,
      <contact fullname="Andrew Malis"/>,
      <contact fullname="Yoav Nir"/>,
      <contact fullname="Ray Pelletier"/>,
      <contact fullname="Melinda Shore"/>,
      <contact fullname="John Klensin"/>,
      <contact fullname="Charles Eckel"/>,
      <contact fullname="Russ Housley"/>,
      <contact fullname="Andrew Sullivan"/>,
      <contact fullname="Eric Rescorla"/>,
      <contact fullname="Richard Barnes"/>,
      <contact fullname="Cullen Jennings"/>,
      <contact fullname="Ted Lemon"/>,
      <contact fullname="Lou Berger"/>,
      <contact fullname="John Levine"/>,
      <contact fullname="Adam Roach"/>,
      <contact fullname="Mark Nottingham"/>,
      <contact fullname="Tom Petch"/>,
      <contact fullname="Randy Bush"/>,
      <contact fullname="Roni Even"/>,
      <contact fullname="Julien Meuric"/>,
      <contact fullname="Lloyd Wood"/>,
      <contact fullname="Alvaro Retana"/>,
      and
      <contact fullname="Martin Vigoureux"/> for their ideas
      and comments to improve this document. </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
