<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.2.13 -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-iab-for-the-users-04" number="8890" submissionType="IAB"
     category="info" consensus="true" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en"
     tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">  

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.34.0 -->
  <front>
    <title>The Internet is for End Users</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8890"/>
    <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
      <organization/>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <city>Prahran</city><region>VIC</region>
	  <country>Australia</country>
	</postal>
        <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>
        <uri>https://www.mnot.net/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2020" month="August"/>
    <keyword>stakeholder</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document explains why the IAB believes that, when there is a
      conflict between the interests of end users of the Internet and other
      parties, IETF decisions should favor end users. It also explores how
      the IETF can more effectively achieve this.</t> 
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Many who participate in the IETF are most comfortable making what we
      believe to be purely technical decisions; our process 
      favors technical merit through our well-known mantra of "rough consensus
      and running code."</t> 
      <t>Nevertheless, the running code that results from our process (when
      things work well) inevitably has an impact beyond technical
      considerations, because the underlying decisions afford some uses while
      discouraging others. While we believe we are making only technical
      decisions, in reality, we are defining (in some degree) what is possible
      on the Internet itself.</t> 
      <t>This impact has become significant. As the Internet increasingly
      mediates essential functions in societies, it has unavoidably become
      profoundly political; it has helped people overthrow governments,
      revolutionize social orders, swing elections, control populations,
      collect data about individuals, and reveal secrets. It has created
      wealth for some individuals and companies while destroying that of others.</t> 
      <t>All of this raises the question: For whom do we go through the pain
      of gathering rough consensus and writing running code?</t> 
      <t>After all, there are a variety of parties that standards can benefit,
      such as (but not limited to) end users, network operators, schools,
      equipment vendors, specification authors, specification implementers,
      content owners, governments, nongovernmental organizations, social
      movements, employers, and parents.</t> 
      <t>Successful specifications will provide some benefit to all the
      relevant parties because standards do not represent a zero-sum
      game. However, there are sometimes situations where there is a conflict
      between the needs of two (or more) parties.</t> 
      <t>In these situations, when one of those parties is an "end user" of
      the Internet -- for example, a person using a web browser, mail client,
      or another agent that connects to the Internet -- the Internet
      Architecture Board argues that the IETF should favor their interests
      over those of other parties.</t> 
      <t><xref target="who" format="default"/> explains what is meant by "end
      users", <xref target="why" format="default"/> outlines why IETF work
      should prioritize them, and <xref target="how" format="default"/>
      describes how we can do that.</t> 
    </section>
    <section anchor="who" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Who Are "End Users"?</name>
      <t>In this document, "end users" means human users whose activities
      IETF standards support, sometimes
      indirectly. Thus, the end user of a protocol to manage routers is not a
      router administrator; it is the people using the network that the router
      operates within.</t> 
      <t>End users are not necessarily a homogenous group; they might have
      different views of how the Internet should work and might occupy
      several roles, such as a seller, buyer, publisher, reader, service
      provider, and consumer. An end user might browse the Web, monitor
      remote equipment, play a game, videoconference with colleagues,
      send messages to friends, or perform an operation in a remote
      surgery theater. They might be "at the keyboard" or represented by
      software indirectly (e.g., as a daemon).</t> 
      <t>Likewise, an individual end user might have many interests (e.g.,
      privacy, security, flexibility, reachability) that are sometimes in
      tension.</t> 
      <t>A person whose interests we need to consider might not directly be
      using a specific system connected to the Internet. For example, if a
      child is using a browser, the interests of that child's parents or
      guardians may be relevant. A person pictured in a photograph may have an
      interest in systems that process that photograph; a person entering a
      room with sensors that send data to the Internet may have interests that may
      be involved in our deliberations about how those sensor readings are
      handled.</t> 
      <t>While such less-direct interactions between people and the Internet
      may be harder to evaluate, this document's concept of "end user"
      nonetheless includes such people.</t> 
    </section>
    <section anchor="why" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Why the IETF Should Prioritize End Users</name>
      <t>Even before the IETF was established, the Internet technical
      community has focused on user needs since at least <xref
      target="RFC0001" format="default"/>, which stated that "One of our goals
      must be to stimulate the immediate and easy use by a wide class of
      users."</t> 
      <t>And, while we specialize in technical matters, the IETF is not
      neutral about the purpose of its work in developing the Internet; in "A 
      Mission Statement for the IETF" <xref target="RFC3935"
      format="default"/>, the definitions include:</t>  
<blockquote>The IETF community wants the Internet to succeed because we
believe that the existence of the Internet, and its influence on economics,
communication, and education, will help us to build a better human
society.</blockquote> 
      <t>Later, in "The Scope of the Internet" (<xref target="RFC3935" sectionFormat="of" section="4.1"/>),
      it says:</t> 
<blockquote>The Internet isn't value-neutral, and neither is the IETF. We want
the Internet to be useful for communities that share our commitment to
openness and fairness. We embrace technical concepts such as decentralized
control, edge-user empowerment and sharing of resources, because those
concepts resonate with the core values of the IETF community. These concepts
have little to do with the technology that's possible, and much to do with the
technology that we choose to create.</blockquote> 
      <t>In other words, the IETF develops and maintains
      the Internet to promote the social good. The society that the IETF
      is attempting to enhance is composed of end users, along with groups of
      them forming businesses, governments, clubs, civil society
      organizations, and other institutions.</t> 
      <t>Merely advancing the measurable success of the Internet (e.g.,
      deployment size, bandwidth, latency, number of users) is not an adequate
      goal; doing so ignores how technology is so often used as a lever to
      assert power over users, rather than empower them.</t> 
      <t>Beyond fulfilling the IETF's mission, prioritizing end users can also
      help to ensure the long-term health of the Internet and the IETF's
      relevance to it. Perceptions of capture by vendors or other providers
      harm both; the IETF's work will (deservedly) lose end users' trust if it
      prioritizes (or is perceived to prioritize) others' interests over
      them.</t> 
      <t>Ultimately, the Internet will succeed or fail based upon the actions
      of its end users, because they are the driving force behind its growth
      to date. Not prioritizing them jeopardizes the network effect that the
      Internet relies upon to provide so much value.</t> 
    </section>
    <section anchor="how" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>How the IETF Can Prioritize End Users</name>
      <t>There are a few ways that the IAB believes the IETF community can
      prioritize end users, based upon our observations. This
      is not a complete list.</t> 
      <section anchor="engaging-the-internet-community" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Engaging the Internet Community</name>
        <t>The IETF community does not have any unique insight into what is
	"good for end users", and it is not uncommon for us to be at a further
	disadvantage because of our close understanding of some -- but not all
	-- aspects of the Internet.</t> 
        <t>At the same time, we have a culture of considerable deference to
	a broader "Internet community" -- roughly what this document calls end
	users -- in our decision-making processes. Mere deference, however, is
	not adequate; even with the best intentions, we cannot assume that our
	experiences of the Internet are those of all of its end users or that
	our decisions have a positive impact upon them.</t> 
        <t>Therefore, we have not only a responsibility to analyze and
	consider the impacts of the IETF's work, but also a responsibility to
	consult with that greater Internet community. In particular, we should
	do so when one of our decisions has a potential impact upon end
	users.</t> 
        <t>The IETF community faces significant hurdles in doing so. Our work
	is specialized and often esoteric, and processes for developing
	standards often involve very long timescales. Affected parties are
	rarely technical experts, and they often base their understanding of the Internet 
	upon incomplete (and sometimes inaccurate) models. Often,
	even when we try to engage a broader audience, their participation is
	minimal -- until a change affects someone in a way they don't
	like. Surprising the Internet community is rarely a good outcome.</t> 
        <t>Government-sponsored individuals sometimes participate in the IETF
	community. While this is welcome, it should not be taken as
	automatically representative of end users elsewhere, or even all end
	users in the relevant jurisdiction. Furthermore, what is desirable in
	one jurisdiction (or at least to its administrators) might be
	detrimental in others (see <xref target="conflict"
	format="default"/>).</t> 
        <t>While some civil society organizations specialize in technology and
	Internet policy, they rarely can
	participate broadly, nor are they necessarily representative of the
	larger Internet community. Nevertheless, their understanding of
	end-user needs is often profound, and they are in many ways the
	best-informed advocates for end-user concerns; they should be
	considered a primary channel for engaging the broader Internet
	community.</t>  
        <t>A promising approach to help fill these gaps is to identify and
	engage with specifically affected communities when making decisions
	that might affect them, for example, one or more industry
	associations, user groups, or a set of individuals, though we can't 
	formally ensure that they are appropriately representative.</t> 
        <t>In doing so, we should not require them to  "come to us"; unless a
	stakeholder community is already engaged in the IETF process
	effectively, the IETF community should explore how to meet with them
	on their terms -- take the initiative to contact them, explain our
	work, and solicit their feedback.</t> 
        <t>In particular, while IAB workshops, BOFs, and Bar BOFs can be an
	effective mechanism to gather input within our community, they rarely
	have the visibility into other communities that is required to
	solicit input, much less effective participation.</t> 
        <t>Instead, an event like a workshop may be more effective if
	co-located with -- and ideally hosted or co-hosted by -- a forum that's
	familiar to that stakeholder community. We should also 
	raise the visibility of IETF work (or potential IETF
	work) in such fora through conference talks, panels, newsletter
	articles, etc.</t> 
        <t>For example, the IAB ESCAPE workshop <xref
	target="RFC8752" format="default"/> solicited input from Internet
	publishers and advertisers about a proposal that might affect them.
	While the workshop was considered successful,
	participation might have been improved by identifying an appropriate
	industry forum and working with them to host the event.</t> 
        <t>When we engage with the Internet community, we should also clearly
	identify tailored feedback mechanisms (e.g., subscribing to a mailing
	list may not be appropriate) and assure that they are well known in
	those communities.</t> 
        <t>The Internet Society can be an invaluable partner in these efforts;
	their focus on the Internet community, policy expertise, and resources
	can help to facilitate discussions with the appropriate parties.</t> 
        <t>Finally, we should remember that the RFC Series contains Requests For
	Comments; if there are serious implications of our work, we should
	document them and ask for feedback from the Internet community.</t> 
      </section>
      <section anchor="creating-user-focused-systems" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Creating User-Focused Systems</name>
        <t>We should pay particular attention to the kinds of architectures we
	create and whether they encourage or discourage an Internet that
	works for end users.</t> 
        <t>For example, one of the most successful Internet applications is
	the Web, which uses the HTTP application protocol. One of HTTP's key
	implementation roles is that of the web browser -- called the "user
	agent" in <xref target="RFC7230" format="default"/> and other
	specifications.</t> 
        <t>User agents act as intermediaries between a service and the end
	user; rather than downloading an executable program from a service
	that has arbitrary access into the users' system, the user agent only
	allows limited access to display content and run code in a sandboxed
	environment. End users are diverse and the ability of a few user
	agents to represent individual interests properly is imperfect, but
	this arrangement is an improvement over the alternative -- the need to
	trust a website completely with all information on your system to
	browse it.</t> 
        <t>Defining the user agent role in standards also creates a virtuous
	cycle; it allows multiple implementations, allowing end users
	to switch between them with relatively low costs (although there are
	concerns about the complexity of the Web creating barriers to entry
	for new implementations). This creates an incentive for implementers
	to consider the users' needs carefully, which are often reflected into
	the defining standards.  The resulting ecosystem has many
	remaining problems, but a distinguished user agent role provides an
	opportunity to improve it.</t> 
        <t>In contrast, the Internet of Things (IoT) has not yet seen the
	broad adoption of a similar role; many current systems require opaque,
	vendor-specific software or hardware for the user-facing
	component. Perhaps as a result of this, that ecosystem and its end
	users face serious challenges.</t> 
      </section>
      <section anchor="identifying-negative-end-user-impact" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Identifying Negative End-User Impact</name>
        <t>At its best, our work will unambiguously build a better human
	society. Sometimes, we will consciously be neutral and
	open-ended, allowing the "tussle" among stakeholders to produce a
	range of results (see <xref target="TUSSLE" format="default"/> for
	further discussion).</t> 
        <t>At the very least, however, we must examine our work for negative
	impact on end users and take steps to mitigate it where
	encountered. In particular, when we've identified a conflict between
	the interests of end users and other stakeholders, we should err on
	the side of protecting end users.</t> 
        <t>Note that "negative impact on end users" is not defined in this
	document; that is something that the relevant body (e.g., working
	group) needs to discuss and come to consensus on. Merely asserting
	that something is harmful is not adequate. The converse is also true,
	though; it's not good practice to avoid identifying harms, nor is it
	acceptable to ignore them when brought to our attention.</t> 
        <t>The IAB and IETF have already established a body of guidance for
	situations where this conflict is common, including (but not
	limited to) <xref target="RFC7754" format="default"/> on filtering,
	<xref target="RFC7258" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC7624"
	format="default"/> on pervasive surveillance, <xref target="RFC7288"
	format="default"/> on host firewalls, and <xref target="RFC6973"
	format="default"/> regarding privacy considerations.</t> 
        <t>Much of that advice has focused on maintaining the end-to-end
	properties of a connection <xref target="RFC3724"
	format="default"/>. This does not mean that our responsibility to end
	users stops there; decisions might affect them in other ways. For
	example, data collection by various applications even inside otherwise
	secure connections is a major problem on the Internet today. Also,
	inappropriate concentration of power on the Internet has become a
	concerning phenomenon -- one that protocol design might have some
	influence upon.</t> 
      </section>
      <section anchor="conflict" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Handling Conflicting End-User Needs</name>
        <t>When the needs of different end users conflict (for example, two
	sets of end users both have reasonable desires), we again should try to
	minimize negative impact.</t> 
        <t>For example, when a decision improves the Internet for end users in
	one jurisdiction, but at the cost of potential harm to others
	elsewhere, that is not a good trade-off. As such, we design
	the Internet for the pessimal environment; if a user can be harmed,
	they probably will be, somewhere.</t> 
        <t>There may be cases where genuine technical need requires
	compromise. However, such trade-offs are carefully examined and avoided
	when there are alternate means of achieving the desired goals. If they
	cannot be, these choices and reasoning ought to be thoroughly
	documented.</t> 
      </section>
      <section anchor="deprioritising-internal-needs" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Deprioritizing Internal Needs</name>
        <t>There are several needs that are very visible to us as
	specification authors but should explicitly not be prioritized over
	the needs of end users.</t> 
        <t>These include convenience for document editors, IETF process
	matters, and "architectural purity" for its own sake.</t> 
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document does not have any direct security impact; however,
      failing to prioritize end users might well affect their security
      negatively in the long term.</t> 
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0001.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3724.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3935.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7258.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7288.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7624.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7754.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8752.xml"/>

      <reference anchor="TUSSLE" target="https://groups.csail.mit.edu/ana/Publications/PubPDFs/Tussle2002.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Tussle in Cyberspace: Defining Tomorrow's Internet</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Clark" fullname="David D. Clark">
            <organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="K." surname="Sollins" fullname="Karen R. Sollins">
            <organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Wroclawski" fullname="John Wroclawski">
            <organization>MIT Lab for Computer Science</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Braden" fullname="Robert Braden">
            <organization>USC Information Sciences Institute</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2002"/>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/633025.633059"/>
      </reference>

    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>IAB Members at the Time of Approval</name>
<t>Internet Architecture Board members at the time this document was approved   
for publication were:</t>
      <ul empty="true" spacing="compact">
        <li><t><contact fullname="Jari Arkko"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Alissa Cooper"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Wes Hardaker"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Ted Hardie"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Christian Huitema"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Zhenbin Li"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Erik Nordmark"/></t></li>
	<li><t><contact fullname="Mark Nottingham"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Melinda Shore"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Jeff Tantsura"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Martin Thomson"/></t></li>
        <li><t><contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/></t></li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgements" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Many discussions influenced this document, both inside and
      outside of the IETF and IAB. In particular, <contact fullname="Edward
      Snowden"/>'s comments regarding the priority of end users at IETF 93 and
      the HTML5 Priority of Constituencies were both influential.</t>   
      <t>Many people gave feedback and input, including <contact
      fullname="Harald Alvestrand"/>, <contact fullname="Mohamed Boucadair"/>,
      <contact fullname="Joe
      Hildebrand"/>, <contact fullname="Lee Howard"/>, <contact fullname="Russ
      Housley"/>, <contact fullname="Niels ten Oever"/>, <contact
      fullname="Mando Rachovitsa"/>, <contact fullname="John
      Klensin"/>, and <contact fullname="Eliot Lear"/>.</t>   
    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
