<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF"
     category="std" consensus="true"
     docName="draft-ietf-regext-login-security-10" number="8807"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true"
     tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3"> 

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.40.1 -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Login Security Extension for the EPP">
    Login Security Extension for the Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8807"/>
    <author fullname="James Gould" initials="J." surname="Gould">
      <organization>VeriSign, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20190</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jgould@verisign.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.verisign.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Matthew Pozun" initials="M." surname="Pozun">
      <organization>VeriSign, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
          <city>Reston</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20190</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mpozun@verisign.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.verisign.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2020"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) includes a client
      authentication scheme that is based on a user identifier and
      password. The structure of the password field is defined by an XML
      Schema data type that specifies minimum and maximum password length
      values, but there are no other provisions for password management other
      than changing the password. 
  
      This document describes an EPP extension
      that allows longer passwords to be created and adds additional security
      features to the EPP login command and response.</t> 
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document describes an Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)
      extension for enhancing the security of the EPP login command in EPP
      <xref target="RFC5730" format="default"/>. EPP <xref target="RFC5730"
      format="default"/> includes a maximum password length of 16 characters,
      which inhibits implementing stronger password security policies with
      higher entropy. The enhancements include supporting longer passwords (or
      passphrases) than the 16-character maximum and providing a list of
      security events in the login response.  The password (current and new)
      in EPP <xref target="RFC5730" format="default"/> can be overridden by
      the password included in the extension to extend past the 16-character
      maximum. The security events supported include password expiry, client
      certificate expiry, insecure cipher, insecure TLS protocol, new password
      complexity, login security statistical warning, and a custom event.  The
      attributes supported by the security events include an identified event
      type or a subtype, an indicated security level of
      warning or error, a future or past-due expiration date, the
      value that resulted in the event, the duration of the statistical event,
      and a free-form description with an optional language.</t>  
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Conventions Used in This Document</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL 
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", 
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are
    to be interpreted as 
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
        <t>XML is case sensitive. Unless stated otherwise, XML specifications
	and examples provided in this document <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
	interpreted in the character case presented in order to develop a
	conforming implementation.</t> 
        <t>In examples, "C:" represents lines sent by a protocol client and
	"S:" represents lines returned by a protocol server. In
	examples, indentation and
	whitespace are provided only to illustrate element
	relationships and are not a required feature of this protocol.</t> 
        <t>"loginSec-1.0" is used as an abbreviation for
        "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0". The XML namespace prefix
        "loginSec" is used, but implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> depend on
        it.  Instead, they are to employ
        a proper namespace-aware XML parser and serializer to interpret and
        output the XML documents.</t>
        <t>"whitespace" is defined by the XML Schema whiteSpace data type in
	<xref target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028" format="default"/>, which
	only includes the ASCII whitespace characters #x9 (tab), #xA
	(linefeed), #xD (carriage return), and #x20 (space).</t> 
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Migrating to Newer Versions of This Extension</name>
      <t>Servers that implement this extension <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> provide a way for
         clients to progressively update their implementations when a new
         version of the extension is deployed.  A newer version of the extension
         is expected to use an XML namespace with a higher version number than
      the prior versions.</t> 
      <t>Servers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> (for a temporary migration period up to
      server policy) provide support for 
          older versions of the extension in parallel to the newest version
          and allow clients to select their preferred version via the
          &lt;svcExtension&gt; element of the &lt;login&gt; command.</t>
      <t>If a client requests multiple versions of the extension at login,
           then, when preparing responses to commands that do not include
           extension elements, the server <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> only include extension elements
           in the namespace of the newest version of the extension requested by
           the client.</t>
      <t>When preparing responses to commands that do include extension
           elements, the server <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> only include extension elements for the
           extension versions present in the command.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="attrs" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Object Attributes</name>
      <t>This extension adds additional elements to <xref target="RFC5730"
      format="default"/> login command and response.  Only those new elements
      are described here.</t> 
      <section anchor="event" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Event</name>
        <t>A security event using the &lt;loginSec:event&gt; element
        represents either a warning or error identified by the server after
        the client has connected and submitted the login command. The
	&lt;loginSec:event&gt; element is contained in a list of one or more
	elements in the &lt;loginSec:loginSecData&gt; element, so there
	<bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be multiple events returned that provide
	information for the client to address. The &lt;loginSec:event&gt;
	<bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include a free-form description. All of the
	security events use a consistent set of attributes, where the exact
	set of applicable attributes is based on the event type. The supported
	set of &lt;loginSec:event&gt; element attributes include:</t> 
        <dl newline="false" indent="4">
          <dt>"type":</dt>
          <dd>A <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14> attribute that defines the type of
	  security event.  The enumerated list of "type" values includes:</dd> 
          <dt/>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="false" indent="4">
              <dt>"password":</dt>
              <dd>Identifies a password expiry event where the password
	      expires in the future or has expired based on the "exDate" date
	      and time. The "exDate" attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set with
	      the password expiry date and time.</dd> 
              <dt>"certificate":</dt>
              <dd>Identifies a client certificate expiry event where the
	      client certificate will expire at the "exDate" date and
	      time. The "exDate" attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set with the
	      certificate expiry date and time.</dd> 
              <dt>"cipher":</dt>
              <dd>Identifies the use of an insecure or deprecated TLS cipher
	      suite. The "name" attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set with the
	      name of the cipher suite, which is free-form and is not expected
	      to be parsed and automatically addressed by the client. An
	      example of cipher suite names can be found in the TLS Cipher
	      Suites of the <eref
	      target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-parameters/tls-parameters.xhtml#tls-parameters-4">"Transport
	      Layer Security (TLS) Parameters" registry</eref>.</dd> 
              <dt>"tlsProtocol":</dt>
              <dd>Identifies the use of an insecure or deprecated TLS
	      protocol. The "name" attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set with
	      the name of the TLS protocol, which is free-form and is not
	      expected to be parsed and automatically addressed by the
	      client.</dd> 
              <dt>"newPW":</dt>
              <dd>The new password does not meet the server password
	      complexity requirements.</dd> 
              <dt>"stat":</dt>
              <dd>Provides a login security statistical warning that
	      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set the "name" attribute to the name of the
	      statistic subtype.</dd> 
              <dt>"custom":</dt>
              <dd>Custom event type that <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set the "name"
	      attribute with the custom event type name.</dd> 
            </dl>
          </dd>
          <dt>"name":</dt>
          <dd>Used to define a subtype when the "type" attribute is not
	  "custom" or the full type name when the "type" attribute is
	  "custom".  The "name" attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set when the
	  "type" attribute is "stat" or "custom". The possible set of "name"
	  values, by event type, can be discovered/negotiated out of band to
	  EPP or using a separate EPP extension designed to provide server
	  policy information to the client.</dd> 
          <dt>"level":</dt>
          <dd>Defines the level of the event as either "warning" for a warning
	  event that needs action or "error" for an error event that requires
	  immediate action.</dd> 
          <dt>"exDate":</dt>
          <dd>Contains the date and time that a "warning" level has or will
	  become an "error" level. At expiry, there <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be a
	  connection failure or <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be a login failure. An
	  example is an expired certification that will result in a connection
	  failure or an expired password that may result in a login
	  failure.</dd> 
          <dt>"value":</dt>
          <dd>Identifies the value that resulted in the login security
	  event. An example is the negotiated insecure cipher suite or the
	  negotiated insecure TLS protocol.</dd> 
          <dt>"duration":</dt>
          <dd>Defines the duration that a statistical event is associated
	  with, ending when the login command was received.  The format of the
	  duration is defined by the duration primitive data type in Section
	  3.2.6 of <xref target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"
	  format="default"/>.</dd> 
          <dt>"lang":</dt>
          <dd>Identifies the negotiated language of the free-form description.
	  The format of the language is defined by the language primitive
	  data type in Section 3.3.3 of <xref
	  target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028" format="default"/>.  The
	  default is "en" (English).</dd> 
        </dl>
        <t>Example login security event for password expiration, where the
	current date is 2020-03-25:</t> 
<sourcecode type="xml"><![CDATA[
<loginSec:event
  type="password"
  level="warning"
  exDate="2020-04-01T22:00:00.0Z"
  lang="en">
  Password expiration soon
</loginSec:event>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example login security event for identifying 100 failed logins over
	the last day, using the "stat" subtype of "failedLogins":</t> 
<sourcecode type="xml"><![CDATA[
<loginSec:event
  type="stat"
  name="failedLogins"
  level="warning"
  value="100"
  duration="P1D">
  Excessive invalid daily logins
</loginSec:event>
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="loginSecurityPassword" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>"[LOGIN-SECURITY]" Password</name>
        <t>When the <xref target="RFC5730" format="default"/> &lt;pw&gt;
	element contains the predefined value of "[LOGIN-SECURITY]", the
	&lt;loginSec:pw&gt; element overrides the &lt;pw&gt; element, which is
	a constant value for the server to use the &lt;loginSec:pw&gt; element
	for the password. Similarly, when the <xref target="RFC5730"
	format="default"/> &lt;newPw&gt; element contains the predefined value
	of "[LOGIN-SECURITY]", the &lt;loginSec:newPw&gt; element overrides
	the &lt;newPw&gt; element, which is a constant value for the server to
	use the &lt;loginSec:newPW&gt; element for the new password. The
	"[LOGIN-SECURITY]" predefined string <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported
	by the server for the client to explicitly indicate to the server
	whether to use &lt;loginSec:pw&gt; element in place of the <xref
	target="RFC5730" format="default"/> &lt;pw&gt; element or to use the
	&lt;loginSec:newPW&gt; in place of the <xref target="RFC5730"
	format="default"/> &lt;newPW&gt; element.  The server <bcp14>MUST
	NOT</bcp14> allow the client to set the password to the value
	"[LOGIN-SECURITY]".</t> 
      </section>
      <section anchor="datestimes" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Dates and Times</name>
        <t>Date and time attribute values <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented
	in Universal Coordinated Time (UTC) using the Gregorian calendar.  The
	extended date-time form using upper case "T" and "Z" characters
	defined in <xref target="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"
	format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used to represent date-time
	values, as XML Schema does not support truncated date-time forms or
	lower case "T" and "Z" characters.</t> 
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="commands" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>EPP Command Mapping</name>
      <t>A detailed description of the EPP syntax and semantics can be found
      in the EPP core protocol specification <xref target="RFC5730"
      format="default"/>.</t> 

      <section anchor="loginCommand" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EPP &lt;login&gt; Command</name>
        <t>This extension defines additional elements to extend the EPP
	&lt;login&gt; command and response to be used in conjunction with
	<xref target="RFC5730" format="default"/>.</t> 
        <t>The EPP &lt;login&gt; command is used to establish a session with
	an EPP server.  This extension overrides the password that is passed
	with the <xref target="RFC5730" format="default"/> &lt;pw&gt; or the
	&lt;newPW&gt; element, as defined in <xref
	target="loginSecurityPassword" format="default"/>.  A
	&lt;loginSec:loginSec&gt; element is sent along with the <xref
	target="RFC5730" format="default"/> &lt;login&gt; command and
	<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain at least one of the following child
	elements:</t> 
        <dl newline="false" indent="4">
          <dt>&lt;loginSec:userAgent&gt;:</dt>
          <dd><bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> client user-agent information that
	  identifies the client application software, technology, and
	  operating system used by the server to identify functional or
	  security constraints, current security issues, and potential future
	  functional or security issues for the client.  The server may use
	  the information for real-time identification and client notification
	  of security issues, such as keying off of the client application
	  software for executing security rule checks.  The server may capture
	  the information to identify future security policy issues, such as
	  deprecating or removing TLS cipher suites or TLS protocols.  The
	  &lt;loginSec:userAgent&gt; element <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain at
	  least one of the following child elements:</dd> 
          <dt/>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="false" indent="4">
              <dt>&lt;loginSec:app&gt;:</dt>
              <dd>
                <t><bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> name of the client application
		software with version if available, such as the name of the
		client SDK "EPP SDK 1.0.0".  The &lt;loginSec:app&gt; element
		value can be created by appending the version number to the
		name of the application software, such as the Augmented
		Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) grammar <xref target="RFC5234"
		format="default"></xref> format:</t>  
<sourcecode type="abnf">
app = name SP version
name = 1*VCHAR
version = 1*VCHAR
</sourcecode>
              </dd>
              <dt>&lt;loginSec:tech&gt;:</dt>
              <dd>
                <t><bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> technology used for the client
		software with version if available, such as "Vendor Java
		11.0.6".  The &lt;loginSec:tech&gt; element value can be
		created by including the technology vendor, technology name,
		and technology version, such as the Augmented Backus-Naur Form
		(ABNF) grammar <xref target="RFC5234" format="default"></xref>
		format:</t>  
<sourcecode type="abnf">
tech = vendor SP name SP version
vendor = 1*VCHAR
name = 1*VCHAR
version = 1*VCHAR
</sourcecode>
              </dd>
              <dt>&lt;loginSec:os&gt;:</dt>
              <dd>
                <t><bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> client operating system used with
		version if available, such as "x86_64 Mac OS X 10.15.2".  The
		&lt;loginSec:os&gt; element value can be created by including
		the operating system architecture, operating system name, and
		operating system version, such as the Augmented Backus-Naur
		Form (ABNF) grammar <xref target="RFC5234"
		format="default"></xref> format:</t>  
<sourcecode type="abnf">
os = arch SP name SP version
arch = 1*VCHAR
name = 1*VCHAR
version = 1*VCHAR
</sourcecode>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>
          <dt>&lt;loginSec:pw&gt;:</dt>
          <dd><bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> plain text password that is case
	  sensitive, has a minimum length of 6 characters, and has a maximum
	  length that is up to server policy.  All leading and trailing
	  whitespace is removed, and all internal contiguous whitespace that
	  includes #x9 (tab), #xA (linefeed), #xD (carriage return), and #x20
	  (space) is replaced with a single #x20 (space).  This element
	  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be set if the <xref target="RFC5730"
	  format="default"/> &lt;pw&gt; element is set to the
	  "[LOGIN-SECURITY]" value.</dd> 
          <dt>&lt;loginSec:newPW&gt;:</dt>
          <dd><bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> plain text new password that is case
	  sensitive, has a minimum length of 6 characters, and has a maximum
	  length that is up to server policy.  All leading and trailing
	  whitespace is removed, and all internal contiguous whitespace that
	  includes #x9 (tab), #xA (linefeed), #xD (carriage return), and #x20
	  (space) is replaced with a single #x20 (space).  This element
	  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be set if the <xref target="RFC5730"
	  format="default"/> &lt;newPW&gt; element is set to the
	  "[LOGIN-SECURITY]" value.</dd> 
        </dl>
        <t>It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the plain text password in
	the &lt;loginSec:pw&gt; and &lt;loginSec:newPw&gt; elements use
	printable ASCII characters #x20 (space) - #x7E (~) with high entropy,
	such as 128 bits.  If non-ASCII characters are supported with the
	plain text password, then use a standard for passwords with
	international characters; the OpaqueString PRECIS profile in <xref
	target="RFC8265" format="default"/> is recommended in the absence of
	other considerations.</t> 
        <t>Example login command that uses the &lt;loginSec:pw&gt; element
	instead of the &lt;pw&gt;
	element  (<xref target="RFC5730" format="default"/>) to establish the session and includes the
	&lt;loginSec:userAgent&gt; element:</t> 
<sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <login>
C:      <clID>ClientX</clID>
C:      <pw>[LOGIN-SECURITY]</pw>
C:      <options>
C:        <version>1.0</version>
C:        <lang>en</lang>
C:      </options>
C:      <svcs>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj1</objURI>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj2</objURI>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj3</objURI>
C:        <svcExtension>
C:          <extURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0</extURI>
C:        </svcExtension>
C:      </svcs>
C:    </login>
C:    <extension>
C:      <loginSec:loginSec
C:        xmlns:loginSec=
C:          "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0">
C:        <loginSec:userAgent>
C:          <loginSec:app>EPP SDK 1.0.0</loginSec:app>
C:          <loginSec:tech>Vendor Java 11.0.6</loginSec:tech>
C:          <loginSec:os>x86_64 Mac OS X 10.15.2</loginSec:os>
C:        </loginSec:userAgent>
C:        <loginSec:pw>this is a long password</loginSec:pw>
C:      </loginSec:loginSec>
C:    </extension>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example login command that uses the &lt;loginSec:pw&gt; element
	instead of the &lt;pw&gt;
	element (<xref target="RFC5730" format="default"/>) to
	establish the session and that uses the &lt;loginSec:newPW&gt;
	element instead of the 
	&lt;newPW&gt; element (<xref target="RFC5730"
	format="default"/>) to set the new password:</t> 
<sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <login>
C:      <clID>ClientX</clID>
C:      <pw>[LOGIN-SECURITY]</pw>
C:      <newPW>[LOGIN-SECURITY]</newPW>
C:      <options>
C:        <version>1.0</version>
C:        <lang>en</lang>
C:      </options>
C:      <svcs>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj1</objURI>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj2</objURI>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj3</objURI>
C:        <svcExtension>
C:          <extURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0</extURI>
C:        </svcExtension>
C:      </svcs>
C:    </login>
C:    <extension>
C:      <loginSec:loginSec
C:        xmlns:loginSec=
C:          "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0">
C:        <loginSec:pw>this is a long password
C:        </loginSec:pw>
C:        <loginSec:newPW>new password that is still long
C:        </loginSec:newPW>
C:      </loginSec:loginSec>
C:    </extension>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example login command that uses the &lt;pw&gt; element (<xref target="RFC5730"
	format="default"/>) to establish the session and
	that uses the &lt;loginSec:newPW&gt; element instead of the  &lt;newPW&gt; element (<xref
	target="RFC5730" format="default"/>) to set the
	new password:</t> 
<sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
C:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
C:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
C:  <command>
C:    <login>
C:      <clID>ClientX</clID>
C:      <pw>shortpassword</pw>
C:      <newPW>[LOGIN-SECURITY]</newPW>
C:      <options>
C:        <version>1.0</version>
C:        <lang>en</lang>
C:      </options>
C:      <svcs>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj1</objURI>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj2</objURI>
C:        <objURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:obj3</objURI>
C:        <svcExtension>
C:          <extURI>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0</extURI>
C:        </svcExtension>
C:      </svcs>
C:    </login>
C:    <extension>
C:      <loginSec:loginSec
C:        xmlns:loginSec=
C:          "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0">
C:        <loginSec:newPW>new password that is still long
C:        </loginSec:newPW>
C:      </loginSec:loginSec>
C:    </extension>
C:    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
C:  </command>
C:</epp>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Upon a completed login command (success or failed), the extension
	<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included in the response when both of the
	following conditions hold:</t> 
        <dl newline="false" indent="4">
          <dt>Client supports extension:</dt>
          <dd>The client supports the extension based on the
	  &lt;svcExtension&gt; element of the &lt;login&gt; command.</dd> 
          <dt>At least one login security event:</dt>
          <dd>The server has identified at least one login security event to
	  communicate to the client.</dd> 
        </dl>
        <t>The extension to the EPP response uses the
	&lt;loginSec:loginSecData&gt; element that contains the following
	child elements:</t> 
        <dl newline="false" indent="4">
          <dt>&lt;loginSec:event&gt;:</dt>
          <dd>One or more &lt;loginSec:event&gt; elements defined in <xref
	  target="event" format="default"/>.</dd> 
        </dl>
        <t>Example EPP response to a successful login command on 2020-03-25,
	where the password will expire in a week:</t> 
<sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg>Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <extension>
S:      <loginSec:loginSecData
S:        xmlns:loginSec=
S:          "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0">
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="password"
S:          level="warning"
S:          exDate="2020-04-01T22:00:00.0Z"
S:          lang="en">
S:          Password expiring in a week
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:      </loginSec:loginSecData>
S:    </extension>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example EPP response to a failed login command where the password
	has expired and the new password does not meet the server complexity
	requirements:</t> 
<sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="2200">
S:      <msg>Authentication error</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <extension>
S:      <loginSec:loginSecData
S:        xmlns:loginSec=
S:          "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0">
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="password"
S:          level="error"
S:          exDate="2020-03-24T22:00:00.0Z">
S:          Password has expired
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="newPW"
S:          level="error">
S:          New password does not meet complexity requirements
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:      </loginSec:loginSecData>
S:    </extension>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example EPP response to a successful login command where
            there is a set of login security events:</t>
<sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
S:<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
S:<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
S:  <response>
S:    <result code="1000">
S:      <msg>Command completed successfully</msg>
S:    </result>
S:    <extension>
S:      <loginSec:loginSecData
S:        xmlns:loginSec=
S:          "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0">
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="password"
S:          level="warning"
S:          exDate="2020-04-01T22:00:00.0Z"
S:          lang="en">
S:          Password expiration soon
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="certificate"
S:          level="warning"
S:          exDate="2020-04-02T22:00:00.0Z"/>
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="cipher"
S:          level="warning"
S:          value="TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA">
S:          Non-PFS Cipher negotiated
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="tlsProtocol"
S:          level="warning"
S:          value="TLSv1.0">
S:          Insecure TLS protocol negotiated
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="stat"
S:          name="failedLogins"
S:          level="warning"
S:          value="100"
S:          duration="P1D">
S:          Excessive invalid daily logins
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:        <loginSec:event
S:          type="custom"
S:          name="myCustomEvent"
S:          level="warning">
S:          A custom login security event occurred
S:        </loginSec:event>
S:      </loginSec:loginSecData>
S:    </extension>
S:    <trID>
S:      <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
S:      <svTRID>54321-XYZ</svTRID>
S:    </trID>
S:  </response>
S:</epp>
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
      <!-- end LOGIN command -->

    </section>
    <!-- EPP command mapping -->

    <section anchor="syntax" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Formal Syntax</name>
      <t>The EPP Login Security Extension schema is presented here.</t>
      <t>The formal
      syntax shown here is a complete XML Schema representation of the object
      mapping suitable for automated validation of EPP XML instances. The
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt; and &lt;CODE ENDS&gt; tags are not part of the XML Schema; they are used to note the
      beginning and ending of the XML Schema for URI registration purposes.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Login Security Extension Schema</name>
<sourcecode type="xml" markers="true"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<schema xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
  xmlns:epp="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0"
  xmlns:eppcom="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0"
  xmlns:loginSec="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0"
  targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0"
  elementFormDefault="qualified">
  <!--
  Import common element types.
  -->
  <import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0" />
  <import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0" />
  <annotation>
    <documentation>Extensible Provisioning Protocol v1.0
       Login Security Extension Schema.</documentation>
  </annotation>
  <!-- Login command extension elements -->
  <element name="loginSec" type="loginSec:loginSecType" />
  <!--
    Attributes associated with the login command extension.
   -->
  <complexType name="loginSecType">
    <sequence>
      <element name="userAgent"
        type="loginSec:userAgentType" minOccurs="0" />
      <element name="pw"
        type="loginSec:pwType" minOccurs="0" />
      <element name="newPW"
        type="loginSec:pwType" minOccurs="0" />
    </sequence>
  </complexType>
  <simpleType name="pwType">
    <restriction base="token">
      <minLength value="6" />
    </restriction>
  </simpleType>
  <complexType name="userAgentType">
    <choice>
      <sequence>
        <element name="app"
          type="token" />
        <element name="tech"
          type="token" minOccurs="0" />
        <element name="os"
          type="token" minOccurs="0" />
      </sequence>
      <sequence>
        <element name="tech"
          type="token" />
        <element name="os"
          type="token" minOccurs="0" />
      </sequence>
      <element name="os"
        type="token" />
    </choice>
  </complexType>
  <!-- Login response extension elements -->
  <element name="loginSecData"
    type="loginSec:loginSecDataType" />
  <complexType name="loginSecDataType">
    <sequence>
      <element name="event"
        type="loginSec:eventType"
        minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded" />
    </sequence>
  </complexType>
  <!-- Security event element -->
  <complexType name="eventType">
    <simpleContent>
      <extension base="normalizedString">
        <attribute name="type"
          type="loginSec:typeEnum" use="required" />
        <attribute name="name"
          type="token" />
        <attribute name="level"
          type="loginSec:levelEnum" use="required" />
        <attribute name="exDate"
          type="dateTime" />
        <attribute name="value"
          type="token" />
        <attribute name="duration"
          type="duration" />
        <attribute name="lang"
          type="language" default="en" />
      </extension>
    </simpleContent>
  </complexType>
  <!--
    Enumerated list of event types, with extensibility via "custom".
    -->
  <simpleType name="typeEnum">
    <restriction base="token">
      <enumeration value="password" />
      <enumeration value="certificate" />
      <enumeration value="cipher" />
      <enumeration value="tlsProtocol" />
      <enumeration value="newPW" />
      <enumeration value="stat" />
      <enumeration value="custom" />
    </restriction>
  </simpleType>
  <!--
    Enumerated list of levels.
    -->
  <simpleType name="levelEnum">
    <restriction base="token">
      <enumeration value="warning" />
      <enumeration value="error" />
    </restriction>
  </simpleType>
  <!--
 End of schema.
 -->
</schema>
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="IANA-XML-Namespace" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>XML Namespace</name>
        <t>This document uses URNs to describe XML namespaces and XML schemas
	conforming to a registry mechanism described in <xref target="RFC3688"
	format="default"/>. The following URI assignment has been made by
	IANA:</t> 
        <t>Registration request for the loginSec namespace:</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>URI:</dt>
	  <dd>urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp:loginSec-1.0</dd>
          <dt>Registrant Contact:</dt>
	  <dd>IESG</dd>
          <dt>XML:</dt>
	  <dd>None. Namespace URIs do not represent an XML specification.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>Registration request for the loginSec XML Schema:</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>URI:</dt>
	  <dd>urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:epp:loginSec-1.0</dd>
          <dt>Registrant Contact:</dt>
	  <dd>IESG</dd>
          <dt>XML:</dt>
	  <dd>See the "Formal Syntax" section of this document.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="EPP-Extension-Registry" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>EPP Extension Registry</name>
        <t>The EPP extension described in this document has been registered
	by IANA in the "Extensions for the Extensible Provisioning
	Protocol (EPP)" registry described in <xref
	target="RFC7451" format="default"/>.  The details of the registration
	are as follows:</t> 
	<dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
        <dt>Name of Extension:</dt>
	<dd>"Login Security Extension for the Extensible
	Provisioning Protocol (EPP)"</dd> 
        <dt>Document status:</dt>
	<dd>Standards Track</dd>
        <dt>Reference:</dt>
	<dd>RFC 8807</dd>
        <dt>Registrant Name and Email Address:</dt>
	<dd>IESG, &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</dd>
        <dt>Top-Level Domains(TLDs):</dt>
	<dd>Any</dd>
        <dt>IPR Disclosure:</dt>
	<dd>None</dd>
        <dt>Status:</dt>
	<dd>Active</dd>
        <dt>Notes:</dt>
	<dd>None</dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security considerations of <xref target="RFC5730"
      format="default"/> apply in this document, and this document enhances
      these considerations.</t> 
      <t>The extension leaves the password (&lt;pw&gt; element) and new
      password (&lt;newPW&gt; element) minimum length greater than 6
      characters and the maximum length up to server policy.  The server
      <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> enforce minimum and maximum length requirements
      that are appropriate for their operating environment.  One example of a
      guideline for password length policies can be found in Section 5 of
      <eref target="https://pages.nist.gov/800-63-3/sp800-63b.html">NIST
      Special Publication 800-63B</eref>.</t> 
      <t>The client <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> decrease
      the security of a new password by decreasing the length of the current
      password.  For example, a client with a 20-character password set using 
      the extension should not use the login command in <xref
      target="RFC5730" format="default"/> without using the extension to set
      a new password that is less than or equal to 16 characters.</t> 
      <t>The extension provides an extensible list of login security events to
      inform clients of connection and login warnings and errors. The server
      returning of security events to unauthenticated users needs to take into
      account the security/privacy issues of returning information to
      potential attackers.</t> 
      <t>The user-agent information represents the client system of a
      system-to-system interface, so the user-agent information <bcp14>MUST
      NOT</bcp14> provide any ability to track individual users or classes of
      users.</t> 
    </section>
  </middle>
  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    


    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3688.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5730.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xmlschema-2-20041028.xml">
          <front>
            <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second Edition</title>
            <seriesInfo name="W3C Recommendation" value="REC-xmlschema-2-20041028"/>
            <author initials="P." surname="Biron" fullname="Paul V. Biron">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Malhotra" fullname="Ashok Malhotra">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="October" year="2004"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

	        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7451.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8265.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors wish to thank the following persons for their feedback
      and suggestions: <contact fullname="Martin Casanova"/>, <contact
      fullname="Scott Hollenbeck"/>, <contact fullname="Barry Leiba"/>,
      <contact fullname="Patrick Mevzek"/>, and <contact fullname="Joseph
      Yee"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
