<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std"
     docName="draft-ietf-ippm-metric-registry-24" number="8911"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true"
     sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.42.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Registry for Performance Metrics">Registry for Performance
    Metrics</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8911"/>

    <author fullname="Marcelo Bagnulo" initials="M." surname="Bagnulo">
      <organization abbrev="UC3M">Universidad Carlos III de
      Madrid</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Universidad 30</street>
          <city>Leganes</city>
          <region>Madrid</region>
          <code>28911</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>34 91 6249500</phone>
        <email>marcelo@it.uc3m.es</email>
        <uri>http://www.it.uc3m.es</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Benoit Claise" initials="B." surname="Claise">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal/>
        <email>benoit.claise@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Philip Eardley" initials="P." surname="Eardley">
      <organization abbrev="BT">BT</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Adastral Park, Martlesham Heath</street>
          <city>Ipswich</city>
          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>
        <email>philip.eardley@bt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
      <organization abbrev="AT&amp;T Labs">AT&amp;T Labs</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>
          <city>Middletown</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
          <code>07748</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>acmorton@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Aamer Akhter" initials="A." surname="Akhter">
      <organization abbrev="Consultant">Consultant</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>118 Timber Hitch</street>
          <city>Cary</city>
          <region>NC</region>
          <code/>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>aakhter@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2021"/>

    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>IPPM</workgroup>
    
    <keyword>IPPM</keyword>
    <keyword>Loss</keyword>
    <keyword>Delay</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines the format for the IANA Registry of Performance Metrics.
      This document also gives a set of guidelines for Registered
      Performance Metric requesters and reviewers.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The IETF specifies and uses Performance Metrics of protocols and
      applications transported over its protocols. Performance Metrics are
      an important part of network operations using IETF protocols, and <xref target="RFC6390" format="default"/> specifies guidelines for their development.</t>
      <t>The definition and use of Performance Metrics in the IETF have been
      fostered in various working groups (WGs). Most notably: </t>
      <ul empty="false" spacing="normal">
        <li>The "IP Performance Metrics" (IPPM) WG is the WG primarily
          focusing on Performance Metrics definition at the IETF.</li>
        <li>The "Benchmarking Methodology" WG (BMWG) defines many Performance
          Metrics for use in laboratory benchmarking of internetworking
          technologies.</li>
        <li>The "Metric Blocks for use with RTCP's Extended Report Framework"
          (XRBLOCK) WG (concluded) specified many Performance Metrics related
          to "RTP Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR)" <xref target="RFC3611" format="default"/>, which establishes a framework to allow new
          information to be conveyed in RTCP, supplementing the original
          report blocks defined in "RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time
          Applications" <xref target="RFC3550" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>The "IP Flow Information eXport" (IPFIX) WG (concluded) specified
          an Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) process for new
          Information Elements. Some Information Elements related to Performance
          Metrics are proposed on a regular basis.</li>
        <li>The "Performance Metrics for Other Layers" (PMOL) WG (concluded)
          defined some Performance Metrics related to Session Initiation
          Protocol (SIP) voice quality <xref target="RFC6035" format="default"/>.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>It is expected that more Performance Metrics will be defined in the
      future -- not only IP-based metrics but also metrics that are
      protocol specific and application specific.</t>
      <t>Despite the importance of Performance Metrics, there are two related
      problems for the industry:</t>

      <ul empty="false" spacing="normal">
        <li>First, ensuring that when one party requests that
      another party measure (or report or in some way act on) a particular
      Performance Metric, both parties have exactly the same
      understanding of what Performance Metric is being referred to.</li>
        <li>Second,
      discovering which Performance Metrics have been specified, to avoid
      developing a new Performance Metric that is very similar but not quite
      interoperable.</li>
      </ul>

     <t>These problems can be addressed by creating a Registry
      for Performance Metrics with the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority
      (IANA).   As such, this document defines the new IANA Registry for Performance
      Metrics.</t>

      <t>Per this document, IANA has created and now maintains the Performance
      Metrics Registry, according to the maintenance procedures and the
      format defined in the sections below. The resulting
      Performance Metrics Registry is for use by the IETF and others. Although
      the Registry formatting specifications herein are primarily for Registry
      creation by IANA, any other organization that wishes to create a
      Performance Metrics Registry may use the same formatting specifications
      for their purposes. The authors make no guarantee of the Registry
      format's applicability to any possible set of Performance Metrics
      envisaged by other organizations, but we encourage others to apply it. In
      the remainder of this document, unless we explicitly say otherwise, we
      will refer to the IANA-maintained Performance Metrics Registry as simply
      the Performance Metrics Registry.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
       <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
       "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document
       are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14
       <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
       when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Performance Metric:</dt>
        <dd>A quantitative measure of performance, targeted to an IETF-specified
          protocol or targeted to an application transported over an
          IETF-specified protocol. Examples of Performance Metrics are the FTP
          response time for a complete file download, the DNS Response time to
          resolve the IP address(es), a database logging time, etc. This
          definition is consistent with the definition of a metric in <xref
          target="RFC2330" format="default"/> and broader than the definition
          of a Performance Metric in <xref target="RFC6390" format="default"/>.</dd>
        <dt>Registered Performance Metric:</dt>
        <dd>A Performance Metric expressed as an entry in
          the Performance Metrics Registry, administered by IANA. Such a
          Performance Metric has met all of the Registry review criteria defined
          in this document in order to be included in the Registry.</dd>
        <dt>Performance Metrics Registry:</dt>
        <dd>The IANA Registry
          containing Registered Performance Metrics.</dd>
        <dt>Proprietary Registry:</dt>
        <dd>A set of metrics that are
          registered in a proprietary Registry, as opposed to the Performance
          Metrics Registry.</dd>
        <dt>Performance Metrics Experts:</dt>
        <dd>A group of designated experts <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>
          selected by the IESG to validate the Performance Metrics before
          updating the Performance Metrics Registry. The Performance Metrics
          Experts work closely with IANA.</dd>
        <dt>Parameter:</dt>
        <dd>An input factor defined as a
          variable in the definition of a Performance Metric. A Parameter is a
          numerical or other specified factor forming one of a set that
          defines a metric or sets the conditions of its operation. All
          Parameters must be known in order to make a measurement using a
          metric and interpret the results. There are two types of Parameters:
          Fixed and Runtime. For the Fixed Parameters, the value
          of the variable is specified in the Performance Metrics Registry
          Entry and different Fixed Parameter values results in different
          Registered Performance Metrics. For the Runtime Parameters, the
          value of the variable is defined when the Metric Measurement Method
          is executed and a given Registered Performance Metric supports
          multiple values for the Parameter. Although Runtime Parameters do
          not change the fundamental nature of the Performance Metric's
          definition, some have substantial influence on the network property
          being assessed and interpretation of the results.</dd>
      </dl>

    <aside><t>Note: Consider the case of packet loss in the following two
              Active Measurement Method cases. The first case is packet loss
              as background loss where the Runtime Parameter set includes a
              very sparse Poisson stream and only characterizes the times
              when packets were lost. Actual user streams likely see much
              higher loss at these times, due to tail drop or radio errors.
              The second case is packet loss ratio as the complimentary
              probability of delivery ratio where
              the Runtime Parameter set includes a very dense, bursty stream,
              and characterizes the loss experienced by a stream that
              approximates a user stream. These are both "Loss metrics", but
              the difference in interpretation of the results is highly
              dependent on the Runtime Parameters (at least), to the extreme
              where we are actually using loss ratio to infer its complimentary
              probability: delivery ratio.</t></aside>

       <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Active Measurement Methods:</dt>
        <dd>Methods of Measurement
          conducted on traffic that serves only the purpose of measurement
          and is generated for that reason alone, and whose traffic
          characteristics are known a priori. The complete definition of
          Active Methods is specified in <xref target="RFC7799" sectionFormat="of" section="3.4"/>. Examples of Active Measurement Methods are the
          Measurement Methods for the one-way delay metric defined in <xref
          target="RFC7679" format="default"/> and the round-trip delay metric defined in <xref target="RFC2681" format="default"/>.</dd>
        <dt>Passive Measurement Methods:</dt>
        <dd>Methods of Measurement
          conducted on network traffic, generated by either (1)&nbsp;the end
          users or (2)&nbsp;network elements that would exist regardless of whether the
          measurement was being conducted or not. The complete definition of
          Passive Methods is specified in <xref target="RFC7799" sectionFormat="of" section="3.6"/>. One characteristic of Passive Measurement
          Methods is that sensitive information may be observed and, as a
          consequence, stored in the measurement system.</dd>
        <dt>Hybrid Measurement Methods:</dt>
        <dd>Methods of Measurement that use a combination of Active Methods and Passive
          Methods, to assess Active Metrics, Passive Metrics, or new metrics
          derived from the a&nbsp;priori knowledge and observations of the stream
          of interest. The complete definition of Hybrid Methods is specified
          in <xref target="RFC7799" sectionFormat="of" section="3.8"/>.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Scope</name>
      <t>This document is intended for two different audiences:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>For those preparing a candidate Performance Metric, it provides
        criteria that the proposal <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> meet (see <xref
        target="metrics-criteria"/>). It also provides instructions for
        writing the text for each column of the candidate Performance Metric
        and the references required for the new Performance Metrics Registry
        Entry (up to and including the publication of one or more immutable
        documents such as an RFC) (see <xref target="columns"/>).</li>
        <li>For the appointed Performance Metrics Experts and for IANA
        personnel administering the new IANA Performance Metrics Registry, it
        defines a set of acceptance criteria against which a candidate
        Registered Performance Metric should be evaluated, and requirements
        for the composition of a candidate Performance Metric Registry Entry.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>Other organizations that standardize performance metrics are
      encouraged to use the process defined in this memo to propose a
      candidate Registered Performance Metric.  In addition, this document may
      be useful for other organizations who are defining a Performance Metrics
      Registry of their own and may reuse the features of the Performance
      Metrics Registry defined in this document.</t>

      <t>This Performance Metrics Registry is applicable to Performance
      Metrics derived from Active Measurement, Passive Measurement, and any
      other form of Performance Metric. This Registry is designed to encompass
      Performance Metrics developed throughout the IETF and especially for the
      technologies specified in the following working groups: IPPM, XRBLOCK,
      IPFIX, and BMWG. This document analyzes a prior attempt to set up a
      Performance Metrics Registry and the reasons why this design was
      inadequate <xref target="RFC6248" format="default"/>. </t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8912" format="default"/> populates the new Registry
      with the initial set of entries.</t>
    </section>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Motivations for the Performance Metrics Registry</name>
      <t>In this section, we detail several motivations for the Performance
      Metrics Registry.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Interoperability</name>
        <t>As with any IETF Registry, the primary intention is to manage the
        registration of Identifiers for use within one or more protocols. In
        the particular case of the Performance Metrics Registry, there are two
        types of protocols that will use the Performance Metrics in the
        Performance Metrics Registry during their operation (by referring to
        the index values): </t>

          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
           <dt>Control Protocol:</dt><dd>This type of protocol is used to allow one
            entity to request that another entity perform a measurement using a
            specific metric defined by the Performance Metrics Registry. One
            particular example is the Large-scale Measurement of Broadband
            Performance (LMAP) framework <xref target="RFC7594" format="default"/>.
            Using the LMAP terminology, the Performance Metrics Registry is
            used in the LMAP Control Protocol to allow a Controller to
            schedule a Measurement Task for one or more Measurement Agents. In
            order to enable this use case, the entries in the Performance
            Metrics Registry must be sufficiently defined to allow a
            Measurement Agent implementation to trigger a specific Measurement
            Task upon the reception of a Control Protocol message. This
            requirement heavily constrains the types of entries that are
            acceptable for the Performance Metrics Registry.</dd>
          <dt>Report Protocol:</dt><dd>This type of protocol is used to allow an entity to report Measurement Results to another entity.  By referencing to a specific Registered Performance Metric, it is
            possible to properly characterize the Measurement Result data
            being reported. Using the LMAP terminology, the Performance
            Metrics Registry is used in the LMAP Report Protocol to allow a
            Measurement Agent to report Measurement Results to a
            Collector.</dd>
</dl>
        <t> It should be noted that the LMAP framework explicitly allows
        for using not only the IANA-maintained Performance Metrics Registry
        but also other registries containing Performance Metrics, i.e.,
        either (1)&nbsp;registries defined by other organizations or (2)&nbsp;private registries. However, others who
        are creating registries to be used in the context of an LMAP framework
        are encouraged to use the Registry format defined in this document,
        because this makes it easier for developers of LMAP Measurement Agents
        to programmatically use information found in those other
        registries' entries.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Single Point of Reference for Performance Metrics</name>
        <t>A Performance Metrics Registry serves as a single point of
        reference for Performance Metrics defined in different working groups
        in the IETF. As we mentioned earlier, there are several working groups that
        define Performance Metrics in the IETF, and it is hard to keep track of
        all of them. This results in multiple definitions of similar Performance
        Metrics that attempt to measure the same phenomena but in slightly
        different (and incompatible) ways. Having a Registry would allow the
        IETF community and others to have a single list of relevant
        Performance Metrics defined by the IETF (and others, where
        appropriate). The single list is also an essential aspect of
        communication about Performance Metrics, where different entities that
        request measurements, execute measurements, and report the results can
        benefit from a common understanding of the referenced Performance
        Metric.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Side Benefits</name>
        <t>There are a couple of side benefits of having such a Registry.
        First, the Performance Metrics Registry could serve as an inventory of
        useful and used Performance Metrics that are normally supported by
        different implementations of Measurement Agents. Second, the results
        of measurements using the Performance Metrics should be comparable
        even if they are performed by different implementations and in
        different networks, as the Performance Metric is properly defined.
        BCP 176 <xref target="RFC6576" format="default"/> examines whether the
        results produced by independent implementations are equivalent in the
        context of evaluating the completeness and clarity of metric
        specifications. <xref target="RFC6576"/> is a BCP <xref
        target="RFC2026"/> that defines the Standards Track advancement
        testing for (Active) IPPM Metrics, and the same process will likely
        suffice to determine whether Registered Performance Metrics are
        sufficiently well specified to result in comparable (or equivalent)
        results. If a Registered Performance Metric has undergone such
        testing, this <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be noted in "Comments and Remarks"
        (see <xref target="remarks"/>), with a reference to the test
        results.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="metrics-criteria" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Criteria for Performance Metrics Registration</name>
      <t>It is neither possible nor desirable to populate the Performance
      Metrics Registry with all combinations of Parameters of all Performance
      Metrics. A Registered Performance Metric <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be: </t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>Interpretable by the human user.</li>
        <li>Implementable by the software or hardware designer.</li>
        <li>Deployable by network operators.</li>
        <li>Accurate in terms of producing equivalent results, and for
          interoperability and deployment across vendors.</li>
        <li>Operationally useful, so that it has significant industry
          interest and/or has seen deployment.</li>
        <li>Sufficiently tightly defined, so that different values for the
          Runtime Parameters do not change the fundamental nature of the
          measurement or change the practicality of its implementation.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>In essence, there needs to be evidence that (1)&nbsp;a candidate
      Registered Performance Metric has significant industry interest or has
      seen deployment and (2)&nbsp;there is agreement that the candidate Registered
      Performance Metric serves its intended purpose.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Performance Metrics Registry: Prior Attempt</name>
      <t>There was a previous attempt to define a Metrics Registry <xref
      target="RFC4148" format="default"></xref>. However, it was
      obsoleted by <xref target="RFC6248" format="default"></xref>
      because it was 
<!-- Begin DNE -->
"found to be
      insufficiently detailed to uniquely identify IPPM metrics... [there was
      too much] variability possible when characterizing a metric exactly",
<!-- End DNE -->
      which led to the IPPM Metrics Registry defined in <xref target="RFC4148"/> having
<!-- Begin DNE --> "very few users, if any." <!-- End DNE --></t>
      <t>Three interesting additional quotes from <xref target="RFC6248" format="default"></xref> might help to understand the issues
      related to that registry. </t>
<!-- Begin DNE.-->
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>"It is not believed to be feasible or even useful to register
          every possible combination of Type P, metric parameters, and Stream
          parameters using the current structure of the IPPM Metrics
          Registry."</li>
        <li>"The current registry structure has been found to be insufficiently
          detailed to uniquely identify IPPM metrics."</li>
        <li>"Despite apparent efforts to find current or even future users,
          no one responded to the call for interest in the RFC 4148 registry
          during the second half of 2010."</li>
<!-- End DNE -->
      </ol>
      <t>The current approach learns from this by tightly defining each
      Registered Performance Metric with only a few variable (Runtime)
      Parameters to be specified by the measurement designer, if any. The idea
      is that entries in the Performance Metrics Registry stem from different
      Measurement Methods that require input (Runtime) Parameters to set
      factors like Source and Destination addresses (which do not change the
      fundamental nature of the measurement). The downside of this approach is
      that it could result in a large number of entries in the Performance
      Metrics Registry. There is agreement that less is more in this context --
      it is better to have a reduced set of useful metrics rather than a large
      set of metrics, some with questionable usefulness.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Why This Attempt Should Succeed</name>
        <t>As mentioned in the previous section, one of the main issues with
        the previous Registry was that the metrics contained in the Registry
        were too generic to be useful. This document specifies stricter
        criteria for Performance Metric registration (see <xref
        target="metrics-criteria"/>) and
        imposes a group of Performance Metrics Experts that will provide
        guidelines to assess if a Performance Metric is properly
        specified.</t>
        <t>Another key difference between this attempt and the previous one is
        that in this case there is at least one clear user for the Performance
        Metrics Registry: the LMAP framework and protocol. Because the LMAP
        protocol will use the Performance Metrics Registry values in its
        operation, this actually helps to determine if a metric is properly
        defined -- in particular, since we expect that the LMAP Control Protocol will enable
        a Controller to request that a Measurement Agent perform a measurement
        using a given metric by embedding the Performance Metrics Registry
        Identifier in the protocol. Such a metric and method are properly
        specified if they are defined well enough so that it is possible (and
        practical) to implement them in the Measurement Agent. This was the failure of the previous attempt: a Registry Entry with an undefined Type-P (<xref target="RFC2330" sectionFormat="of" section="13"/>) allows measurement results to vary significantly.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="columns" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Definition of the Performance Metrics Registry</name>
      <t>This Performance Metrics Registry is applicable to Performance
      Metrics used for Active Measurement, Passive Measurement, and any other
      form of Performance Measurement. Each category of measurement has unique
      properties, so some of the columns defined below are not applicable for
      a given metric category. In this case, the column(s) <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be populated
      with the "N/A" value (Not Applicable). However, the "N/A" value <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
      be used by any metric in the following columns: Identifier, Name, URI,
      Status, Requester, Revision, Revision Date, Description. In the future,
      a new category of metrics could require additional columns, and adding
      new columns is a recognized form of Registry extension. The
      specification defining the new column(s) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> give general guidelines
      for populating the new column(s) for existing entries.</t>
      <t>The columns of the Performance Metrics Registry are defined below.
      The columns are grouped into "Categories" to facilitate the use of the
      Registry. Categories are described at the "Section 7.x" heading level, and columns
      are described at the "Section 7.x.y" heading level. The figure below illustrates this
      organization. An entry (row) therefore gives a complete description of a
      Registered Performance Metric.</t>
      <t>Each column serves as a checklist item and helps to avoid omissions
      during registration and Expert Review <xref target="RFC8126"/>. </t>
      <t>Registry Categories and Columns are shown below in this format:</t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
    Category
    ------------------...
    Column |  Column |...
]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Summary
----------------------------------------------------------------
Identifier | Name | URI | Desc. | Reference | Change     | Ver |
           |      |     |       |           | Controller |

Metric Definition
-----------------------------------------
Reference Definition | Fixed Parameters |

Method of Measurement
---------------------------------------------------------------------
Reference | Packet     | Traffic | Sampling     | Runtime    | Role |
Method    | Stream     | Filter  | Distribution | Parameters |      |
          | Generation |
Output
-----------------------------------------
Type | Reference  | Units | Calibration |
     | Definition |       |             |

Administrative Information
-------------------------------------
Status |Requester | Rev | Rev. Date |

Comments and Remarks
--------------------]]></artwork>
      <t>There is a blank template of the Registry template provided in
      <xref target="blank-reg-template"/> of this memo.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Summary Category</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Identifier</name>
          <t>This column provides a numeric Identifier for the Registered Performance Metric. The Identifier of each Registered Performance Metric <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be unique. Note that revising a Metric according to the process in <xref target="revise-reg-perf-metrics"/> creates a new entry in the Performance Metrics Registry with the same identifier.</t>
          <t>The Registered Performance Metric unique Identifier is an
          unbounded integer (range 0 to infinity).</t>
          <t>The Identifier 0 should be Reserved. The Identifier values from
          64512 to 65535 are reserved for private or experimental use, and the
          user may encounter overlapping uses.</t>
          <t>When adding new Registered Performance Metrics to the
          Performance Metrics Registry, IANA <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> assign the lowest
          available Identifier to the new Registered Performance Metric.</t>
          <t>If a Performance Metrics Expert providing review determines that
          there is a reason to assign a specific numeric Identifier, possibly
          leaving a temporary gap in the numbering, then the Performance Metrics
          Expert <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> inform IANA of this decision.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="name-sec7-1-2" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Name</name>
          <t>As the Name of a Registered Performance Metric is the first thing
          a potential human implementer will use when determining whether it
          is suitable for their measurement study, it is important to be as
          precise and descriptive as possible. In the future, users will review
          the Names to determine if the metric they want to measure has
          already been registered, or if a similar entry is available, as a
          basis for creating a new entry.</t>
          <t>Names are composed of the following elements, separated by an
          underscore character "_":</t>
        <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
          <li>MetricType_Method_SubTypeMethod_... Spec_Units_Output</li>
        </ul>

          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>MetricType:</dt><dd>A combination of the directional properties and
              the metric measured, such as and not limited to:</dd>
	  </dl>

<table anchor="metric-type"> 
  <tbody>         
    <tr>
      <td>RTDelay</td>
      <td>Round-Trip Delay</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>RTDNS</td>
      <td>Response Time Domain Name Service</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>RLDNS</td>
      <td>Response Loss Domain Name Service</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWDelay</td>
      <td>One-Way Delay</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>RTLoss</td>
      <td>Round-Trip Loss</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWLoss</td>
      <td>One-Way Loss</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWPDV</td>
      <td>One-Way Packet Delay Variation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWIPDV</td>
      <td>One-Way Inter-Packet Delay Variation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWReorder</td>
      <td>One-Way Packet Reordering</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWDuplic</td>
      <td>One-Way Packet Duplication</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWBTC</td>
      <td>One-Way Bulk Transport Capacity</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>OWMBM</td>
      <td>One-Way Model-Based Metric</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SPMonitor</td>
      <td>Single-Point Monitor</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>MPMonitor</td>
      <td>Multi-Point Monitor</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
             <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>Method:</dt><dd>One of the methods defined in <xref
              target="RFC7799" format="default"/>, such as and not limited
              to:</dd>
	     </dl>

<table anchor="methods">
  <tbody>      
    <tr>
      <td>Active</td>
      <td>depends on a dedicated measurement packet stream and observations of
      the stream as described in <xref target="RFC7799"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Passive</td>
      <td>depends *solely* on observation of one or more existing packet streams as described in <xref target="RFC7799"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HybridType1</td>
      <td>Hybrid Type I observations on one stream that combine both Active
      Methods and Passive Methods as described in <xref target="RFC7799"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HybridType2</td>
      <td>Hybrid Type II observations on two or more streams that combine both
      Active Methods and Passive Methods as described in <xref target="RFC7799"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Spatial</td>
      <td>spatial metric as described in <xref target="RFC5644"/></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

              <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>SubTypeMethod:</dt><dd>One or more subtypes to further describe the
              features of the entry, such as and not limited to:</dd>
	      </dl>

<table anchor="SubTypeMethod"> 
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>ICMP</td>
      <td>Internet Control Message Protocol</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>IP</td>
      <td>Internet Protocol</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>DSCPxx</td>
      <td>where xx is replaced by a Diffserv code point</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>UDP</td>
      <td>User Datagram Protocol</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>TCP</td>
      <td>Transport Control Protocol</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>QUIC</td>
      <td>QUIC transport protocol</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HS</td>
      <td>Hand-Shake, such as TCP's 3-way HS</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Poisson</td>
      <td>packet generation using Poisson distribution</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Periodic</td>
      <td>periodic packet generation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SendOnRcv</td>
      <td>sender keeps one packet in transit by sending when previous packet arrives</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>PayloadxxxxB</td>
      <td>where xxxx is replaced by an integer, the number of octets or 8-bit
      Bytes in the Payload</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SustainedBurst</td>
      <td>capacity test, worst case</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>StandingQueue</td>
      <td>test of bottleneck queue behavior</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

              <t indent="3">SubTypeMethod values are separated by a hyphen "-"
              character, which indicates that they belong to this element and
              that their order is unimportant when considering Name
              uniqueness.</t>

          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Spec:</dt><dd>An immutable document Identifier combined with a
              document section Identifier. For RFCs, this consists of the RFC
              number and major section number that specifies this Registry
              Entry in the form "RFCXXXXsecY", e.g., RFC7799sec3. Note: The
              RFC number is not the primary reference specification for the
              metric definition (e.g., <xref target="RFC7679"
              format="default"/> as the primary reference specification for
              one-way delay metrics); it will contain the placeholder
              "RFCXXXXsecY" until the
              RFC number is assigned to the specifying document and would
              remain blank in Private Registry Entries without a corresponding
              RFC. Anticipating the "RFC10K" problem, the number of the RFC
              continues to replace "RFCXXXX", regardless of the number of digits
              in the RFC number. Anticipating Registry Entries from other
              standards bodies, the form of this Name Element <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be proposed
              and reviewed for consistency and uniqueness by the Expert
              Reviewer.</dd>

              <dt>Units:</dt><dd><t>The units of measurement for the output, such as and
              not limited to:</t></dd>
          </dl>

<table anchor="units"> 
  <tbody>        
    <tr>
      <td>Seconds</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Ratio</td>
      <td>unitless</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Percent</td>
      <td>value multiplied by 100%</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Logical</td>
      <td>1 or 0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Packets</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>BPS</td>
      <td>bits per second</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>PPS</td>
      <td>packets per second</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>EventTotal</td>
      <td>for unitless counts</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Multiple</td>
      <td>more than one type of unit</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Enumerated</td>
      <td>a list of outcomes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Unitless</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

            <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
              <dt>Output:</dt><dd>The type of output resulting from measurement, such
              as and not limited to:</dd>
            </dl>

<table anchor="output">
  <tbody>      
    <tr>
      <td>Singleton</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Raw</td>
      <td>multiple singletons</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Count</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Minimum</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Maximum</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Median</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mean</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>95Percentile</td>
      <td>95th percentile</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>99Percentile</td>
      <td>99th percentile</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>StdDev</td>
      <td>standard deviation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Variance</td>
      <td></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>PFI</td>
      <td>pass, fail, inconclusive</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>FlowRecords</td>
      <td>descriptions of flows observed</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>LossRatio</td>
      <td>lost packets to total packets, &lt;=1</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

          <t>An example, as described in <xref target="RFC8912"
          sectionFormat="of" section="4"/>, is</t>

         <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
          <li>RTDelay_Active_IP-UDP-Periodic_RFC8912sec4_Seconds_95Percentile</li>
         </ul>

          <t>Note that private registries following the format described here
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use the prefix "Priv_" on any Name to avoid unintended
          conflicts (further considerations are described in <xref target="iana-cons"/>).
          Private Registry Entries usually have no specifying RFC; thus, the
          Spec: element has no clear interpretation.</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>URI</name>

          <t>The URI column <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain a URL <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/> that
          uniquely identifies and locates the Metric Entry so it is accessible
          through the Internet. The URL points to a file containing all of the
          human-readable information for one Registry Entry. The URL <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>
          reference a target file that is preferably HTML-formatted and
          contains URLs to referenced sections of HTMLized RFCs, or other
          reference specifications. These target files for different entries
          can be more easily edited and reused when preparing new entries.
          The exact form of the URL for each target file, and the target file
          itself, will be determined by IANA and reside on
          <eref target="https://www.iana.org/" brackets="angle"/>.
          <xref target="RFC8912" sectionFormat="of" section="4"/>, as well as
          subsequent major sections of that document, provide an example of a target file in HTML form.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Description</name>
          <t>A Registered Performance Metric description is a written
          representation of a particular Performance Metrics Registry Entry.
          It supplements the Registered Performance Metric Name to help
          Performance Metrics Registry users select relevant Registered
          Performance Metrics.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference</name>

          <t>This entry gives the specification containing the candidate
          Registry Entry that was reviewed and agreed upon, if such an RFC or
          other specification exists.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Change Controller</name>
          <t>This entry names the entity responsible for approving revisions
          to the Registry Entry and <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> provide contact information (for an
          individual, where appropriate).</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Version (of Registry Format)</name>
<t>This column gives the version number for the Registry format used, at the time the Performance Metric is registered. The format complying with this memo <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use 1.0. A new RFC that changes the Registry format will designate a new version number corresponding to that format. The version number of Registry Entries <bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14> change unless the Registry Entry is updated to reflect the Registry format (following the procedures in <xref target="managing-perf-metric-grp"/>).</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">

        <name>Metric Definition Category</name>
        <t>This category includes columns to prompt all necessary details
        related to the metric definition, including the immutable document
        reference and values of input factors, called "Fixed Parameters", which
        are left open in the immutable document but have a particular value
        defined by the Performance Metric.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference Definition</name>
          <t>This entry provides a reference (or references) to the relevant
          sections of the document or documents that define the metric, as well as any
          supplemental information needed to ensure an unambiguous definition
          for implementations. A given reference needs to be an immutable
          document, such as an RFC; for other standards bodies, it is likely
          to be necessary to reference a specific, dated version of a
          specification.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Fixed Parameters</name>
          <t>Fixed Parameters are Parameters whose values must be specified in
          the Performance Metrics Registry. The measurement system uses these
          values.</t>
          <t>Where referenced metrics supply a list of Parameters as part of
          their descriptive template, a subset of the Parameters will be
          designated as Fixed Parameters. As an example for Active Metrics,
          Fixed Parameters determine most or all of the IPPM framework
          convention "packets of Type-P" as described in <xref
          target="RFC2330" format="default"/>, such as transport protocol,
          payload length, TTL, etc. An example for Passive Metrics is for an RTP packet loss
          calculation that relies on the validation of a packet as RTP, which
          is a multi-packet validation controlled by the MIN_SEQUENTIAL variable as defined
          by <xref target="RFC3550" format="default"/>. Varying MIN_SEQUENTIAL values can alter
          the loss report, and this variable could be set as a Fixed
          Parameter.</t>
          <t>Parameters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have well-defined names. For human readers, the
          hanging-indent style is preferred, and any Parameter names and
          definitions that do not appear in the Reference Method Specification
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> appear in this column (or the Runtime Parameters column).</t>
          <t>Parameters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have a well-specified data format.</t>
          <t>A Parameter that is a Fixed Parameter for one Performance
          Metrics Registry Entry may be designated as a Runtime Parameter for
          another Performance Metrics Registry Entry.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Method of Measurement Category</name>
        <t>This category includes columns for references to relevant sections
        of the immutable document(s) and any supplemental information needed
        to ensure an unambiguous method for implementations.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference Method</name>
          <t>This entry provides references to relevant sections of immutable
          documents, such as RFC(s) (for other standards bodies, it is likely
          to be necessary to reference a specific, dated version of a
          specification) describing the Method of Measurement, as well as any
          supplemental information needed to ensure unambiguous interpretation
          for implementations referring to the immutable document text.</t>
          <t>Specifically, this section should include pointers to pseudocode
          or actual code that could be used for an unambiguous
          implementation.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Packet Stream Generation</name>
          <t>This column applies to Performance Metrics that generate traffic
          as part of their Measurement Method, including, but not necessarily
          limited to, Active Metrics. The generated traffic is referred to as a
          "stream", and this column describes its characteristics.</t>
          <t>Each entry for this column contains the following information:
          </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Value:</dt><dd>The name of the packet stream scheduling
              discipline</dd>
            <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>The specification where the Parameters of the
              stream are defined</dd>
      </dl>
          <t>The packet generation stream may require Parameters such as the
          average packet rate and distribution truncation value for streams
          with Poisson-distributed inter-packet sending times. If such
          Parameters are needed, they should be included in either the Fixed
          Parameters column or the Runtime Parameters column, depending on
          whether they will be fixed or will be an input for the metric.</t>
          <t>The simplest example of stream specification is singleton
          scheduling (see <xref target="RFC2330" format="default"/>), where a
          single atomic measurement is conducted. Each atomic measurement
          could consist of sending a single packet (such as a DNS request) or
          sending several packets (for example, to request a web page). Other
          streams support a series of atomic measurements using pairs of
          packets, where the packet stream follows a schedule defining the
          timing between transmitted packets, and an atomic measurement
          assesses the reception time between successive packets (e.g., a
          measurement of Inter-Packet Delay Variation). More complex streams
          and measurement relationships are possible. Principally, two
          different streams are used in IPPM Metrics: (1)&nbsp;Poisson,
          distributed as described in <xref target="RFC2330"
          format="default"/> and (2)&nbsp;periodic, as described in <xref
          target="RFC3432" format="default"/>. Both Poisson and periodic have
          their own unique Parameters, and the relevant set of Parameter names
          and values should be included in either the Fixed Parameters column
          or the Runtime Parameters column.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Traffic Filter</name>
          <t>This column applies to Performance Metrics that observe packets
          flowing through (the device with) the Measurement Agent, i.e.,
          packets that are not necessarily addressed to the Measurement Agent.
          This includes, but is not limited to, Passive Metrics. The filter
          specifies the traffic that is measured. This includes protocol field
          values/ranges, such as address ranges, and flow or session
          Identifiers.</t>
          <t>The Traffic Filter itself depends on the needs of the metric itself
          and a balance of an operator's measurement needs and a user's need
          for privacy. Mechanics for conveying the filter criteria might be
          the BPF (Berkeley Packet Filter) or PSAMP (Packet Sampling) <xref target="RFC5475" format="default"/>
          Property Match Filtering, which reuses IPFIX <xref target="RFC7012" format="default"/>. An example BPF string for matching TCP/80
          traffic to remote Destination net 192.0.2.0/24 would be "dst net
          192.0.2.0/24 and tcp dst port 80". More complex filter engines may allow for matching using Deep Packet Inspection (DPI) technology.</t>
          <t>The Traffic Filter includes the following information: </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Type:</dt><dd>The type of Traffic Filter used, e.g., BPF, PSAMP,
              OpenFlow rule, etc., as defined by a normative reference</dd>
            <dt>Value:</dt><dd>The actual set of rules expressed</dd>
      </dl>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Sampling Distribution</name>
          <t>The sampling distribution defines, out of all of the packets that
          match the Traffic Filter, which one or more of those packets are
          actually used for the measurement.  One possibility is "all", which
          implies that all packets matching the Traffic Filter are considered,
          but there may be other sampling strategies. It includes the following information: </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Value:</dt><dd>The name of the sampling distribution</dd>
            <dt>Reference definition:</dt><dd>Pointer to the specification where the
              sampling distribution is properly defined</dd>
        </dl>
          <t>The sampling distribution may require Parameters. If such
          Parameters are needed, they should be included in either the Fixed
          Parameters column or the Runtime Parameters column, depending on
          whether they will be fixed or will be an input for the metric.</t>
          <t>PSAMP is documented in "Sampling and Filtering Techniques for IP Packet Selection" <xref target="RFC5475" format="default"/>,
          while "A Framework for Packet Selection and Reporting" <xref target="RFC5474" format="default"/> provides more background information. The
          sampling distribution Parameters might be expressed in terms of
          the model described in "Information Model for Packet Sampling
          Exports" <xref target="RFC5477" format="default"/> and the process
          provided in "Flow Selection Techniques" <xref target="RFC7014" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Runtime Parameters</name>
          <t>In contrast to the Fixed Parameters, Runtime Parameters are Parameters that do not change the fundamental nature of the measurement and their values are not specified in the Performance Metrics Registry. They are left as variables in the Registry, as an aid to the measurement system implementer or user. Their values are supplied on execution, configured into the measurement system, and reported with the Measurement Results (so that the context is complete).</t>
          <t>Where metrics supply a list of Parameters as part of their
          descriptive template, a subset of the Parameters will be designated
          as Runtime Parameters.</t>
          <t>Parameters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have well-defined names. For human readers, the
          hanging-indent style is preferred, and the names and definitions
          that do not appear in the Reference Method Specification <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> appear
          in this column.</t>
          <t>A data format for each Runtime Parameter <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be specified in
          this column, to simplify the control and implementation of
          measurement devices. For example, Parameters that include an IPv4
          address can be encoded as a 32-bit integer (i.e., a binary
          base64-encoded value) or "ip&nbhy;address" as defined in <xref target="RFC6991" format="default"/>.
          The actual encoding(s) used must be explicitly defined for each
          Runtime Parameter. IPv6 addresses and options <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be accommodated,
          allowing Registered Performance Metrics to be used in that address family. Other
          address families are permissible.</t>
          <t>Examples of Runtime Parameters include IP addresses, measurement
          point designations, start times and end times for measurement, and
          other information essential to the Method of Measurement.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Role</name>
          <t>In some Methods of Measurement, there may be several Roles
          defined, e.g., for a one-way packet delay Active Measurement, there
          is one Measurement Agent that generates the packets and another
          Agent that receives the packets. This column contains the name of
          the Role(s) for this particular entry. In the one-way delay example
          above, there should be two entries in the Registry's Role column, one
          for each Role (Source and Destination). When a Measurement Agent is
          instructed to perform the "Source" Role for the one-way delay metric,
          the Agent knows that it is required to generate packets. The values
          for this field are defined in the Reference Method of Measurement
          (and this frequently results in abbreviated Role names such as
          "Src").</t>
          <t>When the Role column of a Registry Entry defines more than one
          Role, the Role <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be treated as a Runtime Parameter and
          supplied for execution. It should be noted that the LMAP framework
          <xref target="RFC7594" format="default"/> distinguishes the Role from other Runtime
          Parameters.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Output Category</name>
        <t>For entries that involve a stream and many singleton measurements,
        a statistic may be specified in this column to summarize the results
        to a single value. If the complete set of measured singletons is
        output, this will be specified here.</t>
        <t>Some metrics embed one specific statistic in the reference metric
        definition, while others allow several output types or statistics.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Type</name>
          <t>This column contains the name of the output type. The output type
          defines a single type of result that the metric produces. It can be
          the raw results (packet send times and singleton metrics), or it can
          be a summary statistic. The specification of the output type <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          define the format of the output. In some systems, format
          specifications will simplify both measurement implementation and
          collection/storage tasks. Note that if two different statistics are
          required from a single measurement (for example, both "Xth
          percentile mean" and "Raw"), then a new output type must be defined
          ("Xth percentile mean AND Raw"). See <xref target="name-sec7-1-2"/>
          above for a list of output types.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference Definition</name>
          <t>This column contains a pointer to the specification(s) where the
          output type and format are defined.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Metric Units</name>
          <t>The measured results must be expressed using some standard
          dimension or units of measure. This column provides the units.</t>
          <t>When a sample of singletons (see <xref target="RFC2330"
          sectionFormat="of" section="11"/> for definitions of these terms) is collected,
          this entry will specify the units for each measured value.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Calibration</name>
          <t>Some specifications for Methods of Measurement include the
          ability to perform an error calibration. <xref target="RFC7679" sectionFormat="of" section="3.7.3"/> is one example. In the Registry Entry, this field
          will identify a method of calibration for the metric, and, when
          available, the measurement system <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> perform the calibration
          when requested and produce the output with an indication that it is
          the result of a calibration method. In-situ calibration could be
          enabled with an internal loopback that includes as much of the
          measurement system as possible, performs address manipulation as
          needed, and provides some form of isolation (e.g., deterministic
          delay) to avoid send-receive interface contention. Some portion of
          the random and systematic error can be characterized in this way.</t>
          <t>For one-way delay measurements, the error calibration must
          include an assessment of the internal clock synchronization with its
          external reference (this internal clock is supplying timestamps for
          measurement). In practice, the time offsets of clocks at both the
          Source and Destination are needed to estimate the systematic error
          due to imperfect clock synchronization (the time offsets are
          smoothed; thus, the random variation is not usually represented in
          the results).</t>
          <t>Both internal loopback calibration and clock synchronization can
          be used to estimate the *available accuracy* of the Output Metric
          Units. For example, repeated loopback delay measurements will reveal
          the portion of the output result resolution that is the result of
          system noise and is thus inaccurate.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Administrative Information</name>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Status</name>
          <t>This entry indicates the status of the specification of this
          Registered Performance Metric.  Allowed values are 'Current',
          'Deprecated', and Obsolete.  All newly defined Registered
          Performance Metrics have 'Current' Status.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Requester</name>
          <t>This entry indicates the requester for the Registered Performance Metric. The
          requester <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be a document (such as an RFC) or a person.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Revision</name>
          <t>This entry indicates the revision number of a Registered Performance Metric, starting at 0 for Registered Performance Metrics at the time of definition and incremented by one for each revision. However, in the case of a non-backward-compatible revision, see <xref target="deprecating-metrics"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Revision Date</name>
          <t>This entry indicates the date of acceptance of the most recent revision for the
          Registered Performance Metric. The date <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be determined by IANA
          and the reviewing Performance Metrics Expert.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="remarks" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Comments and Remarks</name>
        <t>Besides providing additional details that do not appear in other
        categories, this open category (single column) allows unforeseen
        issues to be addressed by simply updating this informational
        entry.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="managing-perf-metric-grp" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Processes for Managing the Performance Metrics Registry Group</name>
      <t>Once a Performance Metric or set of Performance Metrics has been
      identified for a given application, candidate Performance Metrics
      Registry Entry specifications prepared in accordance with <xref target="columns" format="default"/> should be submitted to IANA to follow the process for
      review by the Performance Metrics Experts, as defined below. This process
      is also used for other changes to a Performance Metrics Registry Entry, such
      as deprecation or revision, as described later in this section.</t>
      <t>It is desirable that the author(s) of a candidate Performance Metrics
      Registry Entry seek review in the relevant IETF working group or offer
      the opportunity for review on the working group mailing list.</t>
      <section anchor="add-new-perf-metrics" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Adding New Performance Metrics to the Performance Metrics Registry</name>
        <t>Requests to add Registered Performance Metrics in the Performance
        Metrics Registry <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be submitted to IANA, which forwards the
        request to a designated group of experts (Performance Metrics Experts)
        appointed by the IESG; these are the reviewers called for by the
        Specification Required policy <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/> defined for the
        Performance Metrics Registry. The Performance Metrics Experts review
        the request for such things as compliance with this document,
        compliance with other applicable Performance Metrics-related RFCs, and
        consistency with the currently defined set of Registered Performance
        Metrics. The most efficient path for submission begins with
        preparation of an Internet-Draft containing the proposed Performance
        Metrics Registry Entry using the template in <xref target="blank-reg-template"/>, so that the
        submission formatting will benefit from the normal IETF Internet-Draft
        submission processing (including HTMLization).</t>
        <t>Submission to IANA may be during IESG review (leading to IETF
        Standards Action), where an Internet-Draft proposes one or more
        Registered Performance Metrics to be added to the Performance Metrics
        Registry, including the text of the proposed Registered Performance
        Metric&wj;(s).</t>
        <t>If an RFC-to-be includes a Performance Metric and a proposed
        Performance Metrics Registry Entry but the Performance Metrics Expert's
        review determines that one or more of the criteria listed in <xref target="metrics-criteria"/> have not
        been met, then the proposed Performance Metrics Registry Entry <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        removed from the text. Once evidence exists that the Performance
        Metric meets the criteria in <xref target="metrics-criteria"/>, the proposed Performance
        Metrics Registry Entry <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be submitted to IANA to be evaluated in
        consultation with the Performance Metrics Experts for registration at
        that time.</t>
        <t>Authors of proposed Registered Performance Metrics <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> review
        compliance with the specifications in this document to check their
        submissions before sending them to IANA.</t>
        <t>At least one Performance Metrics Expert should endeavor to complete
        referred reviews in a timely manner. If the request is acceptable, the
        Performance Metrics Experts signify their approval to IANA, and IANA
        updates the Performance Metrics Registry. If the request is not
        acceptable, the Performance Metrics Experts <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
        coordinate with the requester to change the request so that it is
        compliant; otherwise, IANA <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> coordinate resolution
        of issues on behalf of the expert. The Performance Metrics Experts
        <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to reject clearly frivolous or inappropriate
        change requests outright, but such exceptional circumstances should be
        rare.</t>
	<t>If the proposed Metric is unique in a significant way, in order to
	properly describe the Metric, it may be necessary to propose a new Name
	Element Registry, or (more likely) a new Entry in an existing Name
	Element Registry. This proposal is part of the request for the new
	Metric, so that it undergoes the same IANA review and approval
	process.
	</t>
        <t>Decisions by the Performance Metrics Experts may be appealed per
        <xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="of" section="10"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="revise-reg-perf-metrics" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Backward-Compatible Revision of Registered Performance Metrics</name>
        <t>A request for revision is only permitted when the requested changes
        maintain backward compatibility with implementations of the prior
        Performance Metrics Registry Entry describing a Registered Performance
        Metric (entries with lower revision numbers but having the same Identifier
        and Name).</t>
        <t>The purpose of the Status field in the Performance Metrics Registry is to indicate whether the entry for a Registered Performance Metric is 'Current', 'Deprecated', or 'Obsolete'. The term 'deprecated' is used when an entry is replaced, either with a backwards-compatible revision (this sub-section) or with a non-backwards-compatible revision (in <xref target="deprecating-metrics"/>).</t>
        <t>In addition, no policy is defined for revising the Performance
        Metric Entries in the IANA Registry or addressing errors therein. To
        be clear, changes and deprecations within the Performance Metrics
        Registry are not encouraged and should be avoided to the extent
        possible. However, in recognition that change is inevitable, the
        provisions of this section address the need for revisions.</t>
        <t>Revisions are initiated by sending a candidate Registered
        Performance Metric definition to IANA, per <xref target="add-new-perf-metrics"/>, identifying
        the existing Performance Metrics Registry Entry, and explaining how
        and why the existing entry should be revised.</t>
        <t>The primary requirement in the definition of procedures for
        managing changes to existing Registered Performance Metrics is
        avoidance of measurement interoperability problems; the Performance
        Metrics Experts must work to maintain interoperability above all else.
        Changes to Registered Performance Metrics may only be done in an
        interoperable way; necessary changes that cannot be done in a way that
        allows interoperability with unchanged implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> result in
        the creation of a new Registered Performance Metric (with a new Name,
        replacing the RFCXXXXsecY portion of the Name) and possibly the
        deprecation of the earlier metric.</t>
        <t>A change to a Registered Performance Metric <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be determined to
        be backward compatible when: </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>it involves the correction of an error that is obviously only
            editorial, or</li>
          <li>it corrects an ambiguity in the Registered Performance Metric's
            definition, which itself leads to issues severe enough to prevent
            the Registered Performance Metric's usage as originally defined,
            or</li>
          <li>it corrects missing information in the metric definition
            without changing its meaning (e.g., the explicit definition of
            'quantity' semantics for numeric fields without a Data Type
            Semantics value), or</li>
          <li>it harmonizes with an external reference that was itself
            corrected, or</li>
          <li>if the current Registry format has been revised by adding a new
          column that is not relevant to an existing Registered Performance
          Metric (i.e., the new column can be safely filled in with Not
          Applicable).</li>
          </ol>
        <t>If a Performance Metric revision is deemed permissible and
        backward compatible by the Performance Metrics Experts, according to
        the rules in this document, IANA <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> execute the change(s) in the
        Performance Metrics Registry. The requester of the change is appended
        to the original requester in the Performance Metrics Registry. The
        Name of the revised Registered Performance Metric, including the
        RFCXXXXsecY portion of the Name, <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> remain unchanged even when the
        change is the result of IETF Standards Action. The revised Registry
        Entry <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> reference the new immutable document, such as an RFC. For other standards bodies, it is likely to be necessary to reference
        a specific, dated version of a specification, in an appropriate
        category and column.</t>
        <t>Each Registered Performance Metric in the Performance Metrics
        Registry has a revision number, starting at zero. Each change to a
        Registered Performance Metric following this process increments the
        revision number by one.</t>
        <t>When a revised Registered Performance Metric is accepted into the
        Performance Metrics Registry, the date of acceptance of the most
        recent revision is placed into the Revision Date column of the
        Registry for that Registered Performance Metric.</t>
        <t>Where applicable, additions to Registered Performance Metrics in
        the form of text in the Comments or Remarks column should include the date, but such
        additions may not constitute a revision according to this process.</t>
        <t>Older versions of the updated Metric Entries are kept in the
        Registry for archival purposes. The older entries are kept with all
        fields unmodified (including Revision Date) except for the Status field,
        which <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be changed to 'Deprecated'.</t>
	<t>This process should not in any way be construed as allowing the
   Performance Metrics Experts to overrule IETF consensus.
   Specifically, any Registered Performance Metrics that were added to
   the Performance Metrics Registry with IETF consensus require IETF
   consensus for revision or deprecation.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="deprecating-metrics" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Non-Backward-Compatible Deprecation of Registered Performance Metrics</name>
        <t>This section describes how to make a non-backward-compatible update
        to a Registered Performance Metric. A Registered Performance Metric
        <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be deprecated and replaced when:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>the Registered Performance Metric definition has an error or
            shortcoming that cannot be permissibly changed per <xref target="revise-reg-perf-metrics"/>
            ("Revising Registered Performance Metrics"), or</li>
          <li>the deprecation harmonizes with an external reference that was
            itself deprecated through that reference's accepted deprecation
            method.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>A request for deprecation is sent to IANA, which passes it to the
        Performance Metrics Experts for review. When deprecating a Performance
        Metric, the Performance Metric Description in the Performance Metrics
        Registry <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be updated to explain the deprecation, as well as to
        refer to the new Performance Metric created to replace the deprecated
        Performance Metric.</t>
        <t>When a new, non-backward-compatible Performance Metric replaces a
        (now) deprecated metric, the revision number of the new Registered
        Performance Metric is incremented over the value in the deprecated
        version, and the current date is entered as the Revision Date of the
        new Registered Performance Metric.</t>

        <t>The intentional use of deprecated Registered Performance Metrics
        should result in a log entry or human-readable warning by the
        respective application.</t>
        <t>Names and Metric IDs of deprecated Registered Performance Metrics
        must not be reused.</t>
        <t>The deprecated entries are kept with all Administrative columns
        unmodified, except the Status field (which is changed to
        'Deprecated').</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
	<name>Obsolete Registry Entries</name>
	<t>Existing Registry Entries may become obsolete over time due to:</t>
	<ol>
         <li>the Registered Performance Metric is found to contain considerable
       errors (and no one sees the value in the effort to fix it), or</li>
         <li>one or more critical References (or sections thereof) have been
        designated obsolete by the SDO, or</li>
         <li>other reasons brought to the attention of IANA and the Registry
       Experts.</li>
        </ol>
	<t>When a Performance Metric Registry Entry is declared obsolete, the
	Performance Metric Description in the Performance Metrics Registry is
	updated to explain the reasons the Entry is now obsolete and has not
	been replaced (Deprecation always involves replacement).</t>
        <t> Obsolete entries are kept with all Administrative columns
        unmodified, except the Status field (which is changed to
        'Obsolete'). </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
	<name>Registry Format Version and Future Changes/Extensions</name>
   <t>The Registry Format Version defined in this memo is 1.0, and candidate
   Registry Entries complying with this memo <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use 1.0.</t>
  
   <t>The Registry Format can only be updated by publishing a new RFC with
   the new format (Standards Action).</t>
 
   <t>When a Registered Performance Metric is created or revised, then it
   uses the most recent Registry Format Version.</t>
  
   <t>Only one form of Registry extension is envisaged:</t>
 
   <t indent="3">Adding columns, or both categories and columns, to accommodate
   unanticipated aspects of new measurements and metric categories.</t>
  
   <t>If the Performance Metrics Registry is extended in this way, the
   version number of future entries complying with the extension <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>
   be incremented (in either the unit or the tenths digit, depending
   on the degree of extension).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document defines a Registry structure and does not itself
      introduce any new security considerations for the Internet. The
      definition of Performance Metrics for this Registry may introduce some
      security concerns, but the mandatory references should have their own
      considerations for security, and such definitions should be reviewed
      with security in mind if the security considerations are not covered by
      one or more reference standards.</t>
      <t>The aggregated results of the Performance Metrics described in this
      Registry might reveal network topology information that may be
      considered sensitive. If such cases are found, then access control
      mechanisms should be applied.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-cons" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>With the background and processes described in earlier sections, IANA 
      has taken the actions described below.</t>  

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Registry Group</name>
        <t>The new Registry group is named Performance Metrics. This document
        refers to it as the Performance Metrics Group or Registry Group",
        meaning all registrations appearing on <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/performance-metrics">&lt;https://www.iana.org/assignments/performance-metrics&gt;</eref>.</t>

	<t>For clarity, note that this document and <xref target="RFC8912"/>
	use the following conventions to refer to the various IANA registries
	related to Performance Metrics.</t>

<table anchor="IANAterms-map"> 
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th></th>
      <th>RFC 8911 and RFC 8912</th>
      <th>IANA Web page</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Page Title</td>
      <td>Performance Metrics Group</td>
      <td>Performance Metrics</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Main Registry</td>
      <td>Performance Metrics Registry</td>
      <td>Performance Metrics Registry</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Registry Row</td>
      <td>Performance Metrics Registry Entry</td>
      <td>registration (also template)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

        <t>Registration Procedure: Specification Required</t>
        <t>Reference: RFC 8911</t>
        <t>Experts: Performance Metrics Experts</t>

      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Performance Metrics Name Elements</name>
        <t>This memo specifies and populates the Registries for the
        Performance Metric Name Elements.  The Name assigned to a Performance
        Metric Registry Entry consists of multiple Elements separated by an
        "_" (underscore), in the order defined in <xref 
        target="name-sec7-1-2"/>.  IANA has created the following registries,
        which contain the current set of possibilities for each Element in the
        Performance Metric Name.</t>
        <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
          <li>MetricType</li>
          <li>Method</li>
          <li>SubTypeMethod</li>
          <li>Spec</li>
          <li>Units</li>
          <li>Output</li>
        </ul>
        <t>At creation, IANA has populated the Registered Performance Metrics Name Elements 
        using the lists of values for each Name
        Element listed in <xref target="name-sec7-1-2"/>. The Name Elements in each Registry
        are case sensitive.</t>
        <t>When preparing a Metric Entry for registration, the developer
        <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> choose Name Elements from among the registered elements.
        However, if the proposed metric is unique in a significant way, it may
        be necessary to propose a new Name Element to properly describe the
        metric, as described below.</t>

        <t>A candidate Metric Entry proposes a set of values for its Name
        Elements. These are reviewed by IANA and an Expert Reviewer. It is
        possible that a candidate Metric Entry proposes a new value for a Name
        Element (that is, one that is not in the existing list of
        possibilities), or even that it proposes a new Name Element. Such new
        assignments are administered by IANA through the Specification
        Required policy <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>, which includes Expert Review (i.e., review
        by one of a group of Performance Metrics Experts, who are appointed by
        the IESG upon recommendation of the Transport Area Directors).</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>New Performance Metrics Registry</name>
        <t>This document specifies the Performance Metrics Registry. 
        The Registry contains the following columns in the Summary category:</t>
        <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
          <li>Identifier</li>
          <li>Name</li>
          <li>URI</li>
          <li>Description</li>
          <li>Reference</li>
          <li>Change Controller</li>
          <li>Version</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Descriptions of these columns and additional information
        found in the template for Registry Entries (categories and columns)
        are further defined in <xref target="columns" format="default"/>.</t>

        <t>The Identifier 0 should be Reserved. The Registered Performance
        Metric unique Identifier is an unbounded integer (range 0 to
        infinity). The Identifier values from 64512 to 65535 are reserved for
        private or experimental use, and the user may encounter overlapping
        uses. When adding new Registered Performance Metrics to the
        Performance Metrics Registry, IANA <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> assign the lowest available
        Identifier to the new Registered Performance Metric. If a Performance
        Metrics Expert providing review determines that there is a reason to
        assign a specific numeric Identifier, possibly leaving a temporary gap
        in the numbering, then the Performance Metrics Expert <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> inform IANA of
        this decision.</t>
        <t>Names starting with the prefix "Priv_" are reserved for private use
        and are not considered for registration. The Name column entries are
        further defined in <xref target="columns" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>The URI column will have a URL to each completed
        Registry Entry. The Registry Entry text <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be HTMLized to aid the
        reader (similar to the way that Internet-Drafts are HTMLized, the same tool can perform the function), with links to referenced section(s) of an RFC or another
        immutable document.</t>
        <t>The Reference column will include an RFC number, an approved
        specification designator from another standards body, or some other
        immutable document.</t>

        <t>New assignments for the Performance Metrics Registry will be
   administered by IANA through the Specification Required policy
   <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/> (which includes Expert Review, i.e., review by one of a
   group of experts -- in the case of this document, the Performance
   Metrics Experts, who are appointed by the IESG upon recommendation of
   the Transport Area Directors) or by Standards Action.  The experts can be initially drawn
        from the Working Group Chairs, document editors, and members of the
        Performance Metrics Directorate, among other sources of experts.</t>
        <t>Extensions to the Performance Metrics Registry require IETF
        Standards Action. Only one form of Registry extension is
        envisaged:</t>
        <ul empty="false" spacing="normal">
          <li>Adding columns, or both categories and columns, to accommodate
            unanticipated aspects of new measurements and metric
            categories.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>If the Performance Metrics Registry is extended in this way,
        the version number of future entries complying with the extension
        <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be incremented (in either the unit or the tenths digit, depending on
        the degree of extension).</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="blank-reg-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Blank Registry Template</name>
      <t>This section provides a blank template to help IANA and Registry
      Entry writers.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Summary</name>
        <t>This category includes multiple indexes to the Registry Entry: the
        element ID and Metric Name.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>ID (Identifier)</name>
          <t>&lt;insert a numeric Identifier, an integer, TBD&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Name</name>
          <t>&lt;insert the Name, according to the metric naming convention&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>URI</name>
          <t>URL: <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/performance-metrics/"/>
          ... &lt;Name&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Description</name>
          <t>&lt;provide a description&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference</name> <t>&lt;provide the RFC or other specification
          that contains the approved candidate Registry Entry&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Change Controller</name>
          <t>&lt;provide information regarding the entity responsible for
          approving revisions to the Registry Entry (including contact information for an individual, where appropriate)&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Version (of Registry Format)</name>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Metric Definition</name>
        <t>This category includes columns to prompt the entry of all necessary
        details related to the metric definition, including the immutable
        document reference and values of input factors, called "Fixed
        Parameters".</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference Definition</name>
          <t>&lt;provide a full bibliographic reference to an immutable document&gt;</t>
          <t>&lt;provide a specific section reference and additional clarifications, if
          needed&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Fixed Parameters</name>
          <t>&lt;list and specify Fixed Parameters, input factors that must be
          determined and embedded in the measurement system for use when
          needed&gt;</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Method of Measurement</name>
        <t>This category includes columns for references to relevant sections
        of the immutable document&wj;(s) and any supplemental information needed
        to ensure an unambiguous method for implementations.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference Method</name>
          <t>&lt;for the metric, insert relevant section references and
          supplemental info&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Packet Stream Generation</name>
          <t>&lt;provide a list of generation Parameters and section/spec references if
          needed&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Traffic Filtering (Observation) Details</name>
          <t>This category provides the filter details (when present), which
          qualify the set of packets that contribute to the measured results
          from among all packets observed.</t>
          <t>&lt;provide a section reference&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Sampling Distribution</name>
          <t>&lt;insert time distribution details, or how this is different from
          the filter&gt;</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Runtime Parameters and Data Format</name>
          <t>Runtime Parameters are input factors that must be determined,
          configured into the measurement system, and reported with the
          results for the context to be complete.</t>
          <t>&lt;provide a list of Runtime Parameters and their data formats&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Roles</name>
          <t>&lt;list the names of the different Roles from the Measurement
          Method&gt;</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Output</name>
        <t>This category specifies all details of the output of measurements
        using the metric.</t>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Type</name>
          <t>&lt;insert the name of the output type -- raw results or a selected summary
          statistic&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Reference Definition</name>
          <t>&lt;describe the reference data format for each type of
          result&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Metric Units</name>
          <t>&lt;insert units for the measured results, and provide the reference
          specification&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Calibration</name>
          <t>&lt;insert information on calibration&gt;</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Administrative Items</name>
        <t>This category provides administrative information.</t>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Status</name>
          <t>&lt;provide status: 'Current' or 'Deprecated'&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Requester</name>
          <t>&lt;provide a person's name, an RFC number, etc.&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Revision</name>
          <t>&lt;provide the revision number: starts at 0&gt;</t>
        </section>

        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Revision Date</name>
          <t>&lt;provide the date, in YYYY-MM-DD format&gt;</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Comments and Remarks</name>
        <t>&lt;list any additional (informational) details for this entry&gt;</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2330.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6390.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6576.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7799.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5644.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7679.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2681.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3432.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3611.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4148.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5474.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5475.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5477.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6035.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6248.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7012.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7014.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7594.xml"/>

<!-- draft-ietf-ippm-initial-registry (RFC 8912) -->
        <reference anchor="RFC8912" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8912">
          <front>
            <title>Initial Performance Metrics Registry Entries</title>
            <author initials="A" surname="Morton" fullname="Alfred Morton">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="M" surname="Bagnulo" fullname="Marcelo Bagnulo">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="P" surname="Eardley" fullname="Philip Eardley">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="K" surname="D'Souza" fullname="Kevin D'Souza">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="November" year="2021"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8912"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8912"/>
        </reference>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6991.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Brian Trammell"/> and <contact
      fullname="Bill Cerveny"/>, IPPM co-chairs during the development of this
      memo, for leading several brainstorming sessions on this topic. Thanks
      to <contact fullname="Barbara Stark"/> and <contact fullname="Juergen
      Schoenwaelder"/> for the detailed feedback and suggestions. Thanks to
      <contact fullname="Andrew McGregor"/> for suggestions on metric
      naming. Thanks to <contact fullname="Michelle Cotton"/> for her early
      IANA review, and to <contact fullname="Amanda Baber"/> for answering
      questions related to the presentation of the Registry and accessibility
      of the complete template via URL. Thanks to <contact fullname="Roni
      Even"/> for his review and suggestions to generalize the
      procedures. Thanks to all of the Area Directors for their reviews.</t>
    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
