<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc 
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
number="8716"
updates="7776" 
obsoletes="" 
category="bcp" 
consensus="true"
submissionType="IETF" 
ipr="trust200902" 
sortRefs="true" 
symRefs="true" 
xml:lang="en" 
docName="draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc7776bis-03" 
tocInclude="true" 
version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.34.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Anti-Harassment LLC Update">Update to the IETF
    Anti-Harassment Procedures for the Replacement of the IETF Administrative
    Oversight Committee (IAOC) with the IETF Administration LLC</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8716"/>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="25"/>
    <author fullname="Pete Resnick" initials="P." surname="Resnick">
      <organization>Episteme Technology Consulting LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>503 West Indiana Avenue</street>
          <city>Urbana</city>
          <region>Illinois</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
          <code>61801-4941</code>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 217 337 1905</phone>
        <email>resnick@episteme.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Adrian Farrel" initials="A." surname="Farrel">
      <organization>Old Dog Consulting</organization>
      <address>
        <email>adrian@olddog.co.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2020"/>
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>IASA 2.0</workgroup>
    <keyword>Harassment</keyword>
    <keyword>Ombudsteam</keyword>
    <keyword>IAOC</keyword>
    <keyword>IETF Administration LLC</keyword>
    <keyword>IASA</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>The IETF Anti-Harassment Procedures are described in RFC 7776.</t>
      <t>The IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) has been replaced by the IETF Administration LLC, and the IETF Administrative Director has been replaced by the IETF LLC Executive Director.  This document updates RFC 7776 to amend these terms.</t>
      <t>RFC 7776 contained updates to RFC 7437.  RFC 8713 has incorporated those updates, so this document also updates RFC 7776 to remove those updates.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The IETF Anti-Harassment Procedures are described in RFC 7776 <xref target="RFC7776" format="default"/>.  Those procedures include direction for the IETF Chair and Ombudsteam to take advice from the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) with respect to the budget available for training.</t>
      <t>The IAOC has been replaced by the IETF Administration LLC, and the IETF Administrative Director has been replaced by the IETF LLC Executive Director.  This document updates RFC 7776 to amend these terms and to update a reference.</t>
      <t>RFC 7776 contained updates to <xref target="RFC7437" format="default"/>.  <xref target="RFC8713" format="default"/> has incorporated those updates, so this document also updates RFC 7776 to remove those updates.</t>
      <t>This document makes no other changes to the procedures described in RFC 7776.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="changes" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Changes to RFC 7776</name>
      <section anchor="changes3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Changes to Section 3.4</name>

        <t><xref target="RFC7776" section="3.4" sectionFormat="of"
	format="default"/> is about the qualifications and training of the Ombudsteam.  The last paragraph of that section is replaced as follows:</t>
        <t>OLD
        </t>
          <blockquote>In determining the appropriate training, the IETF Chair and Ombudsteam shall take professional advice and will consult with the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) with respect to the overall IETF budget.</blockquote>
        <t>NEW
        </t>
          <blockquote>In determining the appropriate training, the IETF Chair and Ombudsteam shall take professional advice and will consult with the IETF Administration LLC with respect to the overall IETF budget.</blockquote>
        <t>END</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="changes5" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Changes to Section 5</name>

        <t><xref target="RFC7776" section="5" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/> is about remedies available to the Ombudsteam.  The last paragraph of that section is replaced as follows:</t>
        <t>OLD
        </t>
          <blockquote>Where specific action is required to ensure that a remedy is realized or enforced, the Ombudsteam will make a request in writing to the IETF Secretariat and/or IETF Administrative Director (IAD) to take action as appropriate.</blockquote>
        <t>NEW
        </t>
          <blockquote>Where specific action is required to ensure that a remedy is realized or enforced, the Ombudsteam will make a request in writing to the IETF Secretariat and/or IETF LLC Executive Director to take action as appropriate.</blockquote>
        <t>END</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="changesref" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Changes to References to RFC 7437</name>
        <t>RFC 7776 updated RFC 7437 <xref target="RFC7437" format="default"/> by allowing the Ombudsteam to form a recall petition.  This document does not change any of the associated processes. However,
               during the process of documenting the replacement of the IAOC by the IETF Administration LLC, RFC 7437 has been obsoleted by <xref target="RFC8713" format="default"/>, and as part
               of that work, <xref target="RFC8713" format="default"/> has included the update from RFC 7776.</t>
        <t>This document updates RFC 7776 to remove the update of RFC 7437.</t>

        <section anchor="changemeta" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Changes to Metadata</name>
          <t>The following change is made to the metadata at the head of <xref target="RFC7776" format="default"/>:</t>
          <t>OLD
          </t>
            <blockquote>Updates: 2418, 7437</blockquote>
          <t>NEW
          </t>
            <blockquote>Updates: 2418</blockquote>
          <t>END</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="changeab" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Changes to the Abstract</name>
          <t>The following change is made to text in the Abstract of <xref target="RFC7776" format="default"/>:</t>
          <t>DELETE
          </t>
            <blockquote>This document updates RFC 7437 by allowing the Ombudsteam to form a recall petition without further signatories.</blockquote>
          <t>END</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="change5-1" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Changes to Section 5.1</name>
          <t>The following change is made to text in <xref target="RFC7776" section="5.1" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>:</t>
          <t>OLD
          </t>
          <blockquote>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>Many IETF management positions are appointed by the NomCom with confirmation from the IESG, IAB, or ISOC.  <xref target="RFC7437" format="default"/> describes the
                      recall procedure for such appointments.  This document updates <xref target="RFC7437" format="default"/> by allowing the Ombudsteam to form a recall petition on
                      its own and without requiring 20 signatories from the community.  Such a petition shall be treated in all ways like any other recall petition as
                      described in <xref target="RFC7437" format="default"/>: that is, the fact of the petition and its signatories (the Ombudsteam) shall be announced to the IETF
                      community, and a Recall Committee Chair shall be appointed to complete the Recall Committee process.  It is expected that the Recall Committee will
                      receive a briefing from the Ombudsteam explaining why recall is considered an appropriate remedy.</li></ul></blockquote>
          <t>NEW
          </t>
          <blockquote>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>The Ombudsteam may form a recall petition on its own without requiring signatures from the community as described in <xref target="RFC8713" format="default"/>.</li></ul></blockquote>
          <t>END</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no implications for Internet security.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7776.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="RFC8713" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8713">
          <front>
            <title>IAB, IESG, and IETF LLC Selection, Confirmation, and
                         Recall Process: Operation of the IETF Nominating and
                         Recall Committees</title>
            <author initials="M." surname="Kucherawy" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Hinden" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Livingood" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2020"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="10"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8713"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8713"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7437.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Jason Livingood"/> for suggesting the need for this document.</t>

      <t><contact fullname="Subramanian Moonesamy"/>, <contact fullname="Sean
      Turner"/>, <contact fullname="Jon Peterson"/>, <contact fullname="Roman
      Danyliw"/>, and <contact fullname="Barry Leiba"/> raised useful points
      during their reviews of this work.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
