<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
category="std" 
docName="draft-ietf-core-hop-limit-07" 
number="8768"
ipr="trust200902" 
obsoletes="" 
updates="" 
submissionType="IETF" 
consensus="true"
xml:lang="en" 
tocInclude="true" 
tocDepth="4" 
symRefs="true" 
sortRefs="true" 
version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CoAP Hop-Limit Option">Constrained Application Protocol
    (CoAP) Hop-Limit Option</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8768"/>
    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Rennes</city>
          <code>35000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy.K" initials="T." surname="Reddy.K">
      <organization abbrev="McAfee">McAfee, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560071</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jon Shallow" initials="J." surname="Shallow">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>
        <email>supjps-ietf@jpshallow.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2020"/>
    <workgroup>CORE</workgroup>
    <keyword>security</keyword>
    <keyword>mitigation</keyword>
    <keyword>service delivery</keyword>
    <keyword>connectivity</keyword>
    <keyword>anti-DDoS</keyword>
    <keyword>automation</keyword>
    <keyword>cooperation</keyword>
    <keyword>Resilience</keyword>
    <keyword>Filtering</keyword>
    <keyword>Security Center</keyword>
    <keyword>Mitigator</keyword>
    <keyword>Scrubbing</keyword>
    <keyword>dynamic service protection</keyword>
    <keyword>dynamic mitigation</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>The presence of Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP) proxies may
      lead to infinite forwarding loops, which is undesirable. To prevent and
      detect such loops, this document specifies the Hop-Limit CoAP
      option.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>More and more applications are using the Constrained Application
      Protocol (CoAP) <xref target="RFC7252" format="default"/> as a communication
      protocol between application agents. For example, <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel" format="default"/> specifies how CoAP is used
      as a signaling protocol between domains under distributed
      denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks and DDoS mitigation providers. In such
      contexts, a CoAP client can communicate directly with a server or
      indirectly via proxies.</t>
      <t>When multiple proxies are involved, infinite forwarding loops may be
      experienced (e.g., routing misconfiguration, policy conflicts). To
      prevent such loops, this document defines a new CoAP option, called
      Hop-Limit (<xref target="spec" format="default"/>). Also, the document defines a
      new CoAP Response Code (<xref target="code" format="default"/>) to report loops
      together with relevant diagnostic information to ease troubleshooting
      (<xref target="debug" format="default"/>).</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Intended Usage</name>
        <t>The Hop-Limit option was originally designed for a specific use
        case <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel" format="default"/>. However, its
        intended usage is general: </t>

        <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
          <li>New CoAP proxies <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> implement this option and have it enabled
            by default.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Note that this means that a server that receives requests both via
        proxies and directly from clients may see otherwise identical requests
        with and without the Hop-Limit option included; servers with internal
        caching will therefore also want to implement this option, since
        understanding the Hop-Limit option will improve caching
        efficiency.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="notation" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      <t>Readers should be familiar with the terms and concepts defined in
      <xref target="RFC7252" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="spec" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Hop-Limit Option</name>
      <t>The properties of the Hop-Limit option are shown in <xref target="tab-option-props" format="default"/>. The
      formatting of this table follows the one used in Table 4 of 
      <xref target="RFC7252" section="5.10" sectionFormat="parens" format="default"/>. The C, U, N, and R columns
      indicate the properties Critical, Unsafe, NoCacheKey, and Repeatable
      defined in <xref target="RFC7252" section="5.4" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>. None of these
      properties is marked for the Hop-Limit option.</t>

<table anchor="tab-option-props">
	<name>CoAP Hop-Limit Option Properties</name>
	<thead>
	<tr>
		<th>Number</th>
		<th>C</th>
		<th>U</th>
		<th>N</th>
		<th>R</th>
		<th>Name</th>
		<th>Format</th>
		<th>Length</th>
		<th>Default</th>
	</tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	<tr>
		<td>16</td>
		<td>&nbsp;</td>
		<td>&nbsp;</td>
		<td>&nbsp;</td>
		<td>&nbsp;</td>
		<td>Hop-Limit</td>
		<td>uint</td>
		<td>1</td>
		<td>16</td>
	</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>
      <t>The Hop-Limit option (<xref target="option" format="default"/>) is an elective
      option used to detect and prevent infinite loops of CoAP requests when
      proxies are involved. The option is not repeatable. Therefore, any
      request carrying multiple Hop-Limit options <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be handled following
      the procedure specified in <xref target="RFC7252" section="5.4.5" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The value of the Hop-Limit option is encoded as an unsigned integer
      (see <xref target="RFC7252" section="3.2" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>). This value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
      between 1 and 255 inclusive. CoAP requests received with a Hop-Limit
      option set to '0' or greater than '255' <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be rejected by a CoAP
      server/proxy using 4.00 (Bad Request).</t>
      <t>The Hop-Limit option is safe to forward. That is, a CoAP proxy that
      does not understand the Hop-Limit option should forward it on. The
      option is also part of the cache key. As such, a CoAP proxy that does
      not understand the Hop-Limit option must follow the recommendations in
      <xref target="RFC7252" section="5.7.1" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/> for caching. Note that
      loops that involve only such proxies will not be detected. Nevertheless,
      the presence of such proxies will not prevent infinite loop detection if
      at least one CoAP proxy that supports the Hop-Limit option is involved
      in the loop.</t>
      <t>A CoAP proxy that understands the Hop-Limit option <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
      instructed, using a configuration parameter, to insert a Hop-Limit
      option when relaying a request that does not include the Hop-Limit
      option.</t>
      <t>The initial Hop-Limit value should be configurable. If no initial
      value is explicitly provided, the default initial Hop-Limit value of 16
      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used. This value is chosen so that in the majority of cases, it
      is sufficiently large to guarantee that a CoAP request would not be
      dropped in networks when there were no loops, but not so large as to
      consume CoAP proxy resources when a loop does occur. The value is still
      configurable to accommodate unusual topologies. Lower values should be
      used with caution and only in networks where topologies are known by the
      CoAP client (or proxy) inserting the Hop-Limit option.</t>
      <t>Because forwarding errors may occur if inadequate Hop-Limit values
      are used, proxies at the boundaries of an administrative domain <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be
      instructed to remove or rewrite the value of Hop-Limit carried in
      received requests (i.e., ignore the value of Hop-Limit received in a
      request). This modification should be done with caution in case
      proxy-forwarded traffic repeatedly crosses the administrative domain
      boundary in a loop, rendering ineffective the efficacy of loop detection
      through the Hop-Limit option.</t>

      <t>Otherwise, a CoAP proxy that understands the Hop-Limit option <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
      decrement the value of the option by 1 prior to forwarding it. A CoAP
      proxy that understands the Hop-Limit option <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> use a stored 5.08 
      (Hop Limit Reached) error response unless the value of the Hop-Limit
      option in the presented request is smaller than or equal to the value of
      the Hop-Limit option in the request used to obtain the stored response.
      Otherwise, the CoAP proxy follows the behavior in 
      <xref target="RFC7252" section="5.6" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>.</t>
      <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
        <li>Note: If a request with a given value of Hop-Limit failed to
          reach a server because the hop limit is exhausted, then the same
          failure will be observed if a smaller value of the Hop-Limit option
          is used instead.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>CoAP requests <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be forwarded if the Hop-Limit option is set to
      '0' after decrement. Requests that cannot be forwarded because of
      exhausted Hop-Limit <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be logged with a 5.08 (Hop Limit Reached)
      error response sent back to the CoAP peer. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that CoAP
      implementations support means to alert administrators about loop errors
      so that appropriate actions are undertaken.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="debug" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Debugging and Troubleshooting</name>
      <t>To ease debugging and troubleshooting, the CoAP proxy that detects a
      loop includes an identifier for itself in the diagnostic payload under
      the conditions detailed in <xref target="RFC7252" section="5.5.2" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>. 
      That identifier <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> include any space
      character (ASCII value 32). The identifier inserted by a CoAP proxy can
      be, for example, a proxy name (e.g., p11.example.net), proxy alias
      (e.g., myproxyalias), or IP address (e.g., 2001:db8::1).</t>
      <t>Each intermediate proxy involved in relaying a 5.08 (Hop Limit
      Reached) error message prepends its own identifier in the diagnostic
      payload with a space character used as separator. Only one identifier
      per proxy should appear in the diagnostic payload. 
   This approach allows the limiting of the size of the 5.08 (Hop 
   Limit Reached) error message, eases the correlation with hops 
   count, and detects whether a proxy was involved in the forwarding 
   of the 5.08 (Hop Limit Reached) error message.  Note that
      an intermediate proxy prepends its identifier only if there is enough
      space as determined by the Path MTU 
      (<xref target="RFC7252" section="4.6" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>). 
      If not, an intermediate proxy forwards the
      5.08 (Hop Limit Reached) error message to the next hop without updating
      the diagnostic payload.</t>
      <t>An intermediate proxy <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> forward a 5.08 (Hop Limit Reached)
      error message if it detects that its identifier is included in the
      diagnostic payload. Such messages <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be logged and appropriate
      alerts sent to the administrators.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>HTTP Mapping Considerations</name>
      <t>This section focuses on the HTTP mappings specific to the CoAP
      extension specified in this document. As a reminder, the basic normative
      requirements on HTTP/CoAP mappings are defined in 
      <xref target="RFC7252" section="10" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>. The implementation guidelines for HTTP/CoAP
      mappings are elaborated in <xref target="RFC8075" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>By default, the HTTP-to-CoAP Proxy inserts a Hop-Limit option
      following the guidelines in <xref target="spec" format="default"/>. The
      HTTP-to-CoAP Proxy may be instructed by policy to insert a Hop-Limit
      option only if a Via (<xref target="RFC7230" section="5.7.1" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>)
      or CDN-Loop header field <xref target="RFC8586" format="default"/> is present in
      the HTTP request.</t>
      <t>The HTTP-to-CoAP Proxy uses 508 (Loop Detected) as the HTTP response
      status code to map 5.08 (Hop Limit Reached). Furthermore, it maps the
      diagnostic payload of 5.08 (Hop Limit Reached) as per 
      <xref target="RFC8075" section="6.6" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>By default, the CoAP-to-HTTP Proxy inserts a Via header field in the
      HTTP request if the CoAP request includes a Hop-Limit option. The
      CoAP-to-HTTP Proxy may be instructed by policy to insert a CDN-Loop
      header field instead of the Via header field.</t>
      <t>The CoAP-to-HTTP Proxy maps the 508 (Loop Detected) HTTP response
      status code to 5.08 (Hop Limit Reached). Moreover, the CoAP-to-HTTP
      Proxy inserts its information following the guidelines in <xref target="debug" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>When both HTTP-to-CoAP and CoAP-to-HTTP proxies are involved, the
      loop detection may break if the proxy-forwarded traffic repeatedly
      crosses the HTTP-to-CoAP and CoAP-to-HTTP proxies. Nevertheless, if the
      loop is within the CoAP or HTTP legs, the loop detection is still
      functional.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="code" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>CoAP Response Code</name>
        <t>IANA has registered the following entry in the "CoAP Response
        Codes" subregistry available at
        <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/core-parameters" brackets="angle"/>:</t>
<table anchor="tab-resp-codes">
	<name>CoAP Response Codes</name>
	<thead>
	<tr>
		<th>Code</th>
		<th>Description</th>
		<th>Reference</th>
	</tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	<tr>
		<td>5.08</td>
		<td>Hop Limit Reached</td>
		<td>RFC 8768</td>
	</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>CoAP Option Number</name>
        <t>IANA has registered the following entry in the "CoAP Option
        Numbers" subregistry available at
        <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/core-parameters" brackets="angle"/>:</t>
<table anchor="tab-option-number">
        <name>CoAP Option Number</name>
        <thead>
        <tr>
                <th>Number</th>
                <th>Name</th>
                <th>Reference</th>
        </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
        <tr>
                <td>16</td>
                <td>Hop-Limit</td>
                <td>RFC 8768</td>
        </tr>
        </tbody>
</table>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Security considerations related to CoAP proxying are discussed in
      <xref target="RFC7252" section="11.2" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>A CoAP endpoint can probe the topology of a network into which it is
      making requests by tweaking the value of the Hop-Limit option. Such
      probing is likely to fail if proxies at the boundaries of that network
      rewrite the value of Hop-Limit carried in received requests (see <xref target="spec" format="default"/>).</t>
      <t>The diagnostic payload of a 5.08 (Hop Limit Reached) error message
      may leak sensitive information revealing the topology of an
      administrative domain. To prevent that, a CoAP proxy that is located at
      the boundary of an administrative domain <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be instructed to strip the
      diagnostic payload or part of it before forwarding on the 5.08 (Hop
      Limit Reached) response.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
<displayreference target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel" to="DOTS-SIG-CHANNEL"/>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7252.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8075.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel">
  <front>
    <title>Distributed Denial-of-Service Open Threat Signaling (DOTS) Signal Channel Specification</title>
    <author initials="T" surname="Reddy" fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="M" surname="Boucadair" fullname="Mohamed Boucadair">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="P" surname="Patil" fullname="Prashanth Patil">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="A" surname="Mortensen" fullname="Andrew Mortensen">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="N" surname="Teague" fullname="Nik Teague">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date month="January" day="6" year="2020"/>
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-dots-signal-channel-41"/>
    <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-dots-signal-channel-41.txt"/>
</reference>

        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8586.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="ack" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This specification was part of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dots-signal-channel" format="default"/>. 
      Many thanks to those who reviewed DOTS specifications.</t>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Klaus Hartke"/>, <contact fullname="Carsten Bormann"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Peter van der Stok"/>, <contact fullname="Jim Schaad"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Jaime Jiménez"/>, <contact fullname="Roni Even"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Scott Bradner"/>, <contact fullname="Thomas Fossati"/>,
      <contact fullname="Radia Perlman"/>, <contact fullname="Éric Vyncke"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Suresh Krishnan"/>, <contact fullname="Roman Danyliw"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Barry Leiba"/>, <contact fullname="Christer Holmberg"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/>, and <contact fullname="Adam Roach"/> for their
      review and comments.</t>
      <t><contact fullname="Carsten Bormann"/> provided the "Intended Usage" text.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
