<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc number="8701" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info"
     consensus="true" docName="draft-ietf-tls-grease-04" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title>Applying Generate Random Extensions And Sustain Extensibility (GREASE) to TLS Extensibility</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8701"/>
    <author fullname="David Benjamin" initials="D." surname="Benjamin">
      <organization>Google LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <email>davidben@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2020" month="January"/>
    <area>General</area>

<keyword>TLS</keyword>
<keyword>GREASE</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes GREASE (Generate Random Extensions And Sustain
     Extensibility), a mechanism to prevent extensibility failures in the TLS
     ecosystem. It reserves a set of TLS protocol values that may be advertised
     to ensure peers correctly handle unknown values.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The TLS protocol <xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/> includes several points of
extensibility, including the list of cipher suites and several lists of extensions.
The values transmitted in these lists identify implementation capabilities. TLS follows
a model where one side, usually the client, advertises capabilities, and the
peer, usually the server, selects them. The responding side must ignore unknown
values so that new capabilities may be introduced to the ecosystem while
maintaining interoperability.</t>
      <t>However, bugs may cause an implementation to reject unknown
      values. It will interoperate with existing peers, so the mistake may
      spread through the ecosystem unnoticed. Later, when new values are
      defined, updated peers will discover that the metaphorical joint in the
      protocol has rusted shut and the new values cannot be deployed without
      interoperability failures.</t>
      <t>To avoid this problem, this document reserves some currently unused values for
TLS implementations to advertise at random. Correctly implemented peers will ignore
these values and interoperate. Peers that do not tolerate unknown values will
fail to interoperate, revealing the mistake before it is
widespread.</t>
      <t>In keeping with the rusted joint metaphor, this technique is called "GREASE"
(Generate Random Extensions And Sustain Extensibility).</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>


        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>


      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>GREASE Values</name>
      <t>This document reserves a number of TLS protocol values, referred to as
     GREASE values. These values were allocated sparsely to discourage server
     implementations from conditioning on them. For convenience, they were also
     chosen so all types share a number scheme with a consistent pattern while
     avoiding collisions with any existing applicable registries in TLS.</t>

      <t>The following values are reserved as GREASE values for cipher suites
     and Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) <xref target="RFC7301" format="default"/> identifiers:</t>

<ul empty="true">
<li>{0x0A,0x0A}
</li>
<li>{0x1A,0x1A}
</li>
<li>{0x2A,0x2A}
</li>
<li>{0x3A,0x3A}
</li>
<li>{0x4A,0x4A}
</li>
<li>{0x5A,0x5A}
</li>
<li>{0x6A,0x6A}
</li>
<li>{0x7A,0x7A}
</li>
<li>{0x8A,0x8A}
</li>
<li>{0x9A,0x9A}
</li>
<li>{0xAA,0xAA}
</li>
<li>{0xBA,0xBA}
</li>
<li>{0xCA,0xCA}
</li>
<li>{0xDA,0xDA}
</li>
<li>{0xEA,0xEA}
</li>
<li>{0xFA,0xFA}
</li>
</ul>



      <t>The following values are reserved as GREASE values for extensions,
        named groups, signature algorithms, and versions:</t>


<ul empty="true">
<li>0x0A0A
</li>
<li>0x1A1A
</li>
<li>0x2A2A
</li>
<li>0x3A3A
</li>
<li>0x4A4A
</li>
<li>0x5A5A
</li>
<li>0x6A6A
</li>
<li>0x7A7A
</li>
<li>0x8A8A
</li>
<li>0x9A9A
</li>
<li>0xAAAA 
</li>
<li>0xBABA
</li>
<li>0xCACA
</li>
<li>0xDADA
</li>
<li>0xEAEA
</li>
<li>0xFAFA
</li>
</ul>

      <t>The values allocated above are thus no longer available for use as TLS or
        DTLS <xref target="RFC6347" format="default"/> version numbers.</t>
      <t>The following values are reserved as GREASE values for PskKeyExchangeModes:</t>

<ul empty="true">
<li>0x0B
</li>
<li>0x2A
</li>
<li>0x49
</li>
<li>0x68
</li>
<li>0x87
</li>
<li>0xA6
</li>
<li>0xC5
</li>
<li>0xE4
</li>
</ul>


    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Client-Initiated Extension Points</name>
      <t>Most extension points in TLS are offered by the client and selected by
the server. This section details client and server behavior around
GREASE values for these.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Client Behavior</name>
        <t>When sending a ClientHello, a client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> behave as follows:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>A client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE cipher suite values and advertise them in the "cipher_suites" field.</li>
          <li>A client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE extension values and advertise them as extensions with varying length and contents.</li>
          <li>A client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE named group values and advertise them in the "supported_groups" extension, if sent. It <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also send KeyShareEntry values for a subset of those selected in the "key_share" extension. For each of these, the "key_exchange" field <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be any value.</li>
          <li>A client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE signature algorithm values and advertise them in the "signature_algorithms" or "signature_algorithms_cert" extensions, if sent.</li>
          <li>A client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE version values and advertise them in the "supported_versions" extension, if sent.</li>
          <li>A client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE PskKeyExchangeMode values and advertise them in the "psk_key_exchange_modes" extension, if sent.</li>
          <li>A client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE ALPN identifiers and advertise them in the "application_layer_protocol_negotiation" extension, if sent.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>Clients <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject GREASE values when negotiated by
        the server.  In particular, the client <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> fail the
        connection if a GREASE value appears in any of the following:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The "version" value in a ServerHello or HelloRetryRequest</li>
          <li>The "cipher_suite" value in a ServerHello</li>
          <li>Any ServerHello extension</li>
          <li>Any HelloRetryRequest, EncryptedExtensions, or Certificate extension in TLS 1.3</li>
          <li>The "namedcurve" value in a ServerKeyExchange for an Ephemeral
	  Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman (ECDHE) cipher in TLS 1.2 <xref
	  target="RFC5246" format="default"/> or earlier</li>
          <li>The signature algorithm in a ServerKeyExchange signature in TLS 1.2 or earlier</li>
          <li>The signature algorithm in a server CertificateVerify signature in TLS 1.3</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Note that this can be implemented without special processing on the client. The client
     is already required to reject unknown server-selected values, so it
     may leave GREASE values as unknown and reuse the existing logic.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Server Behavior</name>
        <t>
When processing a ClientHello, servers <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> treat GREASE values differently from any unknown value.
Servers <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> negotiate any GREASE value when offered in a ClientHello.
Servers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> correctly ignore unknown values in a ClientHello and attempt to negotiate with one of the remaining parameters.
(There may not be any known parameters remaining, in which case parameter negotiation will fail.)
        </t>
        <t>Note that these requirements are restatements or corollaries of
     existing server requirements in TLS.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Server-Initiated Extension Points</name>
      <t>Some extension points are offered by the server and selected by the
client. This section details client and server behavior around GREASE
values for these.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Server Behavior</name>
        <t>When sending a CertificateRequest in TLS 1.3, a server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> behave as follows:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>A server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE extension values and advertise them as extensions with varying length and contents.</li>
          <li>A server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE signature algorithm values and advertise them in the "signature_algorithms" or "signature_algorithms_cert" extensions, if present.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>When sending a NewSessionTicket message in TLS 1.3, a server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> select one or more GREASE extension values and advertise them as extensions with varying length and contents.</t>
        <t>Servers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject GREASE values when negotiated by the client.
In particular, the server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> fail the connection if a GREASE
value appears in any of the following:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Any Certificate extension in TLS 1.3</li>
          <li>The signature algorithm in a client CertificateVerify signature</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Note that this can be implemented without special processing on the server. The server
     is already required to reject unknown client-selected values, so it
     may leave GREASE values as unknown and reuse the existing logic.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Client Behavior</name>
        <t>
When processing a CertificateRequest or NewSessionTicket, clients <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> treat GREASE values differently from any unknown value.
Clients <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> negotiate any GREASE value when offered by the server.
Clients <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> correctly ignore unknown values offered by the server and attempt to negotiate with one of the remaining parameters.
(There may not be any known parameters remaining, in which case parameter negotiation will fail.)
        </t>
        <t>Note that these requirements are restatements or corollaries of
     existing client requirements in TLS.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Sending GREASE Values</name>
      <t>Implementations advertising GREASE values <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> select them at random.
This is intended to encourage implementations to ignore all unknown values
rather than any individual value. Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> honor protocol
specifications when sending GREASE values. For instance, <xref target="RFC8446"
sectionFormat="of" section="4.2"/> forbids duplicate extension types within a single
extension block. Implementations sending multiple GREASE extensions in a single
block must therefore ensure the same value is not selected twice.</t>
      <t>Implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> balance diversity in GREASE advertisements with determinism.
  For example, a client that randomly varies GREASE value positions for each
  connection may only fail against a broken server with some probability. This
  risks the failure being masked by automatic retries. A client that positions
  GREASE values deterministically over a period of time (such as a single
  software release) stresses fewer cases but is more likely to detect bugs from
  those cases.</t>
    </section>
 

   <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document updates the &quot;TLS Cipher Suites&quot; registry, available at
     <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-parameters" brackets="angle"/>:</t>
      <table align="center">
        <name>Additions to the TLS Cipher Suites Registry</name>
        <thead >
          <tr >
            <th align="center">Value</th>
            <th align="center">Description</th>
            <th align="center">DTLS-OK</th>
            <th align="center">Recommended</th>
            <th align="center">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x0A,0x0A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x1A,0x1A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x2A,0x2A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x3A,0x3A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x4A,0x4A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x5A,0x5A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x6A,0x6A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x7A,0x7A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x8A,0x8A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0x9A,0x9A}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0xAA,0xAA}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0xBA,0xBA}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0xCA,0xCA}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0xDA,0xDA}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0xEA,0xEA}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">{0xFA,0xFA}</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
     
      <t>This document updates the &quot;TLS Supported Groups&quot; registry, available at
<eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-parameters" brackets="angle"/>:</t>
      <table align="center">
        <name>Additions to the TLS Supported Groups Registry</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="center">Value</th>
            <th align="center">Description</th>
            <th align="center">DTLS-OK</th>
            <th align="center">Recommended</th>
            <th align="center">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">2570</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">6682</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">10794</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">14906</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">19018</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">23130</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">27242</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">31354</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">35466</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">39578</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">43690</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">47802</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">51914</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">56026</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">60138</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">64250</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">Y</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>

      <t>This document updates the &quot;TLS ExtensionType Values&quot; registry, available at
<eref
    target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-extensiontype-values"
    brackets="angle"/>:</t>
      <table align="center">
        <name>Additions to the TLS ExtensionType Values Registry</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="center">Value</th>
            <th align="center">Extension Name</th>
            <th align="center">TLS 1.3</th>
            <th align="center">Recommended</th>
            <th align="center">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">2570</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">6682</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">10794</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">14906</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">19018</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">23130</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">27242</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">31354</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">35466</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">39578</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">43690</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">47802</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">51914</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">56026</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">60138</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">64250</td>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">CH, CR, NST</td>
            <td align="center">N</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>This document updates the &quot;TLS Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation
       (ALPN) Protocol IDs&quot; registry, available at
       <eref
	   target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-extensiontype-values"
	   brackets="angle"/>:</t>
      <table align="center">
        <name>Additions to the TLS Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation
	(ALPN) Protocol IDs Registry</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="center">Protocol</th>
            <th align="center">Identification Sequence</th>
            <th align="center">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x0A 0x0A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x1A 0x1A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x2A 0x2A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x3A 0x3A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x4A 0x4A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x5A 0x5A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x6A 0x6A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x7A 0x7A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x8A 0x8A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0x9A 0x9A</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0xAA 0xAA</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0xBA 0xBA</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0xCA 0xCA</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0xDA 0xDA</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0xEA 0xEA</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Reserved</td>
            <td align="center">0xFA 0xFA</td>
            <td align="center">[RFC8701]</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>GREASE values cannot be negotiated, so they do not directly impact the
     security of TLS connections.</t>
      <t>Historically, when interoperability problems arise in deploying new TLS
     features, implementations have used a fallback retry on error with the
     feature disabled. This allows an active attacker to silently disable the
     new feature. By preventing a class of such interoperability problems,
     GREASE reduces the need for this kind of fallback. Implementations <bcp14>SHOULD
     NOT</bcp14> retry with GREASE disabled on connection failure. While allowing an
     attacker to disable GREASE is unlikely to have immediate security
     consequences, such a fallback would prevent GREASE from defending against
     extensibility failures.</t>
      <t>If an implementation does not select GREASE values at random, it is 
     possible it will allow for fingerprinting of the implementation or 
     perhaps even of individual users. This can result in a negative impact to
     a user's privacy.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6347.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7301.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>
The author would like to thank <contact fullname="Adam Langley"/>, <contact
fullname="Nick Harper"/>, and <contact fullname="Steven Valdez"/> for their
feedback and suggestions. In addition, the rusted joint metaphor is originally
due to <contact fullname="Adam Langley"/>.
</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
