<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.2.9 -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-thaler-iftype-reg-07" number="8892" updates="2863" obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.44.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ifType Guidelines">Guidelines and Registration Procedures for Interface Types and Tunnel Types</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8892"/>
    <author initials="D." surname="Thaler" fullname="Dave Thaler">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dthaler@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Romascanu" fullname="Dan Romascanu">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dromasca@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2020" />
    <area>Internet</area>

<keyword>ifType</keyword>
<keyword>tunnelType</keyword>
<keyword>Transmission Number</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides guidelines and procedures for those who are defining, registering, 
or evaluating definitions of new interface types ("ifType" values) and tunnel types.
The original definition of the IANA interface type registry predated
the use of IANA Considerations sections and YANG modules, so some confusion arose
over time. Tunnel types were added later, with the same requirements and allocation policy as
interface types. This document updates RFC 2863 and provides updated guidance for
these registries.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The IANA IfType-MIB, which contains the list of interface type (ifType) values,
was originally defined in <xref target="RFC1573" format="default"/> as a separate MIB
module together with the Interfaces Group MIB (IF-MIB) module.  The IF-MIB module was
subsequently updated and is currently specified in <xref target="RFC2863" format="default"/>, but the latest IF-MIB
RFC no longer contains the IANA IfType-MIB. Instead, the IANA IfType-MIB is
maintained by IANA as a separate module.  Similarly, <xref target="RFC7224" format="default"/> created an initial
IANA Interface Type YANG Module, and the current version is maintained by IANA.</t>
      <t>The current IANA IfType registry is at <xref target="ifType-registry" format="default"/>, with the same values also
appearing in both <xref target="yang-if-type" format="default"/> and the
      IANAifType textual convention at <xref target="IANAifType-MIB"
      format="default"/>.</t>

      <t>Although the ifType registry was originally defined in a MIB module,
the assignment and use of interface type values are not tied to MIB modules
or any other management mechanism.  An interface type value can be used
as the value of a data model object (MIB object, YANG object, etc.),
as part of a unique identifier of a data model for a given
interface type (e.g., in an OID), or simply as a value exposed by local
APIs or UIs on a device.</t>

      <t>The TUNNEL-MIB was defined in <xref target="RFC2667" format="default"/> (now obsoleted by <xref target="RFC4087" format="default"/>),
which created a tunnelType registry (<xref target="tunnelType-registry" format="default"/> and the IANAtunnelType textual
convention at <xref target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/>), and it
defined the assignment policy for tunnelType values to always be identical to the policy for assigning
      ifType values.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>",
and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as described
in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/> when, and only when, they appear
in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="problems" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Problems</name>
      <t>This document addresses the following issues:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>As noted in <xref target="intro" format="default"/>, the original guidance was written with wording
specific to MIB modules; accordingly, some confusion has resulted
when using YANG modules.  This document clarifies that ifTypes and tunnelTypes are
independent from the type of, or even existence of, a data model.</li>
        <li>The use of and requirements around sub-layers and sub-types
were not well understood, but good examples of both now exist.
This is discussed in <xref target="sublayers" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>Since the "Interface Types (ifType)" and "Tunnel Types
	(tunnelType)" registries were originally defined, and are
still retrievable, in the format of MIB modules (in addition to other formats),
confusion arose when adding YANG modules as another format as to whether
each is a separate registry.  This is discussed in <xref target="formats" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>The registries are retrievable in the format of MIB and YANG modules, but
there was previously no process guidance written to check that those formats were
syntactically correct as updates were made, which led to the registry having syntax errors
that broke tools.  <xref target="procedures" format="default"/> adds a validation step to the
documented assignment procedure.</li>
        <li>Various documents and registries previously said to submit requests via email,
but a web form exists for submitting requests, which caused
some confusion around which was to be used.  This is addressed
in <xref target="procedures" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>Transmission values <xref target="transmission-registry" format="default"/> have generally been allocated as part
of ifType allocation, but no guidance existed as to whether a requester
must ask for it or not, and the request form had no such required field.
As a result, IANA has asked the designated expert to decide for each
allocation, but no relevant guidance for the designated expert has been
documented. This is remedied in <xref target="transmission-discussion" format="default"/>.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sublayers" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Interface Sub-layers and Sub-types</name>

      <t>When multiple sub-layers exist below the network layer,
each sub-layer can be represented by its own
row in the ifTable with its own ifType, with the ifStackTable being used to identify the
upward and downward multiplexing relationships between rows. <xref
target="RFC2863" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1.1"/> provides more
discussion, and <xref target="RFC2863" sectionFormat="bare" section="3.1.2"/> provides guidance for defining interface
sub-layers. More recent experience shows that those guidelines were
phrased in a way that is now too restrictive, since at the time
<xref target="RFC2863" format="default"/> was written, MIB modules were the dominant data model.</t>
      <t>This document clarifies that the same guidance also applies to YANG
      modules.</t>

      <t>Some ifTypes may define sub-types.  For example, the tunnel(131)
      ifType defines sub-types known as “tunnelTypes”, where each tunnelType can have its own MIB and/or YANG
module with protocol-specific information, but there is enough in common
that some information is exposed in a generic IP Tunnel MIB corresponding
to the tunnel(131) ifType.</t>

      <t>For requests that involve multiple sub-layers below the network layer,
requests <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include (or reference) a discussion of the multiplexing relationships
between sub-layers, ideally with a diagram. Various well-written examples exist of
such definitions, including <xref target="RFC3637" sectionFormat="of" section="3.4.1"/>, <xref target="RFC4087" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1.1"/>,
and <xref target="RFC5066" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1.1"/>.</t>

      <t>Definers of sub-layers and sub-types should consider which model is more
appropriate for their needs. A sub-layer is generally used whenever either a
dynamic relationship exists (i.e., when the set of instances above or below a
given instance can change over time) or a multiplexing relationship exists
with another sub-layer. A sub-type can be used when neither of these is true
but where one interface type is conceptually a subclass of another interface type, as far
as a management data model is concerned.</t>

      <t>In general, the intent of an interface type or sub-type is that its definition should
be sufficient to identify an interoperable protocol.   In some cases, however,
a protocol might be defined in a way that is not sufficient to provide
interoperability with other compliant implementations of that protocol.
In such a case, an ifType definition should discuss whether specific
instantiations (or profiles) of behavior should use a sub-layer model
(e.g., each vendor might layer the protocol over its own sub-layer
that provides the missing details) or a sub-type model (i.e., each
vendor might subclass the protocol without any layering relationship).
If a sub-type model is more appropriate, then the data model for the
protocol might include a sub-type identifier so that management software
can discover objects specific to the sub-type.  In either case, such
discussion is important to guide definers of a data model for the more
specific information (i.e., a lower sub-layer or a sub-type), as well
as the designated expert, who must review requests for any such
ifTypes or sub-types.</t>
      <section anchor="alternate-values" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Alternate Values</name>
        <t>Another design decision is whether to reuse an existing ifType or tunnelType
value, possibly using a sub-type or sub-layer model for refinements, or
to use a different value for a new mechanism.</t>
        <t>If there is already an entry that could easily satisfy the modeling and functional
requirements for the requested entry, it should be reused so that
applications and tools that use the existing value can be used without changes.
If, however, the modeling and functional requirements are significantly different
enough such that having existing applications and tools use the existing value
would be seen as a problem, a new value should be used.</t>
        <t>For example, originally different ifType values were used for different
flavors of Ethernet (ethernetCsmacd(6), iso88023Csmacd(7), fastEther(62), etc.),
typically because they were registered by different vendors. Using different values
was, however, seen as problematic because all were functionally similar, so <xref target="RFC3635" format="default"/> then deprecated all but
	ethernetCsmacd(6).</t>

        <t>As another example, a udp(8) tunnelType value was defined in <xref target="RFC2667" format="default"/>
with the description "The value UDP indicates that the payload packet is 
encapsulated within a normal UDP packet (e.g., RFC 1234)." The Teredo tunnel
protocol <xref target="RFC4380" format="default"/> was later defined and encapsulates packets over UDP, but the
protocol model is quite different between <xref target="RFC1234" format="default"/> and Teredo.  For
example, <xref target="RFC1234" format="default"/> supports encapsulation of multicast/broadcast traffic,
whereas Teredo does not.  As such, it would be more confusing to applications
and tools to represent them using the same tunnel type, and so <xref target="RFC4087" format="default"/>
defined a new value for Teredo.</t>

        <t>In summary, definers of new interface or tunnel mechanisms should use a new ifType or
tunnelType value rather than reuse an existing value when key aspects such
as the header format or the link model (point-to-point, non-broadcast multi-access,
broadcast-capable multi-access, unidirectional broadcast, etc.) are significantly 
different from existing values, but they should reuse the same value when the differences
can be expressed in terms of differing values of existing objects other than 
ifType/tunnelType in the standard YANG or MIB module.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="formats" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Available Formats</name>
      <t>Many registries are available in multiple formats.  For example,
XML, HTML, CSV, and plain text are common formats in which many registries
are available.  This document clarifies that the <xref target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/>,
<xref target="yang-if-type" format="default"/>, and <xref target="yang-tunnel-type" format="default"/> MIB and YANG modules
are merely additional formats in which the "Interface Types (ifType)" and "Tunnel Types (tunnelType)"
registries are available.  The MIB and YANG modules are not separate registries, and the same
values are always present in all formats of the same registry.</t>
      <t>The confusion stemmed in part from the fact that the IANA "Protocol Registries"
<xref target="protocol-registries" format="default"/> listed the YANG and MIB module formats separately,
as if they were separate registries. However, the entries for the
yang-if-type and iana-tunnel-type YANG modules said "See ifType definitions registry"
and "See tunnelType registry (mib-2.interface.ifTable.ifEntry.ifType.tunnelType)"
respectively, although the entry for the IANAifType-MIB had no such note.
<xref target="module-formats" format="default"/> addresses this.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="registration" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Registration</name>
      <t>The IANA policy (using terms defined in <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>) for registration is
Expert Review for both interface types and tunnel types.  The role of the 
designated expert in the procedure is to
raise possible concerns about wider implications of proposals for use and
deployment of interface types.  While it is recommended that the responsible
Area Director and the IESG take into consideration the designated
expert opinions, nothing in the procedure empowers the
designated expert to override properly arrived-at IETF or working group
consensus.</t>
      <section anchor="procedures" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Procedures</name>
        <t>Someone wishing to register a new ifType or tunnelType value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>Check the IANA registry to see whether there is already an entry that could
easily satisfy the modeling and functional requirements for the requested entry.
If there is already such an entry, use it or update the existing specification.
Text in an Internet-Draft or part of some permanently
available, stable specification may be written to clarify the usage of an
existing entry or entries for the desired purpose.</li>
          <li>Check the IANA registry to see whether there is already some other entry with
the desired name.  If there is already an unrelated entry under the desired name, choose
a different name.</li>

          <li>Prepare a registration request using the template specified in <xref target="template" format="default"/>.
The registration request can be contained in an Internet-Draft, submitted
alone, or submitted as part of some permanently available, stable specification. The registration request can also be submitted in some
other form (as part of another document or as a stand-alone document),
but the registration request will be treated as an "IETF Contribution"
under the guidelines of <xref target="RFC5378" format="default"/>.</li>

          <li>Submit the registration request (or pointer to a document containing it)
to IANA at iana@iana.org or (if requesting an ifType) via the web form
at <eref brackets="angle" target="https://www.iana.org/form/iftype"/>.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>Upon receipt of a registration request, the following steps <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be followed:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>IANA checks the submission for completeness; if required information is
missing or any citations are not correct, IANA will reject the registration
request.  A registrant can resubmit a corrected request if desired.</li>
          <li>IANA requests Expert Review of the registration request against the
corresponding guidelines from this document.</li>
          <li>The designated expert will evaluate the request against the criteria.</li>
          <li>Once the designated expert approves a registration, IANA updates <xref target="ifType-registry" format="default"/>,
<xref target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/>, and <xref target="yang-if-type" format="default"/> to show the registration for an interface type,
or <xref target="tunnelType-registry" format="default"/>, <xref target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/>, and <xref target="yang-tunnel-type" format="default"/> to show the registration
for a tunnel type.
When adding values, IANA should verify that the updated
MIB module and YANG module formats are syntactically correct before publishing the update.  There are
various existing tools or websites that can be used to do this verification.</li>
          <li>If instead the designated expert
does not approve registration (e.g., for any of the reasons in
<xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="comma" section="5"/>), a registrant can resubmit a corrected request
if desired, or the IESG can override the designated expert and approve
it per the process in <xref target="RFC8126" sectionFormat="of" section="3.3"/>.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section anchor="transmission-discussion" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Media-Specific OID-Subtree Assignments</name>
        <t><xref target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/> notes:</t>
<blockquote>The relationship between the assignment of ifType
  values and of OIDs to particular media-specific MIBs
  is solely the purview of IANA and is subject to change
  without notice.  Quite often, a media-specific MIB's
  OID-subtree assignment within MIB-II's 'transmission'
  subtree will be the same as its ifType value.
  However, in some circumstances this will not be the
  case, and implementors must not pre-assume any
  specific relationship between ifType values and
  transmission subtree OIDs.</blockquote>

        <t>The advice above remains unchanged, but this document changes the allocation procedure
to streamline the process, so that an ifType value and a transmission number value
with the same value will be assigned at the same time.</t>
<t>Rationale:</t>
<ol type="(%d)">        
<li> This saves future effort if a
transmission number is later deemed necessary, since no IANA request is
needed that would then require another Expert Review.</li> 
<li>The transmission numbering space is not scarce, so there seems to be little need to reserve the number for a different purpose than what the ifType
is for.</li>
<li>The designated expert need not review whether a transmission
number value should be registered when processing each ifType request, thus
reducing the possibility of delaying assignment of ifType values.</li>
<li>There is no case on record where allocating the same value could have
caused any problems.</li>
</ol>
      </section>
      <section anchor="template" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Registration Template</name>
        <section anchor="iftype-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>ifType</name>
          <t>The following template describes the fields that <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supplied in a registration request
suitable for adding to the "Interface Types (ifType)" registry:</t>
          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Label for IANA ifType requested:</dt>
            <dd>
  As explained in <xref target="RFC2578" sectionFormat="of" section="7.1.1"/>, a label for a named-number enumeration
must consist of one or more letters or digits, up to a maximum of 64 characters, and 
the initial character must be a lowercase letter. (However, labels longer than 32 
characters are not recommended.) Note that hyphens are not allowed.</dd>
            <dt>Name of IANA ifType requested:</dt>
            <dd>
  A short description (e.g., a protocol name) suitable to appear in a comment in the registry.</dd>
            <dt>Description of the proposed use of the IANA ifType:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
  Requesters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include answers, either directly or via a link to a document
with the answers, to the following questions in the explanation
of the proposed use of the IANA IfType:

              </t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>How would IP run over your ifType?</li>
                <li>Would there be another interface sub-layer between your
		ifType and IP?</li>
                <li>Would your ifType be vendor specific / proprietary? (If so, the label
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> start with a string that shows that. For example, if your company's
name or acronym is xxx, then the ifType label would be something like
xxxSomeIfTypeLabel.)</li>
                <li>Would your ifType require or allow vendor-specific extensions?  If so,
would the vendor use their own ifType in a sub-layer below the requested ifType,
a sub-type of the ifType, or some other mechanism?</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>

            <dt>Reference, Internet-Draft, or Specification:</dt>
            <dd>
  A link to a document is required.</dd>
            <dt>Additional information or comments:</dt>

            <dd>
  Optional; any additional comments for IANA or the designated expert.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="tunneltype-template" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>tunnelType</name>
          <t>Prior to this document, no form existed for tunnelType (and new tunnelType requests did not
need to use the ifType form that did exist). This document therefore specifies a tunnelType
form.</t>
          <t>The following template describes the fields that <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supplied in a 
registration request suitable for adding to the "Tunnel Types (tunnelType)" registry:</t>
          <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Label for IANA tunnelType requested:</dt>
            <dd>
  As explained in <xref target="RFC2578" sectionFormat="of" section="7.1.1"/>, a label for a named-number enumeration
must consist of one or more letters or digits, up to a maximum of 64 characters, and
the initial character must be a lowercase letter. (However, labels longer than 32
characters are not recommended.) Note that hyphens are not allowed.</dd>
            <dt>Name of IANA tunnelType requested:</dt>
            <dd>
  A short description (e.g., a protocol name) suitable to appear in a comment in the registry.</dd>
            <dt>Description of the proposed use of the IANA tunnelType:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
  Requesters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include answers, either directly or via a link to a document
with the answers, to the following questions in the explanation
of the proposed use of the IANA tunnelType:

              </t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>How would IP run over your tunnelType?</li>
                <li>Would there be another interface sub-layer between your tunnelType and IP?</li>
                <li>Would your tunnelType be vendor-specific or proprietary? (If so, the label
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> start with a string that shows that. For example, if your company's
name or acronym is xxx, then the tunnelType label would be something like
xxxSomeTunnelTypeLabel.)</li>
                <li>Would your tunnelType require or allow vendor-specific extensions?  If so,
would the vendor use their own tunnelType in a sub-layer below the requested tunnelType,
or some sort of sub-type of the tunnelType, or some other mechanism?</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
            <dt>Reference, Internet-Draft, or Specification:</dt>
            <dd>
  A link to a document is required.</dd>
            <dt>Additional information or comments:</dt>
            <dd>
  Optionally any additional comments for IANA or the designated expert.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This entire document is about IANA considerations, but this section
      discusses actions taken by and to be taken by IANA. 
There are three registries affected:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">

        <li>Interface Types (ifType) <xref target="ifType-registry" format="default"/>: The registration process
 is updated in <xref target="procedures" format="default"/>, and the template is updated in <xref target="iftype-template" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>Tunnel Types (tunnelType) <xref target="tunnelType-registry" format="default"/>: The registration
 process is updated in <xref target="procedures" format="default"/>, and the template is updated in <xref target="tunneltype-template" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>Transmission Number Values <xref target="transmission-registry" format="default"/>: 
 The assignment process is updated in <xref target="transmission-discussion" format="default"/>.</li>
      </ol>
<t>At the time of publication of this document, IANA is unable to
perform some of the actions requested below due to limitations of their current
platform and toolset. In such cases, IANA is requested to perform these actions
as and when the migration to a new platform that would enable 
these actions is complete.
</t>
      <section anchor="module-formats" numbered="true" toc="default">

<name>MIB and YANG Modules</name>
<t>
   IANA is to complete the following to clarify the relationship
   between MIB modules, YANG modules, and the relevant registries.
</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li><t>The following note has been added to the IANAifType-MIB at
	  <xref target="protocol-registries" format="default"/>: 
          "This is one of the available formats of the Interface Types
	  (ifType) and Tunnel Types (tunnelType) registries."</t></li> 
          <li><t>The note for the iana-if-type YANG module 
	  at <xref target="protocol-registries" format="default"/> has been
	  updated to read:
	  "This is one of the available formats of the Interface Types (ifType) registry."</t></li> 
          <li><t>The note for the iana-tunnel-type YANG
	  module at <xref target="protocol-registries" format="default"/> has
	  been updated to read:
	  "This is one of the available formats of the Tunnel Types (tunnelType) registry."</t></li>

          <li>The new "Interface Parameters" category at <xref
	  target="protocol-registries" format="default"/> includes entries for
	  "Interface Types (ifType)" <xref target="ifType-registry"
	  format="default"/>, "Tunnel Types (tunnelType)" <xref
	  target="tunnelType-registry" format="default"/>, and "Transmission
	  Number Values" <xref target="transmission-registry" 
	  format="default"/>.</li> 
          <li>Update the "Interface Types (ifType)" registry <xref
	  target="ifType-registry" format="default"/> to list MIB <xref
	  target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/> and YANG <xref
	  target="yang-if-type" format="default"/> as Available Formats.</li> 
          <li>Update the "Tunnel Types (tunnelType)" registry <xref
	  target="tunnelType-registry" format="default"/> to list MIB <xref
	  target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/> and YANG <xref
	  target="yang-tunnel-type" format="default"/> as Available
	  Formats.</li> 
          <li>Replace the <xref target="yang-if-type" format="default"/> page
	  with the YANG module content rather than having a page that claims
	  to have multiple Available Formats.</li> 
          <li>Replace the <xref target="yang-tunnel-type" format="default"/>
	  page with the YANG module content rather than having a page that
	  claims to have multiple Available Formats.</li> 

        <li><t>In addition, <xref target="IANAifType-MIB" format="default"/> is to
	be updated as follows:</t>

        <t>OLD:</t>
<blockquote> 
Requests for new values should be made to IANA via email (iana@iana.org).</blockquote>
        <t>NEW:</t> 
<blockquote>
Interface types must not be directly added to the IANAifType-MIB MIB module.
They must instead be added to the "Interface Types (ifType)" registry at
<xref target="ifType-registry" format="default"/>.</blockquote>
        <t>(Note that <xref target="yang-if-type" format="default"/> was
	previously updated with this language.)</t>
	</li>

	<li>IANA has added this document as a reference in the "Interface Types
	(ifType)", "Tunnel Types (tunnelType)", and "Transmission Number
	Values" registries, as well as the iana-if-type
	YANG Module, iana-tunnel-type YANG Module, and IANAifType-MIB.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section anchor="transmission-number-assignments" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Transmission Number Assignments</name>
        <t>Per the discussion in <xref target="transmission-discussion"
	format="default"/>, <xref target="ifType-registry" format="default"/>
	has been updated as follows:</t> 
        <t>OLD:</t>
<blockquote>
For every ifType registration, the corresponding transmission 
number value should be registered or marked "Reserved".</blockquote>
        <t>NEW:</t> 
<blockquote>
For future ifType assignments, an OID-subtree assignment MIB-II's
'transmission' subtree will be made with the same value.</blockquote>
        <t>Similarly, the following change has been made to <xref target="transmission-registry" format="default"/>:</t>
        <t>OLD:</t>
<blockquote>
For every transmission number registration, the corresponding
ifType value should be registered or marked "Reserved".</blockquote>
        <t>NEW:</t> <blockquote>For future transmission number assignments, an 'ifType' will be made with the same value.</blockquote>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Since this document does not introduce any technology or protocol,
there are no security issues to be considered for this document
itself.</t>
      <t>For security considerations related to MIB and YANG modules that
expose these values, see <xref target="RFC2863" sectionFormat="of" section="9"/>, <xref target="RFC4087" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>, 
and <xref target="RFC8675" sectionFormat="of" section="3"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2863.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="ifType-registry" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/smi-numbers">
          <front>
            <title>Interface Types (ifType)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="IANAifType-MIB" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/ianaiftype-mib">
          <front>
            <title>IANAifType-MIB Definitions</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="yang-if-type" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/iana-if-type">
          <front>
            <title>iana-if-type YANG Module</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="yang-tunnel-type" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/iana-tunnel-type">
          <front>
            <title>iana-tunnel-type YANG Module</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="protocol-registries" target="https://www.iana.org/protocols">
          <front>
            <title>Protocol Registries</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="tunnelType-registry" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/smi-numbers">
          <front>
            <title>Tunnel Types (tunnelType)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="transmission-registry" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/smi-numbers">
          <front>
            <title>Transmission Number Values</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IANA</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1573.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7224.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2667.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4087.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3637.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5066.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3635.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4380.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1234.xml"/>
         <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8675.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
