<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
category="std" 
number="8866" 
docName="draft-ietf-mmusic-rfc4566bis-37"
ipr="pre5378Trust200902"
obsoletes="4566" 
updates="" 
submissionType="IETF" 
consensus="true" 
xml:lang="en" 
tocInclude="true" 
symRefs="true" 
sortRefs="true" 
version="3">



  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.27.1 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SDP">SDP: Session Description Protocol</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8866"/>
    <author fullname="Ali Begen" initials="A." surname="Begen">
      <organization>Networked Media</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Turkey</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ali.begen@networked.media</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Paul Kyzivat" initials="P." surname="Kyzivat">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pkyzivat@alum.mit.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Colin Perkins" initials="C." surname="Perkins">
      <organization abbrev="University of Glasgow">University of
      Glasgow</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <extaddr>School of Computing Science</extaddr>
          <city>Glasgow</city>
          <code>G12 8QQ</code>
          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>
        <email>csp@csperkins.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mark Handley" initials="M." surname="Handley">
      <organization abbrev="UCL">University College London</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <code>WC1E 6BT</code>
          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>
        <email>M.Handley@cs.ucl.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2021"/>

<keyword>Multimedia</keyword>
<keyword>conferencing</keyword>
<keyword>session setup</keyword>
<keyword>signaling</keyword>
<keyword>media</keyword>
<keyword>SIP</keyword>
<keyword>RTSP</keyword>
<keyword>voip</keyword>
<keyword>audio</keyword>
<keyword>video</keyword>
<keyword>streaming</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This memo defines the Session Description Protocol (SDP). SDP is
      intended for describing multimedia sessions for the purposes of session
      announcement, session invitation, and other forms of multimedia session
      initiation. This document obsoletes RFC 4566.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>When initiating multimedia teleconferences, voice-over-IP calls,
      streaming video, or other sessions, there is a requirement to convey
      media details, transport addresses, and other session description
      metadata to the participants.</t>
      <t>SDP provides a standard representation for such information,
      irrespective of how that information is transported. SDP is purely a
      format for session description -- it does not incorporate a transport
      protocol, and it is intended to use different transport protocols as
      appropriate, including the Session Announcement Protocol (SAP) <xref target="RFC2974" format="default"/>, Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261" format="default"/>, Real-Time Streaming Protocol (RTSP) <xref target="RFC7826" format="default"/>, electronic mail <xref target="RFC5322" format="default"/> using the MIME extensions <xref target="RFC2045" format="default"/>,
      and the Hypertext Transport Protocol (HTTP) <xref target="RFC7230" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>SDP is intended to be general purpose so that it can be used in a
      wide range of network environments and applications. However, it is not
      intended to support negotiation of session content or media encodings:
      this is viewed as outside the scope of session description.</t>
      <t>This memo obsoletes <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/>. The changes relative to
      <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/> are outlined in <xref target="changes" format="default"/> of this memo.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Glossary of Terms</name>
      <t>The following terms are used in this document and have specific meaning
      within the context of this document.</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Session Description:</dt>
        <dd>A well-defined format for
          conveying sufficient information to discover and participate in a
          multimedia session.</dd>
        <dt>Media Description:</dt>
        <dd>A Media Description contains the information 
          needed for one party to establish an application-layer network protocol 
          connection to another party. It starts with an "m=" line and is terminated 
          by either the next "m=" line or by the end of the session description.</dd>
        <dt>Session-Level Section:</dt>
        <dd>This refers to the parts that are not media descriptions, whereas the session description refers to the whole body that includes the session-level section and the media description(s).</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>The terms "multimedia conference" and "multimedia session" are used
      in this document as defined in <xref target="RFC7656" format="default"/>. The terms
      "session" and "multimedia session" are used interchangeably in this
      document.</t>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default" anchor="usage_examples">
      <name>Examples of SDP Usage</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Session Initiation</name>
        <t>The <xref target="RFC3261" format="default">Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</xref>
        is an application-layer control protocol for creating, modifying, and
        terminating sessions such as Internet multimedia conferences, Internet
        telephone calls, and multimedia distribution. The SIP messages used to
        create sessions carry session descriptions that allow participants to
        agree on a set of compatible media types <xref target="RFC6838" format="default"/>. 
        These session descriptions
        are commonly formatted using SDP. When used with SIP, the <xref target="RFC3264" format="default"> offer/answer model</xref> provides a limited
        framework for negotiation using SDP.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Streaming Media</name>
        <t>The <xref target="RFC7826" format="default">Real-Time Streaming Protocol
        (RTSP)</xref>, is an application-level protocol for control over the
        delivery of data with real-time properties. RTSP provides an
        extensible framework to enable controlled, on-demand delivery of
        real-time data, such as audio and video. An RTSP client and server
        negotiate an appropriate set of parameters for media delivery,
        partially using SDP syntax to describe those parameters.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Email and the World Wide Web</name>
        <t>Alternative means of conveying session descriptions include
        electronic mail and the World Wide Web (WWW). For both email and WWW
        distribution, the media type "application/sdp" is used. This enables
        the automatic launching of applications for participation in the
        session from the WWW client or mail reader in a standard manner.</t>
        <t>Note that descriptions of multicast sessions sent only via email
        or the WWW do not have the property that the receiver of a session
        description can necessarily receive the session because the multicast
        sessions may be restricted in scope, and access to the WWW server or
        reception of email is possibly outside this scope.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Multicast Session Announcement</name>
        <t>In order to assist the advertisement of multicast multimedia
        conferences and other multicast sessions, and to communicate the
        relevant session setup information to prospective participants, a
        distributed session directory may be used. An instance of such a
        session directory periodically sends packets containing a description
        of the session to a well-known multicast group. These advertisements
        are received by other session directories such that potential remote
        participants can use the session description to start the tools
        required to participate in the session.</t>
        <t>One protocol used to implement such a distributed directory is the
        <xref target="RFC2974" format="default">SAP</xref>. SDP provides the recommended
        session description format for such session announcements.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements and Recommendations</name>
      <t>The purpose of SDP is to convey information about media streams in
      multimedia sessions to allow the recipients of a session description to
      participate in the session. SDP is primarily intended for use with
      Internet protocols, although it is sufficiently general that it can describe
      multimedia conferences in other network environments. Media streams can
      be many-to-many. Sessions need not be continually active.</t>
      <t>Thus far, multicast-based sessions on the Internet have differed from
      many other forms of conferencing in that anyone receiving the traffic
      can join the session (unless the session traffic is encrypted). In such
      an environment, SDP serves two primary purposes. It is a means to
      communicate the existence of a session, and it is a means to convey
      sufficient information to enable joining and participating in the
      session. In a unicast environment, only the latter purpose is likely to
      be relevant.</t>
      <t>An SDP description includes the following:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Session name and purpose</li>
        <li>Time(s) the session is active</li>
        <li>The media comprising the session</li>
        <li>Information needed to receive those media (addresses, ports,
          formats, etc.)</li>
      </ul>
      <t>As resources necessary to participate in a session may be limited,
      some additional information may also be desirable:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Information about the bandwidth to be used by the session</li>
        <li>Contact information for the person responsible for the
          session</li>
      </ul>
      <t>In general, SDP must convey sufficient information to enable
      applications to join a session (with the possible exception of
      encryption keys) and to announce the resources to be used to any
      nonparticipants that may need to know. (This latter feature is
      primarily useful when SDP is used with a multicast session announcement
      protocol.)</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Media and Transport Information</name>
        <t>An SDP description includes the following media information:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The type of media (video, audio, etc.)</li>
          <li>The media transport protocol (RTP/UDP/IP, H.320, etc.)</li>
          <li>The format of the media (H.261 video, MPEG video, etc.)</li>
        </ul>
        <t>In addition to media format and transport protocol, SDP conveys
        address and port details. For an IP multicast session, these
        comprise:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The multicast group address for media</li>
          <li>The transport port for media</li>
        </ul>
        <t>This address and port are the destination address and destination
        port of the multicast stream, whether being sent, received, or
        both.</t>
        <t>For unicast IP sessions, the following are conveyed:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The remote address for media</li>
          <li>The remote transport port for media</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The semantics of the address and port depend on context. 
        Typically, this <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be the remote address and remote port 
        to which media is to be sent or received. 
        Details may differ based on the network type, address type, 
        protocol, and media specified, and whether the SDP is being distributed 
        as an advertisement or negotiated in an offer/answer <xref target="RFC3264" format="default"/> exchange.
        (E.g., Some address types or protocols may not have a notion of port.) 
        Deviating from typical behavior should be done cautiously 
        since this complicates implementations (including middleboxes that must 
        parse the addresses to open Network Address Translation (NAT) or 
        firewall pinholes).</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Timing Information</name>
        <t>Sessions may be either bounded or unbounded in time. Whether or not
        they are bounded, they may be only active at specific times. SDP can
        convey:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>An arbitrary list of start and stop times bounding the
            session</li>
          <li>For each bound, repeat times such as "every Wednesday at 10am
            for one hour"</li>
        </ul>
        <t>This timing information is globally consistent, irrespective of
        local time zone or daylight saving time (see <xref target="timing" format="default"/>).</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Obtaining Further Information about a Session</name>
        <t>A session description could convey enough information to decide
        whether or not to participate in a session. SDP may include additional
        pointers in the form of Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs) <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/> 
        for more information about the session.
        (Note that use of URIs to indicate remote resources is subject to 
        the security considerations from <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/>.)
</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Internationalization</name>
        <t>The SDP specification recommends the use of the ISO 10646 character
        set in the UTF-8 encoding <xref target="RFC3629" format="default"/> to allow many
        different languages to be represented. However, to assist in compact
        representations, SDP also allows other character sets such as
        <xref target="ISO.8859-1.1998" format="default"/> to be used when desired. 
        Internationalization only applies to
        free-text subfields (session name and background information), and not to
        SDP as a whole.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="SDP-specification" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SDP Specification</name>
      <t>An SDP description is denoted by the media type "application/sdp"
      (See <xref target="iana" format="default"/>).</t>
      <t>An SDP description is entirely textual. SDP field names and attribute
      names use only the US-ASCII subset of UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629" format="default"/>, 
      but textual fields and
      attribute values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use the full ISO 10646 character set in UTF-8
      encoding, or some other character set defined by the "a=charset:"
      attribute (<xref target="charset" format="default"/>). 
      Field and attribute values that use the full UTF-8 character
      set are never directly compared, hence there is no requirement for UTF-8
      normalization. The textual form, as opposed to a binary encoding such as
      ASN.1 or XDR, was chosen to enhance portability, to enable a variety of
      transports to be used, and to allow flexible, text-based toolkits to be
      used to generate and process session descriptions. However, since SDP
      may be used in environments where the maximum permissible size of a
      session description is limited, the encoding is deliberately compact.
      Also, since descriptions may be transported via very unreliable means
      or damaged by an intermediate caching server, the encoding was designed
      with strict order and formatting rules so that most errors would result
      in malformed session descriptions that could be detected easily and
      discarded.</t>
      <t>An SDP description consists of a number of lines of text of the
      form:</t>
      <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   <type>=<value>
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>where &lt;type&gt; is exactly one case-significant character and
      &lt;value&gt; is structured text whose format depends on &lt;type&gt;.
      In general, &lt;value&gt; is either a number of subfields delimited by a
      single space character or a free format string, and is case-significant
      unless a specific field defines otherwise. Whitespace separators are not used
      on either side of the "=" sign, however, the value can contain a leading
      whitespace as part of its syntax, i.e., that whitespace is part of the value.</t>
      <t>An SDP description <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to the syntax defined in <xref target="abnf" format="default"/>.
      The following is an overview of the syntax.</t>
      <t>An SDP description consists of a session-level section followed by
      zero or more media descriptions. The session-level section starts with a
      "v=" line and continues to the first media description (or the end of
      the whole description, whichever comes first). Each media description
      starts with an "m=" line and continues to the next media description
      or the end of the whole session description, whichever comes first. In
      general, session-level values are the default for all media unless
      overridden by an equivalent media-level value.</t>
      <t>Some lines in each description are required and some are optional,
      but when present, they must appear in exactly the order given here. (The fixed order
      greatly enhances error detection and allows for a simple parser).
      In the following overview, optional items are marked with a "*".</t>
      <sourcecode type=""><![CDATA[
   Session description
      v=  (protocol version)
      o=  (originator and session identifier)
      s=  (session name)
      i=* (session information)
      u=* (URI of description)
      e=* (email address)
      p=* (phone number)
      c=* (connection information -- not required if included in
           all media descriptions)
      b=* (zero or more bandwidth information lines)
      One or more time descriptions: 
        ("t=", "r=" and "z=" lines; see below)
      k=* (obsolete)
      a=* (zero or more session attribute lines)
      Zero or more media descriptions

   Time description
      t=  (time the session is active)
      r=* (zero or more repeat times)
      z=* (optional time zone offset line)

   Media description, if present
      m=  (media name and transport address)
      i=* (media title)
      c=* (connection information -- optional if included at
           session level)
      b=* (zero or more bandwidth information lines)
      k=* (obsolete)
      a=* (zero or more media attribute lines)
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>The set of type letters is deliberately small and not intended to be
      extensible -- an SDP parser <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> completely ignore or reject any session
      description that contains a type letter that it does not understand. The
      attribute mechanism ("a=", described in <xref target="attribspec" format="default"/>) is the primary means for
      extending SDP and tailoring it to particular applications or media. Some
      attributes (the ones listed in <xref target="attrs" format="default"/>) have
      a defined meaning, but others may be added on a media-
      or session-specific basis. (Attribute scopes in addition to media-specific
      and session-specific scopes may also be defined in extensions to this document,
      e.g., <xref target="RFC5576" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8864" format="default"/>.)
      An SDP parser <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore any attribute it doesn't understand.</t>
      <t>An SDP description may contain URIs that reference external content
      in the "u=", "k=", and "a=" lines. These URIs may be dereferenced in
      some cases, making the session description non-self-contained.</t>
      <t>The connection ("c=") information in the session-level section
      applies to all the media descriptions of that session unless overridden by connection
      information in the media description. 
      For instance, in the example below, each audio media description behaves as if 
      it were given a "c=IN IP4 198.51.100.1".
</t>
      <t>An example SDP description is:</t>
      <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      v=0
      o=jdoe 3724394400 3724394405 IN IP4 198.51.100.1
      s=Call to John Smith
      i=SDP Offer #1
      u=http://www.jdoe.example.com/home.html
      e=Jane Doe <jane@jdoe.example.com>
      p=+1 617 555-6011
      c=IN IP4 198.51.100.1
      t=0 0
      m=audio 49170 RTP/AVP 0
      m=audio 49180 RTP/AVP 0
      m=video 51372 RTP/AVP 99
      c=IN IP6 2001:db8::2
      a=rtpmap:99 h263-1998/90000
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>Text-containing fields such as the session-name-field and information-field are octet
      strings that may contain any octet with the exceptions of 0x00 (Nul),
      0x0a (ASCII newline), and 0x0d (ASCII carriage return). The sequence
      CRLF (0x0d0a) is used to end a line, although parsers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
      tolerant and also accept lines terminated with a single newline
      character. If the "a=charset:" attribute is not present, these octet
      strings <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be interpreted as containing ISO-10646 characters in UTF-8
      encoding. When the "a=charset:" attribute is present the session-name-field,
      information-field, and some attribute fields are interpreted according
      to the selected character set.</t>
      <t>A session description can contain domain names in the "o=", "u=",
      "e=", "c=", and "a=" lines. Any domain name used in SDP <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> comply with
      <xref target="RFC1034" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC1035" format="default"/>. Internationalized
      domain names (IDNs) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be represented using the ASCII Compatible
      Encoding (ACE) form defined in <xref target="RFC5890" format="default"/> and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be
      directly represented in UTF-8 or any other encoding (this requirement is
      for compatibility with <xref target="RFC2327" format="default"/> and other early
      SDP-related standards, which predate the development of
      internationalized domain names).</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Protocol Version ("v=")</name>
      <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      v=0
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "v=" line (version-field) gives the version of the Session Description
        Protocol. This memo defines version 0. There is no minor version
        number.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="origin" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Origin ("o=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
     o=<username> <sess-id> <sess-version> <nettype> <addrtype>
     <unicast-address>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "o=" line (origin-field) gives the originator of the session (her username and
        the address of the user's host) plus a session identifier and version
        number:</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>&lt;username&gt;</dt>
          <dd>is the user's login on the
            originating host, or it is "-" if the originating host does not
            support the concept of user IDs. The &lt;username&gt; <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
            contain spaces.</dd>
          <dt>&lt;sess-id&gt;</dt>
          <dd>is a numeric string such that the
            tuple of &lt;username&gt;, &lt;sess-id&gt;, &lt;nettype&gt;,
            &lt;addrtype&gt;, and &lt;unicast-address&gt; forms a globally
            unique identifier for the session. The method of &lt;sess-id&gt;
            allocation is up to the creating tool, but a timestamp, 
            in seconds since January 1, 1900 UTC, is recommended 
            to ensure uniqueness.</dd>
          <dt>&lt;sess-version&gt;</dt>
          <dd>is a version number for this
            session description. Its usage is up to the creating tool, so long
            as &lt;sess-version&gt; is increased when a modification is made
            to the session description. Again, as with &lt;sess-id&gt; 
            it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that a timestamp be used.</dd>
          <dt>&lt;nettype&gt;</dt>
          <dd>is a text string giving the type of
            network. Initially, "IN" is defined to have the meaning "Internet",
            but other values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be registered in the future (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>).</dd>
          <dt>&lt;addrtype&gt;</dt>
          <dd>is a text string giving the type of
            the address that follows. Initially, "IP4" and "IP6" are defined,
            but other values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be registered in the future (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>).</dd>
          <dt>&lt;unicast-address&gt;</dt>
          <dd>is an address of the machine
            from which the session was created. For an address type of "IP4",
            this is either a fully qualified domain name of the machine or the
            dotted-decimal representation of an IP version 4 address of the
            machine. For an address type of "IP6", this is either a fully
            qualified domain name of the machine or the address of the machine 
            represented as specified in <xref target="RFC5952" section="4" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>.
            For both "IP4" and "IP6", the fully qualified domain name is the form that
            <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be given unless this is unavailable, in which case a
            globally unique address <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be substituted.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>In general, the "o=" line serves as a globally unique identifier
        for this version of the session description, and the subfields
        excepting the version, taken together identify the session irrespective
        of any modifications.</t>
        <t>For privacy reasons, it is sometimes desirable to obfuscate the
        username and IP address of the session originator. If this is a
        concern, an arbitrary &lt;username&gt; and private
        &lt;unicast-address&gt; <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be chosen to populate the "o=" line,
        provided that these are selected in a manner that does not affect the
        global uniqueness of the field.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Session Name ("s=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   s=<session name>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "s=" line (session-name-field) is the textual session name. 
        There <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one and only one "s=" line per session description. 
        The "s=" line <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be empty. If a session has no meaningful name, 
        then "s= " or "s=-" (i.e., a single space or dash as the session name) is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>.
        If a session-level "a=charset:" attribute is present, it specifies the character set used 
        in the "s=" field. If a session-level "a=charset:" attribute is not present, 
        the "s=" field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain ISO 10646 characters in UTF-8 encoding.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Session Information ("i=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   i=<session information>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "i=" line (information-field) provides textual information about the session. There
        can be at most one session-level "i=" line per session description,
        and at most one "i=" line in each media description. Unless a
        media-level "i=" line is provided, the session-level "i=" line applies
        to that media description. If the "a=charset:" attribute is present, it
        specifies the character set used in the "i=" line. If the "a=charset:"
        attribute is not present, the "i=" line <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain ISO 10646
        characters in UTF-8 encoding.</t>
        <t>At most one "i=" line can be used for each media description. In media
        definitions, "i=" lines are primarily intended for labeling media
        streams. As such, they are most likely to be useful when a single
        session has more than one distinct media stream of the same media
        type. An example would be two different whiteboards, one for slides
        and one for feedback and questions.</t>
        <t>The "i=" line is intended to provide a free-form human-readable
        description of the session or the purpose of a media stream. It is not
        suitable for parsing by automata.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>URI ("u=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   u=<uri>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "u=" line (uri-field) provides a URI (Uniform Resource Identifier) 
        <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/>. The URI should be a pointer to additional
        human readable information about the session. 
        This line is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>. No more than one
        "u=" line is allowed per session description.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Email Address and Phone Number ("e=" and "p=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   e=<email-address>
   p=<phone-number>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "e=" line (email-field) and "p=" line (phone-field) specify contact information for the person
        responsible for the session. This is not necessarily the same person
        that created the session description.</t>
        <t>Inclusion of an email address or phone number is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>.</t>
        <t>If an email address or phone number is present, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        specified before the first media description. More than one email or phone
        line can be given for a session description.</t>
        <t>Phone numbers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be given in the form of an international
        public telecommunication number (see ITU-T Recommendation E.164 <xref target="E164" format="default"/>)
        preceded by a "+". Spaces and hyphens may be used to split up a phone-field
        to aid readability if desired. For example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   p=+1 617 555-6011
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Both email addresses and phone numbers can have an <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> free
        text string associated with them, normally giving the name of the
        person who may be contacted. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be enclosed in parentheses if
        it is present. For example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   e=j.doe@example.com (Jane Doe)
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The alternative <xref target="RFC5322" format="default"/> name quoting convention is
        also allowed for both email addresses and phone numbers. For
        example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   e=Jane Doe <j.doe@example.com>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The free text string <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be in the ISO-10646 character set with
        UTF-8 encoding, or alternatively in ISO-8859-1 or other encodings if
        the appropriate session-level "a=charset:" attribute is set.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="connection-information" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Connection Information ("c=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   c=<nettype> <addrtype> <connection-address>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "c=" line (connection-field) contains information necessary
        to establish a network connection.</t>
        <t>A session description <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain either at least one "c=" line in
        each media description or a single "c=" line at the session level. It
        <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> contain a single session-level "c=" line and additional media-level "c="
        line(s) per-media-description, in which case the media-level values
        override the session-level settings for the respective media.</t>
        <t>The first subfield (&lt;nettype&gt;) is the network type, which
        is a text string giving the type of network. Initially, "IN" is
        defined to have the meaning "Internet", but other values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be
        registered in the future (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>The second subfield (&lt;addrtype&gt;) is the address type. This
        allows SDP to be used for sessions that are not IP based. This memo
        only defines "IP4" and "IP6", but other values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be registered in the
        future (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>The third subfield (&lt;connection-address&gt;) is the
        connection address. Additional subfields <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be added after the
        connection address depending on the value of the &lt;addrtype&gt;
        subfield.</t>
        <t>When the &lt;addrtype&gt; is "IP4" or "IP6", the connection address is
        defined as follows:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>If the session is multicast, the connection address will be an
            IP multicast group address. If the session is not multicast, then
            the connection address contains the unicast IP address of the
            expected data source, data relay, or data sink as determined by
            additional attribute-fields (<xref target="attribspec" format="default"/>). 
            It is not expected that unicast
            addresses will be given in a session description that is
            communicated by a multicast announcement, though this is not
            prohibited.</li>
          <li>Sessions using an "IP4" multicast connection address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also
            have a time to live (TTL) value present in addition to the
            multicast address. The TTL and the address together define the
            scope with which multicast packets sent in this session will be
            sent. TTL values <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be in the range 0-255. Although the TTL <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
            be specified, its use to scope multicast traffic is deprecated;
            applications <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use an administratively scoped address
            instead.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The TTL for the session is appended to the address using a slash as
        a separator. An example is:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   c=IN IP4 233.252.0.1/127
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>"IP6" multicast does not use TTL scoping, and hence the TTL value
        <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be present for "IP6" multicast. It is expected that IPv6 scoped
        addresses will be used to limit the scope of multimedia
        conferences.</t>
        <t>Hierarchical or layered encoding schemes are data streams where the
        encoding from a single media source is split into a number of layers.
        The receiver can choose the desired quality (and hence bandwidth) by
        only subscribing to a subset of these layers. Such layered encodings
        are normally transmitted in multiple multicast groups to allow
        multicast pruning. This technique keeps unwanted traffic from sites
        only requiring certain levels of the hierarchy. For applications
        requiring multiple multicast groups, we allow the following notation
        to be used for the connection address:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   <base multicast address>[/<ttl>]/<number of addresses>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>If the number of addresses is not given, it is assumed to be one.
        Multicast addresses so assigned are contiguously allocated above the
        base address, so that, for example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   c=IN IP4 233.252.0.1/127/3
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>would state that addresses 233.252.0.1, 233.252.0.2, and
        233.252.0.3 are to be used with a TTL of 127. This is semantically
        identical to including multiple "c=" lines in a media description:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   c=IN IP4 233.252.0.1/127
   c=IN IP4 233.252.0.2/127
   c=IN IP4 233.252.0.3/127
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Similarly, an IPv6 example would be:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   c=IN IP6 ff00::db8:0:101/3
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>which is semantically equivalent to:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   c=IN IP6 ff00::db8:0:101
   c=IN IP6 ff00::db8:0:102
   c=IN IP6 ff00::db8:0:103
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>(remember that the TTL subfield is not present in "IP6"
        multicast).</t>
        <t>Multiple addresses or "c=" lines <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be specified on a per media description
        basis only if they provide multicast addresses for different layers in
        a hierarchical or layered encoding scheme. Multiple addresses or "c=" lines 
        <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be specified at session level.</t>
        <t>The slash notation for multiple addresses described above <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
        be used for IP unicast addresses.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="bandwidthInfo" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Bandwidth Information ("b=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   b=<bwtype>:<bandwidth>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> "b=" line (bandwidth-field) denotes the proposed bandwidth to be used by the
        session or media description. The &lt;bwtype&gt; is an alphanumeric modifier
        that provides the meaning of the &lt;bandwidth&gt; number. Two values are
        defined in this specification, but other values <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be registered in
        the future (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC3556" format="default"/>,
        <xref target="RFC3890" format="default"/>):</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>CT</dt>
          <dd><t>If the bandwidth of a session is different from
            the bandwidth implicit from the scope, a "b=CT:" line <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
            supplied for the session giving the proposed upper limit to the
            bandwidth used (the "conference total" bandwidth). Similarly, if
            the bandwidth of bundled media streams 
            <xref target="RFC8843" format="default"/> 
            in an "m=" line is different
            from the implicit value from the scope, a "b=CT:" line <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
            be supplied in the media level. The primary purpose of this is to
            give an approximate idea as to whether two or more sessions (or
            bundled media streams) can coexist simultaneously. Note that a "b=CT:" line
            gives a total bandwidth figure for all the media at all
            endpoints.</t>
          <t>The Mux Category for "b=CT:" is NORMAL. This is discussed
            in <xref target="RFC8859" format="default"/>.</t>
          </dd>
          <dt>AS</dt>
          <dd><t>The bandwidth is interpreted to be application
            specific (it will be the application's concept of maximum
            bandwidth). Normally, this will coincide with what is set on the
            application's "maximum bandwidth" control if applicable. For
            RTP-based applications, the "b=AS:" line gives the RTP "session bandwidth" as
            defined in <xref target="RFC3550" section="6.2" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/>. Note that a "b=AS:" line
            gives a bandwidth figure for a single media at a single endpoint,
            although there may be many endpoints sending simultaneously.</t>
          <t>The Mux Category for "b=AS:" is SUM. This is discussed
            in <xref target="RFC8859" format="default"/>.</t>
        </dd>
        </dl>
        <t><xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/> defined an "X-" prefix for &lt;bwtype&gt; names. 
	This was intended for experimental purposes only. For example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   b=X-YZ:128
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Use of the "X-" prefix is <bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>. Instead new (non "X-" prefix) &lt;bwtype&gt; names
        <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be defined, and then <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered with IANA in the standard namespace. SDP parsers
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore bandwidth-fields with unknown &lt;bwtype&gt; names. The &lt;bwtype&gt; names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        alphanumeric and, although no length limit is given, it is recommended
        that they be short.</t>
        <t>The &lt;bandwidth&gt; is interpreted as kilobits per second by
        default (including the transport and network-layer, but not the link-layer, overhead). The definition of a new &lt;bwtype&gt; modifier <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> specify
        that the bandwidth is to be interpreted in some alternative unit (the
        "CT" and "AS" modifiers defined in this memo use the default
        units).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="timing" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Time Active ("t=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   t=<start-time> <stop-time>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>A "t=" line (time-field) begins a time description that specifies the start and stop times for a session.
        Multiple time descriptions <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used if a session is active at multiple
        irregularly spaced times; each additional time description specifies
        additional periods of time for which the session will be active. If the
        session is active at regular repeat times, a repeat description, 
        begun by an "r=" line (see <xref target="repeattime" format="default"/>) can be
        included following the time-field -- in which case the
        time-field specifies the start and stop times of the entire repeat
        sequence.</t>
        <t>The following example specifies two active intervals:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   t=3724394400 3724398000 ; Mon 8-Jan-2018 10:00-11:00 UTC
   t=3724484400 3724488000 ; Tue 9-Jan-2018 11:00-12:00 UTC
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The first and second subfields of the time-field give the start and stop times,
        respectively, for the session. These are the decimal
        representation of time values in seconds
        since January 1, 1900 UTC. To convert these values to Unix
        time (UTC), subtract decimal 2208988800.</t>
        <t>Some time representations will
        wrap in the year 2036. Because SDP uses an arbitrary length
        decimal representation, it does not have this issue. Implementations
        of SDP need to be prepared to handle these larger values.</t>
        <t>If the &lt;stop-time&gt; is set to zero, then the session is not
        bounded, though it will not become active until after the
        &lt;start-time&gt;. If the &lt;start-time&gt; is also zero, the
        session is regarded as permanent.</t>
        <t>User interfaces <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> strongly discourage the creation of
        unbounded and permanent sessions as they give no information about
        when the session is actually going to terminate, and so make
        scheduling difficult.</t>
        <t>The general assumption may be made, when displaying unbounded
        sessions that have not timed out to the user, that an unbounded
        session will only be active until half an hour from the current time
        or the session start time, whichever is the later. If behavior other
        than this is required, a &lt;stop-time&gt; <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be given and modified as
        appropriate when new information becomes available about when the
        session should really end.</t>
        <t>Permanent sessions may be shown to the user as never being active
        unless there are associated repeat times that state precisely when the
        session will be active.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="repeattime" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Repeat Times ("r=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   r=<repeat interval> <active duration> <offsets from start-time>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>An"r=" line (repeat-field) specifies repeat times for a session. 
        If needed to express complex schedules, multiple repeat-fields may
        be included. For example, if a
        session is active at 10am on Monday and 11am on Tuesday for one hour
        each week for three months, then the &lt;start-time&gt; in the
        corresponding "t=" line would be the representation of 10am on the
        first Monday, the &lt;repeat interval&gt; would be 1 week, the
        &lt;active duration&gt; would be 1 hour, and the offsets would be zero
        and 25 hours. The corresponding "t=" line stop time would be the
        representation of the end of the last session three months later. By
        default, all subfields are in seconds, so the "r=" and "t=" lines might
        be the following:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   t=3724394400 3730536000 ; Mon 8-Jan-2018 10:00-11:00 UTC
                           ; Tues 20-Mar-2018 12:00 UTC
   r=604800 3600 0 90000   ; 1 week, 1 hour, zero, 25 hours    
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>To make the description more compact, times may also be given in
        units of days, hours, or minutes. The syntax for these is a number
        immediately followed by a single case-sensitive character. Fractional
        units are not allowed -- a smaller unit should be used instead. The
        following unit specification characters are allowed:</t>
<table>
<name>Time Unit Specification Characters</name>
	<tbody>
	<tr>
		<td>d</td>
		<td>days (86400 seconds)</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>h</td>
		<td>hours (3600 seconds)</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>m</td>
		<td>minutes (60 seconds)</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>s</td>
		<td>seconds (allowed for completeness)</td>
	</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>
        <t>Thus, the above repeat-field could also have been
        written:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   r=7d 1h 0 25h
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Monthly and yearly repeats cannot be directly specified with a
        single SDP repeat time; instead, separate time-descriptions should be used to
        explicitly list the session times.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="tzadj" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Time Zone Adjustment ("z=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   z=<adjustment time> <offset> <adjustment time> <offset> ....
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>A "z=" line (zone-field) is an optional modifier to the repeat-fields it immediately follows.
        It does not apply to any other fields.</t>
        <t>To schedule a repeated session that spans a change from daylight
        saving time to standard time or vice versa, it is necessary to specify
        offsets from the base time. This is required because different time
        zones change time at different times of day, different countries
        change to or from daylight saving time on different dates, and some
        countries do not have daylight saving time at all.</t>
        <t>Thus, in order to schedule a session that is at the same time
        winter and summer, it must be possible to specify unambiguously by
        whose time zone a session is scheduled. To simplify this task for
        receivers, we allow the sender to specify the time (represented as seconds 
        since January 1, 1900 UTC) that a time zone adjustment happens  
        and the offset from the time when the session
        was first scheduled. The "z=" line allows the sender to specify a list
        of these adjustment times and offsets from the base time.</t>
        <t>An example might be the following:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
   t=3724394400 3754123200       ; Mon 8-Jan-2018 10:00 UTC
                                 ; Tues 18-Dec-2018 12:00 UTC
   r=604800 3600 0 90000         ; 1 week, 1 hour, zero, 25 hours 
   z=3730928400 -1h 3749680800 0 ; Sun 25-Mar-2018 1:00 UTC,
                                 ; offset 1 hour,
                                 ; Sun 28-Oct-2018 2:00 UTC,
                                 ; no offset
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This specifies that at time 3730928400 (Sun 25-Mar-2018 1:00 UTC, 
        the onset of British Summer Time)  the time base by which the
        session's repeat times are calculated is shifted back by 1 hour, and
        that at time 3749680800 (Sun 28-Oct-2018 2:00 UTC, the end of British 
        Summer Time) the session's original time base is restored.
        Adjustments are always relative to the specified start time -- they
        are not cumulative.</t>
        <t>If a session is likely to last several years, it is expected that
        the session description will be modified periodically rather than
        transmit several years' worth of adjustments in one session
        description.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="key-field" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Encryption Keys ("k=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   k=<method>
   k=<method>:<encryption key>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The "k=" line (key-field) is obsolete and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used. It is included in 
            this document for legacy reasons. One <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> include a "k=" line 
            in an SDP, and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> discard it if it is received in an SDP. </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="attribspec" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Attributes ("a=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   a=<attribute-name>
   a=<attribute-name>:<attribute-value>
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Attributes are the primary means for extending SDP. Attributes may
        be defined to be used as session-level attributes, media-level
        attributes, or both. (Attribute scopes in addition to media-level and
        session-level scopes may also be defined in extensions to this document,
        e.g., <xref target="RFC5576" format="default"/> and  
        <xref target="RFC8864" format="default"/>.)</t>
        <t>A media description may contain any number of "a=" lines (attribute-fields)
        that are media description specific. These are referred to as media-level
        attributes and add information about the media description. Attribute-fields
        can also be added before the first media description; these session-level
        attributes convey additional information that applies to the session
        as a whole rather than to individual media descriptions.</t>
        <t>Attribute-fields may be of two forms:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>A property attribute is simply of the form "a=&lt;attribute-name&gt;".
            These are binary attributes, and the presence of the attribute
            conveys that the attribute is a property of the session. An
            example might be "a=recvonly".</li>
          <li>A value attribute is of the form
            "a=&lt;attribute-name&gt;:&lt;attribute-value&gt;". For example, a whiteboard
            could have the value attribute "a=orient:landscape".</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Attribute interpretation depends on the media tool being invoked.
        Thus receivers of session descriptions should be configurable in their
        interpretation of session descriptions in general and of attributes in
        particular.</t>
        <t>Attribute names <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the US-ASCII subset of
        ISO-10646/UTF-8.</t>
        <t>Attribute values are octet strings, and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use any octet value
        except 0x00 (Nul), 0x0A (LF), and 0x0D (CR). By default, attribute
        values are to be interpreted as in ISO-10646 character set with UTF-8
        encoding. Unlike other text fields, attribute values are NOT normally
        affected by the "a=charset:" attribute as this would make comparisons
        against known values problematic. However, when an attribute is
        defined, it can be defined to be charset dependent, in which case its
        value should be interpreted in the session charset rather than in
        ISO-10646.</t>
        <t>Attributes <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered with IANA (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>). 
        If an attribute is received that is not understood,
        it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the receiver.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Media Descriptions ("m=")</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   m=<media> <port> <proto> <fmt> ...
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>A session description may contain a number of media descriptions.
        Each media description starts with an "m=" line (media-field) and is terminated by
        either the next "m=" line or by the end of the session description. A
        media-field has several subfields:</t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
          <dt>&lt;media&gt;</dt>
          <dd>is the media type. This document defines the values "audio", "video", "text", "application", and "message". This list is extended by other memos and may be further extended by additional memos registering media types in the future (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>). For example, <xref target="RFC6466" format="default"/> defined the "image" media type.</dd>
          <dt>&lt;port&gt;</dt>
          <dd><t>is the transport port to which the
            media stream is sent. The meaning of the transport port depends on
            the network being used as specified in the relevant "c=" line, and
            on the transport protocol defined in the &lt;proto&gt; subfield
            of the media-field. Other ports used by the media application
            (such as the RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) port <xref target="RFC3550" format="default"/>) <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be derived algorithmically from the base
            media port or <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be specified in a separate attribute (for
            example, the "a=rtcp:" attribute as defined in <xref target="RFC3605" format="default"/>).</t>
    
          <t>If noncontiguous ports are used or if they don't follow the
            parity rule of even RTP ports and odd RTCP ports, the "a=rtcp:"
            attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used. Applications that are requested to send
            media to a &lt;port&gt; that is odd and where the "a=rtcp:" attribute is
            present <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> subtract 1 from the RTP port: that is, they <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
            send the RTP to the port indicated in &lt;port&gt; and send the
            RTCP to the port indicated in the "a=rtcp:" attribute.</t>
       
            <t>For applications where hierarchically encoded streams are being
            sent to a unicast address, it may be necessary to specify multiple
            transport ports. This is done using a similar notation to that
            used for IP multicast addresses in the "c=" line: </t>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
    m=<media> <port>/<number of ports> <proto> <fmt> ...
]]></sourcecode>
            <t>In such a case, the ports used depend on the transport
            protocol. For RTP, the default is that only the even-numbered
            ports are used for data with the corresponding one-higher odd
            ports used for the RTCP belonging to the RTP session, and the
            &lt;number of ports&gt; denoting the number of RTP sessions. For
            example: </t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
       m=video 49170/2 RTP/AVP 31
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>would specify that ports 49170 and 49171 form one RTP/RTCP pair,
            and 49172 and 49173 form the second RTP/RTCP pair. RTP/AVP is the
            transport protocol, and 31 is the format (see the description of &lt;fmt&gt; below).</t>
          <t>This document does not include a mechanism for declaring hierarchically 
	    encoded streams using noncontiguous ports.
	    (There is currently no attribute defined that can accomplish this. 
	    The "a=rtcp:" attribute defined in <xref target="RFC3605" format="default"/> does not handle hierarchical encoding.)
	    If a need arises to declare noncontiguous ports then it will be necessary to define a new attribute to do so.</t>
            <t>If multiple addresses are specified in the "c=" line and
            multiple ports are specified in the "m=" line, a one-to-one
            mapping from port to the corresponding address is implied. For
            example: </t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
       m=video 49170/2 RTP/AVP 31
       c=IN IP4 233.252.0.1/127/2
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>would imply that address 233.252.0.1 is used with ports 49170
            and 49171, and address 233.252.0.2 is used with ports 49172 and
            49173.</t>
            <t>The mapping is similar if multiple addresses are specified using multiple "c=" lines.
            For example: </t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
       m=video 49170/2 RTP/AVP 31
       c=IN IP6 ff00::db8:0:101
       c=IN IP6 ff00::db8:0:102
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>would imply that address ff00::db8:0:101 is used with ports 49170
            and 49171, and address ff00::db8:0:102 is used with ports 49172 and
            49173.</t>
          <t>This document gives no meaning to assigning the same media address to 
	    multiple media descriptions. 
	    Doing so does not implicitly group those media descriptions in any way.
	    An explicit grouping framework (for example, <xref target="RFC5888" format="default"/>) 
	    should instead be used to express the intended semantics. 
	    For instance, see <xref target="RFC8843" format="default"/>.</t>
           </dd>
          <dt>&lt;proto&gt;</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>is the transport protocol. The meaning
            of the transport protocol is dependent on the address type subfield
            in the relevant "c=" line. Thus a "c=" line with an address type of "IP4" indicates that
            the transport protocol runs over IPv4. The following transport
            protocols are defined, but may be extended through registration of
            new protocols with IANA (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>): </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>udp: denotes that the data is transported directly in UDP 
                with no additional framing.</li>
              <li>RTP/AVP: denotes <xref target="RFC3550" format="default">RTP</xref> used
                under the <xref target="RFC3551" format="default">RTP Profile for Audio and
                Video Conferences with Minimal Control</xref> running over
                UDP.</li>
              <li>RTP/SAVP: denotes the <xref target="RFC3711" format="default">Secure
                Real-time Transport Protocol</xref> running over UDP.</li>
              <li>RTP/SAVPF: denotes SRTP with the <xref target="RFC5124" format="default">
                Extended SRTP Profile for RTCP-Based Feedback</xref> running over UDP.</li>
            </ul>
          <t>The main reason to specify the transport protocol in addition
            to the media format is that the same standard media formats may be
            carried over different transport protocols even when the network
            protocol is the same -- a historical example is vat (MBone's popular multimedia audio tool) Pulse Code
            Modulation (PCM) audio and RTP PCM audio; another might be TCP/RTP
            PCM audio. In addition, relays and monitoring tools that are
            transport-protocol-specific but format-independent are
            possible.</t>
          </dd>
          <dt>&lt;fmt&gt;</dt>
          <dd><t>is a media format description. The
            fourth and any subsequent subfields describe the format of the
            media. The interpretation of the media format depends on the value
            of the &lt;proto&gt; subfield.</t>

          <t>If the &lt;proto&gt; subfield is "RTP/AVP" or "RTP/SAVP", the
            &lt;fmt&gt; subfields contain RTP payload type numbers.  When a list of 
payload type numbers is given, this implies that all of these 
payload formats MAY be used in the session, and these payload 
formats are listed in order of preference, with the first format listed 
being preferred. When multiple payload formats are listed,
the first acceptable payload format 
from the beginning of the list <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be used for the session.

            For dynamic payload type assignments, the "a=rtpmap:"
            attribute (see <xref target="rtpmap" format="default"/>) <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be used to map from
            an RTP payload type number to a media encoding name that
            identifies the payload format. The "a=fmtp:" attribute <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used
            to specify format parameters (see <xref target="fmtp" format="default"/>).</t>
          <t>If the &lt;proto&gt; subfield is "udp", the &lt;fmt&gt;
            subfields <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reference a media type describing the format under
            the "audio", "video", "text", "application", or "message"
            top-level media types. The media type registration <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> define
            the packet format for use with UDP transport.</t>
          <t>For media using other transport protocols, the &lt;fmt&gt;
            subfield is protocol specific. Rules for interpretation of the
            &lt;fmt&gt; subfield <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be defined when registering new
            protocols (see <xref target="MediaTypes"/>).</t>
          <t><xref target="RFC4855" section="3" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/> states that the payload
            format (encoding) names defined in the RTP profile are commonly
            shown in upper case, while media subtype names are commonly shown
            in lower case. It also states that both of these names are
            case-insensitive in both places, similar to parameter names which
            are case-insensitive both in media type strings and in the default
            mapping to the SDP "a=fmtp:" attribute.</t>
         </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="attrs" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SDP Attributes</name>
      <t>The following attributes are defined. Since application writers may
      add new attributes as they are required, this list is not exhaustive.
      Registration procedures for new attributes are defined in <xref target="AttributeNames" format="default"/>. 
      Syntax is provided using ABNF <xref target="RFC7405" format="default"/> 
      with some of the rules defined further in <xref target="abnf" format="default"/>.</t>
      <section anchor="cat" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>cat (Category)</name>
<dl>
       <dt>Name:</dt><dd>cat</dd>
       <dt>Value:</dt><dd>cat-value</dd>
       <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session</dd>
       <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
       <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      cat-value = category
      category = non-ws-string
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=cat:foo.bar
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This attribute gives the dot-separated hierarchical category of the
        session. This is to enable a receiver to filter unwanted sessions by
        category. There is no central registry of categories. This attribute
        is obsolete and <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be used. It <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be ignored if received.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="keywds" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>keywds (Keywords)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>keywds</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>keywds-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>yes</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      keywds-value = keywords
      keywords = text
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=keywds:SDP session description protocol
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Like the "a=cat:" attribute, this was intended to assist identifying wanted
        sessions at the receiver, and to allow a receiver to select interesting
        sessions based on keywords describing the purpose of the session; however, there
        is no central registry of keywords. Its value should be interpreted in
        the charset specified for the session description if one is specified,
        or by default in ISO 10646/UTF-8. This attribute is obsolete and 
	<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be used. It <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be ignored if received.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>tool</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>tool</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>tool-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      tool-value = tool-name-and-version
      tool-name-and-version = text
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=tool:foobar V3.2
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This gives the name and version number of the tool used to create
        the session description.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ptime" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>ptime (Packet Time)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>ptime</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>ptime-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      ptime-value = non-zero-int-or-real
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=ptime:20
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This gives the length of time in milliseconds represented by the
        media in a packet. This is probably only meaningful for audio data,
        but may be used with other media types if it makes sense. It should
        not be necessary to know "a=ptime:" to decode RTP or vat audio, and it is
        intended as a recommendation for the encoding/packetization of
        audio.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>maxptime (Maximum Packet Time)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>maxptime</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>maxptime-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      maxptime-value = non-zero-int-or-real
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=maxptime:20
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This gives the maximum amount of media that can be encapsulated in
        each packet, expressed as time in milliseconds. The time <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be
        calculated as the sum of the time the media present in the packet
        represents. For frame-based codecs, the time <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be an integer
        multiple of the frame size. This attribute is probably only meaningful
        for audio data, but may be used with other media types if it makes
        sense. Note that this attribute was introduced after <xref target="RFC2327" format="default"/>, 
        and implementations that have not been updated will ignore this
        attribute.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="rtpmap" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>rtpmap</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>rtpmap</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>rtpmap-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      rtpmap-value = payload-type SP encoding-name
        "/" clock-rate [ "/" encoding-params ]
      payload-type = zero-based-integer
      encoding-name = token
      clock-rate = integer
      encoding-params = channels
      channels = integer
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This attribute maps from an RTP payload type number (as used in an
        "m=" line) to an encoding name denoting the payload format to be used.
        It also provides information on the clock rate and encoding
        parameters. Note that the payload type number is indicated in a 7-bit
        field, limiting the values to inclusively between 0 and 127.</t>
        <t>Although an RTP profile can make static assignments of payload type
        numbers to payload formats, it is more common for that assignment to
        be done dynamically using "a=rtpmap:" attributes. As an example of a
        static payload type, consider u-law PCM encoded single-channel audio
        sampled at 8 kHz. This is completely defined in the RTP audio/video
        profile as payload type 0, so there is no need for an "a=rtpmap:"
        attribute, and the media for such a stream sent to UDP port 49232 can
        be specified as: </t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
          m=audio 49232 RTP/AVP 0
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>An example of a dynamic payload type is 16-bit linear encoded
        stereo audio sampled at 16 kHz. If we wish to use the dynamic RTP/AVP
        payload type 98 for this stream, additional information is required to
        decode it: </t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
          m=audio 49232 RTP/AVP 98
          a=rtpmap:98 L16/16000/2
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Up to one "a=rtpmap:" attribute can be defined for each media format
        specified. Thus, we might have the following: </t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
          m=audio 49230 RTP/AVP 96 97 98
          a=rtpmap:96 L8/8000
          a=rtpmap:97 L16/8000
          a=rtpmap:98 L16/11025/2
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>RTP profiles that specify the use of dynamic payload types <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        define the set of valid encoding names and/or a means to register
        encoding names if that profile is to be used with SDP. The "RTP/AVP"
        and "RTP/SAVP" profiles use media subtypes for encoding names, under
        the top-level media type denoted in the "m=" line. In the example
        above, the media types are "audio/L8" and "audio/L16".</t>
        <t>For audio streams, encoding-params indicates the number
        of audio channels. This parameter is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> and may be omitted if
        the number of channels is one, provided that no additional parameters
        are needed.</t>
        <t>For video streams, no encoding parameters are currently
        specified.</t>
        <t>Additional encoding parameters <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be defined in the future, but
        codec-specific parameters <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be added. Parameters added to an
        "a=rtpmap:" attribute <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> only be those required for a session
        directory to make the choice of appropriate media to participate in a
        session. Codec-specific parameters should be added in other attributes
        (for example, "a=fmtp:").</t>
        <t>Note: RTP audio formats typically do not include information about
        the number of samples per packet. If a non-default (as defined in the
        RTP Audio/Video Profile <xref target="RFC3551" format="default"/>) packetization is required, the "a=ptime:"
        attribute is used as given in <xref target="ptime" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Media Direction Attributes</name>
        <t>At most one occurrence of "a=recvonly", "a=sendrecv", "a=sendonly", 
        or "a=inactive" <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear at
        session level, and at most one <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear in each media description.</t>
        <t>If any one of these appears in a media description, then it applies for
        that media description. If none appears in a media description, then the one
        from session level, if any, applies to that media description.</t>
        <t>If none of the media direction attributes is present at either
        session level or media level, "a=sendrecv" <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be assumed as the
        default.</t>
        <t>Within the following SDP example, the "a=sendrecv" attribute applies 
        to the first audio media and the "a=inactive" attribute applies to the others.</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      v=0
      o=jdoe 3724395000 3724395001 IN IP6 2001:db8::1
      s=-
      c=IN IP6 2001:db8::1
      t=0 0
      a=inactive
      m=audio 49170 RTP/AVP 0
      a=sendrecv
      m=audio 49180 RTP/AVP 0
      m=video 51372 RTP/AVP 99
      a=rtpmap:99 h263-1998/90000
]]></sourcecode>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>recvonly (Receive-Only)</name>
<dl>
          <dt>Name:</dt><dd>recvonly</dd>
          <dt>Value:</dt><dd></dd>
          <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session, media</dd>
          <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
          <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=recvonly
]]></sourcecode>

          <t>This specifies that the tools should be started in receive-only
          mode where applicable. Note that receive-only mode applies to the media only,
          not to any associated control protocol. 
          An RTP-based system in receive-only mode <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> still send RTCP packets 
          as described in <xref target="RFC3550" section="6" sectionFormat="comma" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>sendrecv (Send-Receive)</name>
<dl>
          <dt>Name:</dt><dd>sendrecv</dd>
          <dt>Value:</dt><dd></dd>
          <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session, media</dd>
          <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
          <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=sendrecv
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>This specifies that the tools should be started in send and
          receive mode. This is necessary for interactive multimedia
          conferences with tools that default to receive-only mode.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>sendonly (Send-Only)</name>
<dl>
          <dt>Name:</dt><dd>sendonly</dd>
          <dt>Value:</dt><dd></dd>
          <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session, media</dd>
          <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
          <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=sendonly
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>This specifies that the tools should be started in send-only
          mode. An example may be where a different unicast address is to be
          used for a traffic destination than for a traffic source. In such a
          case, two media descriptions may be used, one in send-only mode and one
          in receive-vonly mode. Note that send-only mode applies only to the media, and any
          associated control protocol (e.g., RTCP) <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> still be received
          and processed as normal.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="inactive" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>inactive</name>
<dl>
          <dt>Name:</dt><dd>inactive</dd>
          <dt>Value:</dt><dd></dd>
          <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session, media</dd>
          <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
          <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=inactive
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>This specifies that the tools should be started in inactive mode.
          This is necessary for interactive multimedia conferences where users
          can put other users on hold. No media is sent over an inactive media
          stream. Note that an RTP-based system <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> still send RTCP (if RTCP
          is used), even if started in inactive mode.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>orient (Orientation)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>orient</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>orient-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      orient-value = portrait / landscape / seascape
      portrait  = %s"portrait"
      landscape = %s"landscape"
      seascape  = %s"seascape"
         ; NOTE: These names are case-sensitive.
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=orient:portrait
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Normally this is only used for a whiteboard or presentation tool.
        It specifies the orientation of the workspace on the screen.
        Permitted values are "portrait", "landscape", and "seascape"
        (upside-down landscape).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="type" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>type (Conference Type)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>type</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>type-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      type-value = conference-type
      conference-type = broadcast / meeting / moderated / test /
                        H332
      broadcast = %s"broadcast"
      meeting   = %s"meeting"
      moderated = %s"moderated"
      test      = %s"test"
      H332      = %s"H332"
         ; NOTE: These names are case-sensitive.
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=type:moderated
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This specifies the type of the multimedia conference. 
        Allowed values are "broadcast", "meeting", "moderated", "test", and "H332".
        These values have implications for other options that are likely to be appropriate:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>When "a=type:broadcast" is specified, "a=recvonly" is probably
                 appropriate for those connecting.</li>
          <li>When "a=type:meeting" is specified, "a=sendrecv" is likely to be appropriate.</li>
          <li>"a=type:moderated" suggests the use of a floor control tool and 
                 that the media tools be started so as to mute new sites joining the 
                 multimedia conference.</li>
          <li>Specifying "a=type:H332" indicates that this loosely
                 coupled session is part of an H.332 session as defined in the ITU
                 H.332 specification <xref target="ITU.H332.1998" format="default"/>. Media tools should
                 be started using "a=recvonly".</li>
          <li>Specifying "a=type:test" is suggested as a hint that,
                 unless explicitly requested otherwise, receivers can safely avoid
                 displaying this session description to users.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="charset" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>charset (Character Set)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>charset</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>charset-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      charset-value = <defined in [RFC2978]>
]]></sourcecode>

        <t>This specifies the character set to be used to display the session
        name and information data. By default, the ISO-10646 character set in
        UTF-8 encoding is used. If a more compact representation is required,
        other character sets may be used. For example, the ISO 8859-1 is
        specified with the following SDP attribute:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=charset:ISO-8859-1
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The charset specified <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one of those registered in the IANA
        Character Sets registry
        (<eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/character-sets"/>), such as ISO-8859-1.
        The character set identifier is a string that <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be compared
        against identifiers from the "Name" or "Preferred MIME Name" field of
        the registry using a case-insensitive comparison. If the identifier is
        not recognized or not supported, all strings that are affected by it
        <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be regarded as octet strings.</t>
        <t>Charset-dependent fields <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain only sequences of bytes that are
        valid according to the definition of the selected character set.
        Furthermore, charset-dependent fields <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain the bytes 0x00 (Nul), 
        0x0A (LF), and 0x0d (CR).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sdplang" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>sdplang (SDP Language)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>sdplang</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>sdplang-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session, media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      sdplang-value = Language-Tag
      ; Language-Tag defined in RFC 5646
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=sdplang:fr
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Multiple "a=sdplang:" attributes can be provided either at session or
        media level if the session description or media use multiple
        languages.</t>
        <t>As a session-level attribute, it specifies the language for the
        session description (not the language of the media). As a media-level
        attribute, it specifies the language for any media-level SDP
        information-field associated with that media (again not the language
        of the media), overriding any "a=sdplang:" attributes specified at
        session level.</t>
        <t>In general, sending session descriptions consisting of multiple
        languages is discouraged. Instead, multiple session descriptions <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
        sent describing the session, one in each language. However, this is
        not possible with all transport mechanisms, and so multiple "a=sdplang:"
        attributes are allowed although <bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>.</t>
        <t>The "a=sdplang:" attribute value must be a single language tag
        <xref target="RFC5646" format="default"/>. An "a=sdplang:" attribute
        <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be specified when a session is distributed with sufficient
        scope to cross geographic boundaries, where the language of recipients
        cannot be assumed, or where the session is in a different language
        from the locally assumed norm.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="lang" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>lang (Language)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>lang</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>lang-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>session, media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      lang-value = Language-Tag
      ; Language-Tag defined in RFC 5646
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=lang:de
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Multiple "a=lang:" attributes can be provided either at session or media
        level if the session or media has capabilities in more than one
        language, in which case the order of the attributes indicates the
        order of preference of the various languages in the session or media,
        from most preferred to least preferred.</t>
        <t>As a session-level attribute, "a=lang:" specifies a language capability
        for the session being described. As a media-level attribute, it
        specifies a language capability for that media, overriding any
        session-level language(s) specified.</t>
        <t>The "a=lang:" attribute value must be a single <xref target="RFC5646" format="default"/> 
        language tag. An "a=lang:" attribute <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
        be specified when a session is of sufficient scope to cross geographic
        boundaries where the language of participants cannot be assumed, or
        where the session has capabilities in languages different from the
        locally assumed norm.</t>
        <t>The "a=lang:" attribute is supposed to be used for setting the initial
 language(s) used in the session. Events during the session may influence which language(s) are used, and the participants are not strictly bound to only use the declared languages.</t>
        <t>Most real-time use cases start with just one language used, while other cases involve a range of languages, e.g., an interpreted or subtitled session. When more than one "a=lang:" attribute is specified, 
the "a=lang:" attribute itself does not provide any information about multiple languages being intended to be used during the session, or if the intention is to only select one of the languages. If needed, a new attribute can be defined and used to indicate such intentions. Without such semantics, it is assumed that for a negotiated session one of the declared languages will be selected and used.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>framerate (Frame Rate)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>framerate</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>framerate-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      framerate-value = non-zero-int-or-real
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=framerate:60
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This gives the maximum video frame rate in frames/sec. It is
        intended as a recommendation for the encoding of video data. Decimal
        representations of fractional values are allowed. It is defined only
        for video media.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>quality</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>quality</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>quality-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      quality-value = zero-based-integer
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=quality:10
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This gives a suggestion for the quality of the encoding as an
        integer value. The intention of the quality attribute for video is to
        specify a non-default trade-off between frame-rate and still-image
        quality. For video, the value is in the range 0 to 10, with the
        following suggested meaning: </t>
<table>
<name>Encoding Quality Values</name>
	<tbody>
	<tr>
		<td>10</td>
		<td>the best still-image quality the compression scheme can give.</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>5</td>
		<td>the default behavior given no quality suggestion.</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>0</td>
		<td>the worst still-image quality the codec designer thinks is still usable.</td>
	</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>
      </section>
      <section anchor="fmtp" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>fmtp (Format Parameters)</name>
<dl>
        <dt>Name:</dt><dd>fmtp</dd>
        <dt>Value:</dt><dd>fmtp-value</dd>
        <dt>Usage Level:</dt><dd>media</dd>
        <dt>Charset Dependent:</dt><dd>no</dd>
</dl>
        <t>Syntax:</t>
        <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
      fmtp-value = fmt SP format-specific-params
      format-specific-params = byte-string
        ; Notes:
        ; - The format parameters are media type parameters and
        ;   need to reflect their syntax.
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>Example:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="sdp"><![CDATA[
      a=fmtp:96 profile-level-id=42e016;max-mbps=108000;max-fs=3600
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>This attribute allows parameters that are specific to a particular
        format to be conveyed in a way that SDP does not have to understand
        them. The format must be one of the formats specified for the media.
        Format-specific parameters, semicolon separated, may be any set of parameters required to be
        conveyed by SDP and given unchanged to the media tool that will use
        this format. At most one instance of this attribute is allowed for
        each format.</t>
        <t>The "a=fmtp:" attribute may be used to specify parameters for any
        protocol and format that defines use of such parameters.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>SDP is frequently used with the <xref target="RFC3261" format="default">Session
      Initiation Protocol</xref> using the <xref target="RFC3264" format="default">offer/answer
      model</xref> to agree on parameters for unicast sessions. When used in
      this manner, the security considerations of those protocols apply.</t>
      <t>SDP is a session description format that describes multimedia
      sessions. Entities receiving and acting upon an SDP message <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
      aware that a session description cannot be trusted unless it has been
      obtained by an authenticated and integrity-protected transport protocol from a known and trusted
      source. Many different transport protocols may be used to distribute
      session descriptions, and the nature of the authentication and integrity protection  will differ
      from transport to transport. For some transports, security features are
      often not deployed. In case a session description has not been obtained
      in a trusted manner, the endpoint <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> exercise care because, among
      other attacks, the media sessions received may not be the intended ones,
      the destination to where the media is sent  may not be the expected one, any
      of the parameters of the session may be incorrect, or the media security
      may be compromised. It is up to the endpoint to make a sensible decision,
      taking into account the security risks of the application and the user
      preferences - the endpoint may decide to ask the user whether or not to accept the
      session.</t>
      <t>On receiving a session description over an unauthenticated transport
      mechanism or from an untrusted party, software parsing the session description
      should take a few precautions. Similar concerns apply if integrity protection is not in place. 
      Session descriptions contain information
      required to start software on the receiver's system. Software that
      parses a session description <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be able to start other software
      except that which is specifically configured as appropriate software to
      participate in multimedia sessions. It is normally considered
      inappropriate for software parsing a session description to start, on a
      user's system, software that is appropriate to participate in multimedia
      sessions, without the user first being informed that such software will
      be started and giving the user's consent. Thus, a session description
      arriving by session announcement, email, session invitation, or WWW page
      <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> deliver the user into an interactive multimedia session unless
      the user has explicitly pre-authorized such action. As it is not always
      simple to tell whether or not a session is interactive, applications
      that are unsure should assume sessions are interactive.
      Software processing URLs contained in session descriptions should also 
      heed the security considerations identified in <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>In this specification, there are no attributes that would allow the
      recipient of a session description to be informed to start multimedia
      tools in a mode where they default to transmitting. Under some
      circumstances it might be appropriate to define such attributes. If this
      is done, an application parsing a session description containing such
      attributes <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> either ignore them or inform the user that joining
      this session will result in the automatic transmission of multimedia
      data. The default behavior for an unknown attribute is to ignore
      it.</t>
      <t>In certain environments, it has become common for intermediary
      systems to intercept and analyze session descriptions contained within
      other signaling protocols. This is done for a range of purposes,
      including but not limited to opening holes in firewalls to allow media
      streams to pass, or to mark, prioritize, or block traffic selectively.
      In some cases, such intermediary systems may modify the session
      description, for example, to have the contents of the session
      description match NAT bindings dynamically created. These behaviors are
      <bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14> unless the session description is conveyed in such a
      manner that allows the intermediary system to conduct proper checks to
      establish the authenticity of the session description, and the authority
      of its source to establish such communication sessions. SDP by itself
      does not include sufficient information to enable these checks: they
      depend on the encapsulating protocol (e.g., SIP or RTSP).
      The use of some procedures and SDP extensions 
      (e.g., Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) <xref target="RFC8445" format="default"/> 
      and ICE-SIP-SDP <xref target="RFC8839" format="default"/>) 
      may avoid the need for intermediaries to modify SDP.</t>
      <t>SDP <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used to convey keying material (e.g., using 
      the "a=crypto:" attribute <xref target="RFC4568" format="default"/>) unless it can be guaranteed that the channel over 
      which the SDP is delivered is both private and authenticated.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>The "application/sdp" Media Type</name>
        <t>One media type registration from <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/> has been 
        updated, as defined below.</t>

<dl>
   <dt>Type name:</dt><dd>application</dd>

   <dt>Subtype name:</dt><dd>sdp</dd>

   <dt>Required parameters:</dt><dd>None.</dd>

   <dt>Optional parameters:</dt><dd>None.</dd>

   <dt>Encoding considerations:</dt><dd>8-bit text.
      SDP files are primarily UTF-8 format text. The "a=charset:"
      attribute may be used to signal the presence of other character
      sets in certain parts of an SDP file (see <xref target="attrs"/> of RFC
      8866).  Arbitrary binary content cannot be directly
      represented in SDP.</dd>

   <dt>Security considerations:</dt><dd>
      See <xref target="security"/> of RFC 8866.</dd>

   <dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt><dd>
      See RFC 8866.</dd>

   <dt>Published specification:</dt><dd>
      See RFC 8866.</dd>

   <dt>Applications which use this media type:</dt><dd><t><br/>
      Voice over IP, video teleconferencing, streaming media, instant
      messaging, among others.  See also <xref target="usage_examples"/> of RFC 8866.</t></dd>
              
   <dt>Fragment identifier considerations:</dt><dd>None</dd>

   <dt>Additional information:</dt><dd><t><br/></t>
  <dl spacing="compact">
   <dt>Deprecated alias names for this type:</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
   <dt>Magic number(s):</dt><dd>None.</dd>
   <dt>File extension(s):</dt><dd>The extension ".sdp" is commonly used.</dd>
   <dt>Macintosh File Type Code(s):</dt><dd>"sdp"</dd>
 </dl>
</dd>

   <dt>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:</dt><dd><br/>
      IETF MMUSIC working group<br/>&lt;mmusic@ietf.org&gt;</dd>

   <dt>Intended usage:</dt><dd>COMMON</dd>
              
   <dt>Restrictions on usage:</dt><dd>None</dd>

   <dt>Author/Change controller:</dt><dd><br/>
      Authors of RFC 8866<br/>
      IETF MMUSIC working group delegated from the IESG
 </dd>

</dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="SDP_Parameters" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Registration of SDP Parameters with IANA</name>
        <t>This document specifies IANA parameter registries
        for six named SDP subfields. Using
        the terminology in the SDP specification Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF), they
        are &lt;media&gt;, &lt;proto&gt;, &lt;attribute-name&gt;, &lt;bwtype&gt;, &lt;nettype&gt;, and
        &lt;addrtype&gt;.</t>
        <t>This document also replaces and updates the definitions of all those parameters previously
        defined by <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>IANA has changed all references to RFC 4566 in these registries to instead refer to this document.</t>
        <t>The contact name and email address for all parameters registered in this document is: </t>
          <t indent="3">The IETF MMUSIC working group &lt;mmusic@ietf.org&gt; or its successor as designated by the IESG.</t>

        <t>All of these registries have a common format:</t>
<table>
<name>Common Format for SDP Registries</name>
        <tbody>
        <tr>
                <th>Type</th>
                <th>SDP Name</th>
                <th>[other fields]</th>
                <th>Reference</th>
        </tr>
        </tbody>
</table>
        <section anchor="Registration_Procedure" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Registration Procedure</name>
          <t>A specification document that defines values for SDP &lt;media&gt;, &lt;proto&gt;, 
          &lt;attribute-name&gt;, &lt;bwtype&gt;, &lt;nettype&gt;, and &lt;addrtype&gt; parameters <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          include the following information: 
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>Contact name</li>
            <li>Contact email address</li>
            <li>Name being defined (as it will appear in SDP)</li>
            <li>Type of name (&lt;media&gt;, &lt;proto&gt;, &lt;attribute-name&gt;, &lt;bwtype&gt;, &lt;nettype&gt;,
              or &lt;addrtype&gt;)</li>
            <li>A description of the purpose of the defined name</li>
            <li>A stable reference to the document containing this
              information and the definition of the value.
              (This will typically be an RFC number.)</li>
          </ul>
          <t>The subsections below specify what other information (if any) must be specified 
          for particular parameters, and what other fields are to be included 
          in the registry.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="MediaTypes" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Media Types (&lt;media&gt;)</name>
          <t>The set of media types is intended to be small and <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be
          extended except under rare circumstances. The same rules should
          apply for media names as well as for top-level media types, and where
          possible the same name should be registered for SDP as for MIME. For
          media other than existing top-level media types, a Standards Track
          RFC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be produced for a new top-level media type to be
          registered, and the registration <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> provide good justification why
          no existing media name is appropriate (the "Standards Action" policy
          of <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>).</t>
          <t>This memo registers the media types "audio", "video", "text",
          "application", and "message".</t>
          <t>Note: The media types "control" and "data" were listed as valid
          in an early version of this specification <xref target="RFC2327" format="default"/>; however, their
          semantics were never fully specified, and they are not widely used.
          These media types have been removed in this specification, although
          they still remain valid media type capabilities for a SIP user agent
          as defined in <xref target="RFC3840" format="default"/>. If these media types are
          considered useful in the future, a Standards Track RFC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
          produced to document their use. Until that is done, applications
          <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> use these types and <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> declare support for them
          in SIP capabilities declarations (even though they exist in the
          registry created by <xref target="RFC3840" format="default"/>). Also note that <xref target="RFC6466" format="default"/> defined the "image" media type.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="protoreg" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Transport Protocols (&lt;proto&gt;)</name>
          <t>The &lt;proto&gt; subfield describes the transport protocol used.
          The registration procedure for this registry is "RFC Required".</t>
          <t>This document registers two values: 
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>"RTP/AVP" is a reference to <xref target="RFC3550" format="default"/>
                   used under the <xref target="RFC3551" format="default">RTP Profile for Audio and
                   Video Conferences with Minimal Control</xref> running over UDP/IP.</li>
            <li>"udp" indicates direct use of UDP.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>New transport protocols <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be defined, and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered with IANA.
          Registrations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reference an RFC describing the protocol. Such an
          RFC <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be Experimental or Informational, although it is preferable
          that it be Standards Track. The RFC defining a new protocol <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> define the rules
          by which the &lt;fmt&gt; (see below) namespace is managed.</t>
          <t>&lt;proto&gt; names starting with "RTP/" <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be used for
          defining transport protocols that are profiles of RTP. 
          For example, a profile whose short name is "XYZ" would be denoted by 
          a &lt;proto&gt; subfield of "RTP/XYZ".</t>
          <t>Each transport protocol, defined by the &lt;proto&gt; subfield, has an
          associated &lt;fmt&gt; namespace that describes the media formats that may
          be conveyed by that protocol. Formats cover all the possible
          encodings that could be transported in a multimedia session.</t>
          <t>RTP payload formats under the "RTP/AVP" and other "RTP/*" profiles
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the payload type number as their &lt;fmt&gt; value. If the
          payload type number is dynamically assigned by this session
          description, an additional "a=rtpmap:" attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included to
          specify the format name and parameters as defined by the media type
          registration for the payload format. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that other
          RTP profiles that are registered (in combination with RTP) as SDP
          transport protocols specify the same rules for the &lt;fmt&gt;
          namespace.</t>
          <t>For the "udp" protocol, the allowed &lt;fmt&gt; values are media subtypes
          from the IANA Media Types registry. The media type and subtype combination 
          &lt;media&gt;/&lt;fmt&gt; specifies the format of the body of UDP packets.
          Use of an existing media subtype for the format is encouraged. If no suitable media
          subtype exists, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that a new one be registered
          through the IETF process <xref target="RFC6838" format="default"/> by production of,
          or reference to, a Standards Track RFC that defines the format.</t>
          <t>For other protocols, formats <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be registered according to the
          rules of the associated &lt;proto&gt; specification.</t>
          <t>Registrations of new formats <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> specify which transport
          protocols they apply to.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="AttributeNames" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Attribute Names (&lt;attribute-name&gt;)</name>
          <t>Attribute-field names (&lt;attribute-name&gt;) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered with
          IANA and documented to avoid any issues due to
          conflicting attribute definitions under the same name. 
          (While unknown attributes in
          SDP are simply ignored, conflicting ones that fragment the
          protocol are a serious problem.)</t>
          <t>The format of the &lt;attribute-name&gt; registry is:</t>
<table anchor="attRegformat">
<name>Format of the &lt;attribute-name&gt; Registry</name>
        <tbody>
        <tr>
                <th>Type</th>
                <th>SDP Name</th>
                <th>Usage Level</th>
                <th>Mux Category</th>
                <th>Reference</th>
        </tr>
        </tbody>
</table>

          <t>For example, the attribute "a=lang:", which is defined for both
        session and media level, will be listed in the new registry as
        follows:</t>
<table anchor="attReg">
        <name>&lt;attribute-name&gt; Registry Example</name>
        <thead> 
        <tr>
                <th>Type</th>
                <th>SDP Name</th>
                <th>Usage Level</th>
                <th>Mux Category</th>
                <th>Reference</th>
        </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
        <tr>
                 <td>attribute</td>
                 <td>lang</td>
                 <td>session, media</td>
                 <td>TRANSPORT</td>
                 <td>[RFC8866]
                     <xref target="RFC8859" format="default"/>
                 </td>
        </tr>
        </tbody>
</table>
          <t>This one &lt;attribute-name&gt; registry combines all of the previous usage-level-specific "att-field" 
          registries, including updates made by <xref target="RFC8859" format="default"/>,  
          and renames the "att-field" registry to the
          "attribute-name (formerly "att-field")" registry. 
          IANA has completed the necessary reformatting.</t>
          <t><xref target="attrs" format="default"/> of this document replaces the initial set of
          attribute definitions made by <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/>.
          IANA has updated the registry accordingly.</t>
          <t>Documents can define new attributes and can also extend the
          definitions of previously defined attributes.</t>
          <section anchor="newatt" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>New Attributes</name>
            <t>New attribute registrations are accepted according to the
            "Specification Required" policy of <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>,
            provided that the specification includes the following
            information:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>Contact name</li>
              <li>Contact email address</li>
              <li>Attribute name: the name of the attribute that will appear
                in SDP. This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to the definition of
                &lt;attribute-name&gt;.</li>
              <li>Attribute syntax: for a value attribute (see <xref target="attribspec" format="default"/>),
                an ABNF definition of the attribute value &lt;attribute-value&gt;
                syntax (see <xref target="abnf" format="default"/>) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provided.
                The syntax <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> follow the rule form per 
                <xref target="RFC5234" section="2.2" sectionFormat="of" format="default"/> 
                and <xref target="RFC7405" format="default"/>. This <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> define the allowable
                values that the attribute might take. It <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also define an
                extension method for the addition of future values. For a
                property attribute, the ABNF definition is omitted as the
                property attribute takes no values.</li>
              <li>Attribute semantics: for a value attribute, a semantic
                description of the values that the attribute might take <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
                be provided. The usage of a property attribute is described
                under Purpose below.</li>
              <li>Attribute value: the name of an ABNF syntax rule defining
                the syntax of the value. Absence of a rule name indicates that
                the attribute takes no values. Enclosing the rule name in "["
                and "]" indicates that a value is optional.</li>
              <li>Usage level: the usage level(s) of the attribute. 
                This <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be one or more of the following: 
                session, media, source, dcsa, and dcsa(subprotocol). 
                For a definition of source-level attributes, see <xref target="RFC5576" format="default"/>. 
                For a definition of dcsa attributes see
                <xref target="RFC8864" format="default"/>.</li>
              <li>Charset dependent: this <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "Yes" or "No" depending
                on whether the attribute value is subject to the "a=charset:" attribute.</li>
              <li>Purpose: an explanation of the purpose and usage of the
                attribute.</li>
              <li>O/A procedures: offer/answer procedures as explained in
                <xref target="RFC3264" format="default"/>.</li>
              <li>Mux Category: this <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> indicate one of the following
                categories: NORMAL, NOT RECOMMENDED, IDENTICAL, SUM, TRANSPORT,
                INHERIT, IDENTICAL-PER-PT, SPECIAL, or TBD as defined by
                <xref target="RFC8859" format="default"/>.</li>
              <li>Reference: a reference to the specification defining the
                attribute.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>The above is the minimum that IANA will accept. Attributes that
            are expected to see widespread use and interoperability <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
            documented with a Standards Track RFC that specifies the attribute
            more precisely.</t>
            <t>Submitters of registrations should ensure that the
            specification is in the spirit of SDP attributes, most notably
            that the attribute is platform independent in the sense that it
            makes no implicit assumptions about operating systems and does not
            name specific pieces of software in a manner that might inhibit
            interoperability.</t>
            <t>Submitters of registrations should also carefully choose the
            attribute usage level. They should not choose only "session" when
            the attribute can have different values when media is
            disaggregated, i.e., when each "m=" section has its own IP address
            on a different endpoint. In that case, the attribute type chosen
            should be "session, media" or "media" (depending on desired semantics). 
            The default rule is that for all new
            SDP attributes that can occur both in session and media level, the
            media level overrides the session level. When this is not the case
            for a new SDP attribute, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be explicitly stated.</t>
            <t>IANA has registered the initial set of attribute names
            (&lt;attribute-name&gt; values) with definitions as in <xref target="attrs" format="default"/> 
            of this memo (these definitions replace those in
            <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/>).</t>
          </section>
          <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Updates to Existing Attributes</name>
            <t>Updated attribute registrations are accepted according to the
            "Specification Required" policy of <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>.</t>
            <t>The Designated Expert reviewing the update is requested to evaluate
            whether the update is compatible with the prior intent and use of the attribute,
            and whether the new document is of sufficient maturity and authority in
            relation to the prior document.
            </t>
            <t>The specification updating the attribute (for
            example, by adding a new value) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> update registration
            information items from  <xref target="newatt" format="default"/> according
            to the following constraints:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>Contact name: a name for an entity 
                responsible for the update <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provided.</li>
              <li>Contact email address: an email address for an entity 
                responsible for the update <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provided.</li>
              <li>Attribute name: <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provided and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be changed.
                Otherwise it is a new attribute.</li>
              <li>Attribute syntax: the existing rule syntax with the syntax
                extensions <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provided if there is a change to the
                syntax. A revision to an existing attribute usage <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> extend
                the syntax of an attribute, but <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be backward
                compatible.</li>
              <li>Attribute semantics: a semantic description of new
                additional attribute values or a semantic extension of
                existing values. Existing attribute values semantics <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only
                be extended in a backward compatible manner.</li>
              <li>Usage level: updates <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> only add additional levels.</li>
              <li>Charset dependent: <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be changed.</li>
              <li>Purpose: <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be extended according to the updated
                usage.</li>
              <li>O/A procedures: <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be updated in a backward compatible
                manner and/or it applies to a new usage level only.</li>
              <li>Mux Category: no change unless from "TBD" to another value 
                (see <xref target="RFC8859" format="default"/>.
                It <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also change if media level is being added to the
                definition of an attribute that previously did not include
                it.</li>
              <li>Reference: a new (additional or replacement) reference <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provided.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>Items <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be omitted if there is no impact to them as a
            result of the attribute update.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Bandwidth Specifiers (&lt;bwtype&gt;)</name>
          <t>A proliferation of bandwidth specifiers is strongly
          discouraged.</t>
          <t>New bandwidth specifiers (&lt;bwtype&gt; subfield values) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered
          with IANA. The submission <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reference a Standards Track RFC
          specifying the semantics of the bandwidth specifier precisely, and
          indicating when it should be used, and why the existing registered
          bandwidth specifiers do not suffice.</t>
          <t>The RFC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> specify the Mux Category for this value as defined by
          <xref target="RFC8859" format="default"/>.</t>
          <t>The format of the &lt;bwtype&gt; registry is:</t>
<table anchor="bwtypeRegformat">
        <name>Format of the &lt;bwtype&gt; Registry</name>
        <tbody>
        <tr>
                <th>Type</th>
                <th>SDP Name</th>
                <th>Mux Category</th>
                <th>Reference</th>
        </tr>
        </tbody>
</table>
          <t>IANA has updated the &lt;bwtype&gt; registry entries for the 
          bandwidth specifiers "CT" and "AS" with the
          definitions in <xref target="bandwidthInfo" format="default"/> of this memo (these definitions replace
          those in <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/>).</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="nettypereg" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Network Types (&lt;nettype&gt;)</name>
          <t>Network type "IN", representing the Internet, 
          is defined in <xref target="origin" format="default"/> and 
          <xref target="connection-information" format="default"/> of this memo
          (this definition replaces that in <xref target="RFC4566" format="default"/>).</t>
          <t>To enable SDP to reference a new non-Internet environment,
          a new network type (&lt;nettype&gt; subfield value) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered
          with IANA. The registration is subject to the "RFC Required" policy 
          of <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>. Although non-Internet environments are
          not normally the preserve of IANA, there may be circumstances when
          an Internet application needs to interoperate with a non-Internet
          application, such as when gatewaying an Internet telephone call into
          the Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN). The number of network
          types should be small and should be rarely extended. A new network type
          registration <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reference an RFC that gives details of the network
          type and the address type(s) that may be used with it.</t>
          <t>The format of the &lt;nettype&gt; registry is:</t>
<table anchor="nettypeRegformat">
        <name>Format of the &lt;nettype&gt; Registry</name>
        <tbody>
        <tr>
                <th>Type</th>
                <th>SDP Name</th>
                <th>Usable addrtype Values</th>
                <th>Reference</th>
        </tr>
        </tbody>
</table>
          <t>IANA has updated the &lt;nettype&gt; registry to this
        new format. The following is the updated content of the registry: </t>
<table anchor="nettypeReg">
	<name>Content of the &lt;nettype&gt; registry</name>
	<thead>
	<tr>
		<th>Type</th>
		<th>SDP Name</th>
		<th>Usable addrtype Values</th>
		<th>Reference</th>
	</tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	<tr>
		<td>nettype</td>
		<td>IN</td>
		<td>IP4, IP6</td>
		<td>[RFC8866]</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>nettype</td>
		<td>TN</td>
		<td>RFC2543</td>
		<td><xref target="RFC2848" format="default"/></td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>nettype</td>
		<td>ATM</td>
		<td>NSAP, GWID, E164</td>
		<td><xref target="RFC3108" format="default"/></td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>nettype</td>
		<td>PSTN</td>
		<td>E164</td>
		<td><xref target="RFC7195" format="default"/></td>
	</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>
          <t>Note that both <xref target="RFC7195" format="default"/> 
          and <xref target="RFC3108" format="default"/> registered "E164" as an
          address type, although <xref target="RFC7195" format="default"/> mentions that the "E164" address type
          has a different context for ATM and PSTN networks.</t>
        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Address Types (&lt;addrtype&gt;)</name>
          <t>New address types (&lt;addrtype&gt;) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be registered with IANA. The
          registration is subject to the "RFC Required" policy
          of <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>. A new address type registration
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reference an RFC, giving details of the syntax of the address
          type. Address types are not expected to be registered
          frequently.</t>
          <t><xref target="connection-information" format="default"/> of this document gives 
          new definitions of address types "IP4" and "IP6".</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Encryption Key Access Methods (OBSOLETE)</name>
        <t>The IANA previously maintained a table of SDP encryption key access
        method ("enckey") names. This table is obsolete, since the "k=" line
        is not extensible. New registrations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be accepted.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="abnf" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SDP Grammar</name>
      <t>This section provides an Augmented BNF grammar for SDP. ABNF is
      defined in <xref target="RFC5234" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC7405" format="default"/>.</t>

      <sourcecode type="abnf" name="sdp-syntax.abnf"><![CDATA[
; SDP Syntax
session-description = version-field
                      origin-field
                      session-name-field
                      [information-field]
                      [uri-field]
                      *email-field
                      *phone-field
                      [connection-field]
                      *bandwidth-field
                      1*time-description
                      [key-field]
                      *attribute-field
                      *media-description

version-field =       %s"v" "=" 1*DIGIT CRLF
                          ;this memo describes version 0

origin-field =       %s"o" "=" username SP sess-id SP sess-version SP
                         nettype SP addrtype SP unicast-address CRLF

session-name-field =  %s"s" "=" text CRLF

information-field =   %s"i" "=" text CRLF

uri-field =           %s"u" "=" uri CRLF

email-field =         %s"e" "=" email-address CRLF

phone-field =         %s"p" "=" phone-number CRLF

connection-field =    %s"c" "=" nettype SP addrtype SP
                          connection-address CRLF
                          ;a connection field must be present
                          ;in every media description or at the
                          ;session level

bandwidth-field =     %s"b" "=" bwtype ":" bandwidth CRLF

time-description =    time-field
                          [repeat-description]

repeat-description =  1*repeat-field
                          [zone-field]

time-field =          %s"t" "=" start-time SP stop-time CRLF

repeat-field =        %s"r" "=" repeat-interval SP typed-time
                          1*(SP typed-time) CRLF

zone-field =          %s"z" "=" time SP ["-"] typed-time
                          *(SP time SP ["-"] typed-time) CRLF

key-field =           %s"k" "=" key-type CRLF

attribute-field =     %s"a" "=" attribute CRLF

media-description =   media-field
                      [information-field]
                      *connection-field
                      *bandwidth-field
                      [key-field]
                      *attribute-field

media-field =         %s"m" "=" media SP port ["/" integer]
                          SP proto 1*(SP fmt) CRLF

; sub-rules of 'o='
username =            non-ws-string
                      ;pretty wide definition, but doesn't
                      ;include space

sess-id =             1*DIGIT
                      ;should be unique for this username/host

sess-version =        1*DIGIT

nettype =             token
                      ;typically "IN"

addrtype =            token
                      ;typically "IP4" or "IP6"

; sub-rules of 'u='
uri =                 URI-reference
                      ; see RFC 3986

; sub-rules of 'e=', see RFC 5322 for definitions
email-address        = address-and-comment / dispname-and-address
                       / addr-spec
address-and-comment  = addr-spec 1*SP "(" 1*email-safe ")"
dispname-and-address = 1*email-safe 1*SP "<" addr-spec ">"

; sub-rules of 'p='
phone-number =        phone *SP "(" 1*email-safe ")" /
                      1*email-safe "<" phone ">" /
                      phone

phone =               ["+"] DIGIT 1*(SP / "-" / DIGIT)

; sub-rules of 'c='
connection-address =  multicast-address / unicast-address

; sub-rules of 'b='
bwtype =              token

bandwidth =           1*DIGIT

; sub-rules of 't='
start-time =          time / "0"

stop-time =           time / "0"

time =                POS-DIGIT 9*DIGIT
                      ; Decimal representation of time in
                      ; seconds since January 1, 1900 UTC.  
                      ; The representation is an unbounded 
                      ; length field containing at least 
                      ; 10 digits. Unlike some representations
                      ; used elsewhere, time in SDP does not 
                      ; wrap in the year 2036.

; sub-rules of 'r=' and 'z='
repeat-interval =     POS-DIGIT *DIGIT [fixed-len-time-unit]

typed-time =          1*DIGIT [fixed-len-time-unit]

fixed-len-time-unit = %s"d" / %s"h" / %s"m" / %s"s"
; NOTE: These units are case-sensitive.

; sub-rules of 'k='
key-type =            %s"prompt" /
                      %s"clear:" text /
                      %s"base64:" base64 /
                      %s"uri:" uri
                      ; NOTE: These names are case-sensitive.

base64      =         *base64-unit [base64-pad]
base64-unit =         4base64-char
base64-pad  =         2base64-char "==" / 3base64-char "="
base64-char =         ALPHA / DIGIT / "+" / "/"

; sub-rules of 'a='
attribute =           (attribute-name ":" attribute-value) / 
                      attribute-name

attribute-name =      token

attribute-value =     byte-string

att-field =           attribute-name ; for backward compatibility 

; sub-rules of 'm='
media =               token
                      ;typically "audio", "video", "text", "image"
                      ;or "application"

fmt =                 token
                      ;typically an RTP payload type for audio
                      ;and video media

proto  =              token *("/" token)
                      ;typically "RTP/AVP", "RTP/SAVP", "udp",
                      ;or "RTP/SAVPF"

port =                1*DIGIT

; generic sub-rules: addressing
unicast-address =     IP4-address / IP6-address / FQDN / extn-addr

multicast-address =   IP4-multicast / IP6-multicast / FQDN
                      / extn-addr

IP4-multicast =       m1 3( "." decimal-uchar )
                      "/" ttl [ "/" numaddr ]
                      ; IP4 multicast addresses may be in the
                      ; range 224.0.0.0 to 239.255.255.255

m1 =                  ("22" ("4"/"5"/"6"/"7"/"8"/"9")) /
                      ("23" DIGIT )

IP6-multicast =       IP6-address [ "/" numaddr ]
                      ; IP6 address starting with FF

numaddr =             integer
            
ttl =                 (POS-DIGIT *2DIGIT) / "0"

FQDN =                4*(alpha-numeric / "-" / ".")
                      ; fully qualified domain name as specified
                      ; in RFC 1035 (and updates)

IP4-address =         b1 3("." decimal-uchar)

b1 =                  decimal-uchar
                      ; less than "224"

IP6-address =                                      6( h16 ":" ) ls32
                      /                       "::" 5( h16 ":" ) ls32
                      / [               h16 ] "::" 4( h16 ":" ) ls32
                      / [ *1( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::" 3( h16 ":" ) ls32
                      / [ *2( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::" 2( h16 ":" ) ls32
                      / [ *3( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"    h16 ":"   ls32
                      / [ *4( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"              ls32
                      / [ *5( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"              h16
                      / [ *6( h16 ":" ) h16 ] "::"

h16 =                 1*4HEXDIG

ls32 =                ( h16 ":" h16 ) / IP4-address

; Generic for other address families
extn-addr =      non-ws-string

; generic sub-rules: datatypes
text =                byte-string
                      ;default is to interpret this as UTF8 text.
                      ;ISO 8859-1 requires "a=charset:ISO-8859-1"
                      ;session-level attribute to be used

byte-string =         1*(%x01-09/%x0B-0C/%x0E-FF)
                      ;any byte except NUL, CR, or LF

non-ws-string =       1*(VCHAR/%x80-FF)
                      ;string of visible characters

token-char =          ALPHA / DIGIT
                              / "!" / "#" / "$" / "%" / "&"
                              / "'" ; (single quote)
                              / "*" / "+" / "-" / "." / "^" / "_"
                              / "`" ; (Grave accent)
                              / "{" / "|" / "}" / "~"

token =               1*(token-char)

email-safe =          %x01-09/%x0B-0C/%x0E-27/%x2A-3B/%x3D/%x3F-FF
                      ;any byte except NUL, CR, LF, or the quoting
                      ;characters ()<>

integer =             POS-DIGIT *DIGIT

zero-based-integer = "0" / integer

non-zero-int-or-real = integer / non-zero-real

non-zero-real = zero-based-integer "." *DIGIT POS-DIGIT

; generic sub-rules: primitives
alpha-numeric =       ALPHA / DIGIT

POS-DIGIT =           %x31-39 ; 1 - 9

decimal-uchar =       DIGIT
                      / POS-DIGIT DIGIT
                      / ("1" 2(DIGIT))
                      / ("2" ("0"/"1"/"2"/"3"/"4") DIGIT)
                      / ("2" "5" ("0"/"1"/"2"/"3"/"4"/"5"))

; external references:
ALPHA =               <ALPHA definition from RFC 5234>
DIGIT =               <DIGIT definition from RFC 5234>
CRLF =                <CRLF definition from RFC 5234>
HEXDIG =              <HEXDIG definition from RFC 5234>
SP =                  <SP definition from RFC 5234>
VCHAR =               <VCHAR definition from RFC 5234>
URI-reference =       <URI-reference definition from RFC 3986>
addr-spec =           <addr-spec definition from RFC 5322>
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
    <section anchor="changes" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Summary of Changes from RFC 4566</name>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Generally clarified and refined terminology. Aligned terms used in
   text with the ABNF. The terms &lt;attribute&gt;, &lt;att-field&gt;, and
   "att-field" are now &lt;attribute-name&gt;. The terms &lt;value&gt; and
   &lt;att-value&gt; are now &lt;attribute-value&gt;. The term "media" is now
   &lt;media&gt;. </li>
        <li>Identified now-obsolete items: "a=cat:" (<xref target="cat" format="default"/>), 
            "a=keywds:" (<xref target="keywds" format="default"/>), and "k=" 
            (<xref target="key-field" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Updated normative and informative references, and added references 
	       to additional relevant related RFCs.</li>
        <li>Reformatted the SDP Attributes section (<xref target="attrs" format="default"/>) for readability. 
	       The syntax of attribute values is now given in ABNF.</li>
        <li>Made mandatory the sending of RTCP with inactive media streams (<xref target="inactive" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Removed the section "Private Sessions". That section dated back to a time
	    when the primary use of SDP was with SAP (Session Announcement Protocol),
	    which has fallen out of use. Now the vast majority of uses of SDP is
	    for establishment of private sessions. The considerations for that are
	    covered in <xref target="security" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>Expanded and clarified the specification of the "a=lang:" (<xref target="lang" format="default"/>) 
	       and "a=sdplang:" (<xref target="sdplang" format="default"/>) attributes.</li>
        <li>Removed some references to SAP because it is no longer in widespread use.</li>
        <li>Changed the way &lt;fmt&gt; values for UDP transport are registered (<xref target="protoreg" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Changed the mechanism and documentation required for 
	       registering new attributes (<xref target="newatt" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Tightened up IANA registration procedures for extensions. 
	       Removed phone number and long-form name (<xref target="SDP_Parameters" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Expanded the IANA &lt;nettype&gt; registry to identify valid &lt;addrtype&gt; subfields (<xref target="nettypereg" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Reorganized the several IANA "att-field" registries 
	       into a single &lt;attribute-name&gt; registry (<xref target="AttributeNames" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>
		<t>Revised ABNF syntax (<xref target="abnf" format="default"/>) for clarity
                   and for alignment with text. Backward compatibility is 
                   maintained with a few exceptions.  Of particular note: </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>Revised the syntax of time descriptions ("t=", "r=", "z=") to 
               remove ambiguities. Clarified that "z=" only modifies the 
               immediately preceding "r=" lines. Made "z=" without a 
	       preceding "r=" a syntax error (<xref target="tzadj" format="default"/>). 
	       (This is incompatible with certain aberrant usage.)</li>
            <li>Updated the "IP6-address" and "IP6-multicast" rules, consistent 
               with the syntax in <xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/>, mirroring a bug fix made to 
               <xref target="RFC3261" format="default"/> by <xref target="RFC5954" format="default"/>. 
	       Removed rules that were unused as a result of this change.</li>
            <li>The "att-field" rule has been renamed "attribute-name" because
               elsewhere "*-field" always refers to a complete line. However,
               the rulename "att-field" remains defined as a synonym for
               backward compatibility with references from other RFCs.</li>
            <li>The "att-value" rule has been renamed "attribute-value".</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Revised normative statements that were redundant with ABNF syntax,
            making the text non-normative.</li>

        <li>Revised IPv4 unicast and multicast addresses in the 
	       example SDP descriptions per <xref target="RFC5735"/> and <xref
	       target="RFC5771"/>.</li>
        <li>Changed some examples to use IPv6 addresses, and added additional
            examples using IPv6.</li>
        <li>Incorporated case-insensitivity rules from <xref target="RFC4855" format="default"/>.</li>
        <li>Revised sections that incorrectly referenced NTP (<xref target="origin" format="default"/>, 
            <xref target="timing" format="default"/>, <xref target="repeattime" format="default"/>, and 
            <xref target="tzadj" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Clarified the explanation of the impact and use of the "a=charset:" attribute
            (<xref target="charset" format="default"/>).</li>
        <li>Revised the description of the "a=type:" attribute to remove implication that it
            sometimes changes the default media direction to something other than "a=sendrecv"
            (<xref target="type" format="default"/>).</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2848.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2978.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3108.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5576.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5890.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5952.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7195.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

  <reference anchor="RFC8864" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8864">
    <front>
      <title>Negotiation Data Channels Using the Session Description
 Protocol (SDP)</title>
      <author fullname="Keith Drage" initials="K." surname="Drage">
        <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
      </author>
      <author fullname="Raju Makaraju" initials="M." surname="Makaraju">
        <organization>Nokia</organization>
      </author>
      <author fullname="Richard Ejzak" initials="R." surname="Ejzak">
        <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
      </author>
      <author fullname="Jerome Marcon" initials="J." surname="Marcon">
        <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
      </author>
      <author fullname="Roni Even" initials="R." surname="Even" role="editor">
        <organization>Huawei</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="January" year="2021"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8864"/>
    <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8864"/>
  </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC8859" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8859">
          <front>
            <title>A Framework for Session Description Protocol (SDP)
            Attributes When Multiplexing</title>
            <author initials="S" surname="Nandakumar" fullname="Suhas Nandakumar">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2021"/>
          </front>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8859"/>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8859"/>

        </reference>

        <reference anchor="ISO.8859-1.1998">
          <front>
            <title>Information technology - 8-bit single byte coded graphic - character sets - Part 1: Latin alphabet No. 1, JTC1/SC2</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="" year="1998"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC Standard" value="8859-1"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="E164" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-E.164-201011-I/en">
          <front>
            <title>E.164 : The international public telecommunication numbering plan</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Telecommunication Union</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="November" year="2010"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ITU Recommendation" value="E.164"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>

        <name>Informative References</name>

<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2327.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2974.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3264.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3551.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3556.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3605.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3711.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3840.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3890.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4568.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4855.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5124.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5735.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5771.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5888.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6466.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6838.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7405.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7656.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7826.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8445.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5954.xml"/>

    <reference anchor="RFC8843" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8843">
      <front>
        <title>Negotiating Media Multiplexing Using the Session Description Protocol (SDP)</title>
        <author initials="C" surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="H" surname="Alvestrand" fullname="Harald Alvestrand">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="C" surname="Jennings" fullname="Cullen Jennings">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <date month="January" year="2021"/>
      </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8843"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8843"/>
    </reference>

<reference anchor='RFC8839' target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8839">
<front>
<title>Session Description Protocol (SDP) Offer/Answer Procedures for Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE)</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Petit-Huguenin' fullname='Marc Petit-Huguenin'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Nandakumar' fullname='Suhas Nandakumar'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Holmberg' fullname='Christer Holmberg'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Kernen' fullname='Ari Kernen'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Shpount' fullname='Roman Shpount'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month="January" year="2021"/>

</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8839"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8839"/>

</reference>

        <reference anchor="ITU.H332.1998" target="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.332-199809-I/en">
          <front>
            <title>H.332 : H.323 extended for loosely coupled conferences</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Telecommunication Union</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="September" year="1998"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ITU Recommendation" value="H.332"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Many people in the IETF Multiparty Multimedia Session Control
      (MMUSIC) working group have made comments and suggestions contributing
      to this document.</t>
      <t>In particular, we would like to thank the following people who contributed 
      to the creation of this document or one of its predecessor documents:
      <contact fullname="Adam Roach"/>, <contact fullname="Allison Mankin"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Bernie Hoeneisen"/>, <contact fullname="Bill Fenner"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Carsten Bormann"/>, <contact fullname="Eve Schooler"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Flemming Andreasen"/>, <contact fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Jrg Ott"/>, <contact fullname="John Elwell"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Jon Peterson"/>, <contact fullname="Jonathan Lennox"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg"/>, <contact fullname="Keith Drage"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Peter Parnes"/>, <contact fullname="Rob Lanphier"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Ross Finlayson"/>, <contact fullname="Sean Olson"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Spencer Dawkins"/>, <contact fullname="Steve Casner"/>, 
      <contact fullname="Steve Hanna"/>, <contact fullname="Van Jacobson"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
