<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" number="8661" 
docName="draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-ldp-interop-15"  
category="std" consensus="yes" submissionType="IETF" ipr="trust200902" 
obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" 
tocInclude="true" version="3">


  <front>
    <title abbrev="Segment Routing and LDP">Segment Routing MPLS Interworking with
    LDP</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8661"/>
    <author fullname="Ahmed Bashandy" initials="A." role="editor" surname="Bashandy">
      <organization>Individual</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>United States of America</street>
        </postal>
        <email>abashandy.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C." role="editor" surname="Filsfils">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Brussels</street>
          <street>Belgium</street>
        </postal>
        <email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S." surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Italy</street>
        </postal>
        <email>stefano@previdi.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Bruno Decraene" initials="B." surname="Decraene">
      <organization>Orange</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>France</street>
        </postal>
        <email>bruno.decraene@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stephane Litkowski" initials="S." surname="Litkowski">
      <organization>Orange</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>France</street>
        </postal>
        <email>slitkows.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2019"/>
<keyword>SR-MPLS
</keyword>
     <abstract>
       <t>A Segment Routing (SR) node steers a packet through a controlled set
       of instructions, called segments, by prepending the packet with an SR
       header. A segment can represent any instruction, topological or
      service based. SR allows enforcing a flow through any topological path
      while maintaining per-flow state only at the ingress node to the SR
      domain.</t>
      <t>The Segment Routing architecture can be directly applied to the MPLS
      data plane with no change in the forwarding plane. This document
      describes how Segment Routing MPLS operates in a network where LDP is
      deployed and in the case where SR-capable and non-SR-capable nodes
      coexist.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="sec-1" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Segment Routing, as described in <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>, can be used on top of the
      MPLS data plane without any modification as described in <xref target="RFC8660" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>Segment Routing control plane can coexist with current label
      distribution protocols such as LDP <xref target="RFC5036" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>This document outlines the mechanisms through which SR interworks
      with LDP in cases where a mix of SR-capable and non-SR-capable routers
      coexist within the same network and more precisely in the same routing
      domain.</t>
      <t><xref target="sec-2" format="default"/> describes the coexistence of SR with
      other MPLS control-plane protocols. <xref target="sec-4" format="default"/> documents
      the interworking between SR and LDP in the case of nonhomogeneous
      deployment. <xref target="sec-5" format="default"/> describes how a partial SR
      deployment can be used to provide SR benefits to LDP-based traffic
      including a possible application of SR in the context of interdomain
      MPLS use cases. <xref target="Appendix-A" format="default"/> documents a method to
      migrate from LDP to SR-based MPLS tunneling.</t>
      <t>Typically, an implementation will allow an operator to select
      (through configuration) which of the described modes of SR and LDP
      coexistence to use.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-2" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SR-LDP Ships-in-the-Night Coexistence</name>
      <t>"MPLS Control-Plane Client (MCC)" refers to any control-plane
      protocol installing forwarding entries in the MPLS data plane. SR, LDP
      <xref target="RFC5036" format="default"/>, RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC3209" format="default"/>, BGP <xref target="RFC8277" format="default"/>, etc., are examples of MCCs.</t>
      <t>An MCC, operating at Node N, must ensure that the incoming label it
      installs in the MPLS data plane of Node N has been uniquely allocated to
      itself.</t>
      <t>Segment Routing makes use of the Segment Routing Global Block (SRGB,
      as defined in <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>) for the
      label allocation. The use of the SRGB allows SR to coexist with any
      other MCC.</t>
      <t>This is clearly the case for the adjacency segment: it is a local
      label allocated by the label manager, as is the case for any MCC.</t>
      <t>This is clearly the case for the prefix segment: the label manager
      allocates the SRGB set of labels to the SR MCC client, and the operator
      ensures the unique allocation of each global prefix segment or label
      within the allocated SRGB set.</t>
      <t>Note that this static label-allocation capability of the label
      manager has existed for many years across several vendors and is
      therefore not new. Furthermore, note that the label manager's ability to
      statically allocate a range of labels to a specific application is not
      new either. This is required for MPLS-TP operation. In this case, the
      range is reserved by the label manager, and it is the MPLS-TP <xref target="RFC5960" format="default"/> Network Management System (acting as an MCC) that ensures the unique
      allocation of any label within the allocated range and the creation of
      the related MPLS forwarding entry.</t>

<t>Let us illustrate an example of ship-in-the-night (SIN) coexistence.
</t>
      <figure anchor="ref-sin-coexistence">
        <name>SIN Coexistence</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                           PE2          PE4
                             \          /
                       PE1----A----B---C---PE3
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>The EVEN VPN service is supported by PE2 and PE4 while the ODD VPN
      service is supported by PE1 and PE3. The operator wants to tunnel the
      ODD service via LDP and the EVEN service via SR.</t>
<t>This can be achieved in the following manner:
</t>
<ul>
<li>The operator configures PE1, PE2, PE3, and PE4 with respective loopbacks
192.0.2.201/32, 192.0.2.202/32, 192.0.2.203/32, and 192.0.2.204/32. These PEs
advertised their VPN routes with next hop set on their respective loopback
address.
</li>
<li>The operator configures A, B, C with respective loopbacks 192.0.2.1/32,
192.0.2.2/32, 192.0.2.3/32.
</li>
<li>The operator configures PE2, A, B, C, and PE4 with SRGB [100, 300].
</li>
<li>The operator attaches the respective Node Segment Identifiers (Node SIDs,
as defined in <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>), 202, 101, 102, 103,
and 204, to the loopbacks of nodes PE2, A, B, C, and PE4. The Node SIDs are
configured to request Penultimate Hop Popping.
</li>

<li>PE1, A, B, C, and PE3 are LDP capable.
</li>
<li>PE1 and PE3 are not SR capable.
</li>
</ul>
   
      <t>PE3 sends an ODD VPN route to PE1 with next-hop 192.0.2.203 and VPN
      label 10001.</t>
      <t>From an LDP viewpoint, PE1 received an LDP label binding (1037) for a
      Forwarding Equivalence Class (FEC) 192.0.2.203/32 from its next-hop A; A
      received an LDP label binding (2048) for that FEC from its next-hop B; B
      received an LDP label binding (3059) for that FEC from its next-hop C;
      and C received implicit NULL LDP binding from its next-hop PE3.</t>
      <t>As a result, PE1 sends its traffic to the ODD service route
      advertised by PE3 to next-hop A with two labels: the top label is 1037
      and the bottom label is 10001. Node A swaps 1037 with 2048 and forwards
      to B; B swaps 2048 with 3059 and forwards to C; C pops 3059 and forwards
      to PE3.</t>
      <t>PE4 sends an EVEN VPN route to PE2 with next-hop 192.0.2.204 and VPN
      label 10002.</t>
      <t>From an SR viewpoint, PE2 maps the IGP route 192.0.2.204/32 onto
      Node SID 204; Node A swaps 204 with 204 and forwards to B; B swaps 204
      with 204 and forwards to C; and C pops 204 and forwards to PE4.</t>
      <t>As a result, PE2 sends its traffic to the VPN service route
      advertised by PE4 to next-hop A with two labels: the top label is 204
      and the bottom label is 10002. Node A swaps 204 with 204 and forwards to
      B. B swaps 204 with 204 and forwards to C. C pops 204 and forwards to
      PE4.</t>
<t>The two modes of MPLS tunneling coexist.
</t>
<ul empty="false">
<li>The ODD service is tunneled from PE1 to PE3 through a continuous LDP LSP
traversing A, B, and C.
</li>
<li>The EVEN service is tunneled from PE2 to PE4 through a continuous SR node
segment traversing A, B, and C.
</li>
</ul>


      <section anchor="sec-2.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>MPLS2MPLS, MPLS2IP, and IP2MPLS Coexistence</name>
        <t>MPLS2MPLS refers to the forwarding behavior where a router receives
        a labeled packet and switches it out as a labeled packet. Several
        MPLS2MPLS entries may be installed in the data plane for the same
        prefix.</t>

<t>Let us examine A's MPLS forwarding table as an example:</t>

<ul empty="true"><li><t>Incoming label: 1037</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: 2048</li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: B</li>
 </ul>
 <t>Note: This entry is programmed by LDP for 192.0.2.203/32.</t>
</li>
</ul>

<ul empty="true"><li><t>Incoming label: 203</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: 203</li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: B</li>
 </ul>
 <t>Note: This entry is programmed by SR for 192.0.2.203/32.</t>
 </li>
</ul>

        <t>These two entries can coexist because their incoming label is
        unique. The uniqueness is guaranteed by the label manager allocation
        rules.</t>
        <t>The same applies for the MPLS2IP forwarding entries. MPLS2IP is the
        forwarding behavior where a router receives a labeled IPv4/IPv6 packet
        with one label only, pops the label, and switches the packet out as
        IPv4/IPv6. For IP2MPLS coexistence, refer to <xref target="sec-7.1" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-4" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SR and LDP Interworking</name>
      <t>This section analyzes the case where SR is available in one part of
      the network and LDP is available in another part. It describes how a
      continuous MPLS tunnel can be built throughout the network.</t>
      <figure anchor="ref-sr-and-ldp-interworking">
        <name>SR and LDP Interworking</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                          PE2            PE4
                            \            /
                     PE1----P5--P6--P7--P8---PE3

                     <-----SR---->
                               <------LDP------>
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
<t>Let us analyze the following example:
</t>
<ul>

<li>P6, P7, P8, PE4, and PE3 are LDP capable.
</li>
<li>PE1, PE2, P5, and P6 are SR capable. PE1, PE2, P5, and P6 are configured
with SRGB (100, 200) and with node segments 101, 102, 105, and 106, respectively.
</li>
<li>A service flow must be tunneled from PE1 to PE3 over a continuous MPLS
tunnel encapsulation; therefore, SR and LDP need to interwork.
</li>
</ul>

      <section anchor="sec-4.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>LDP to SR</name>
        <t>In this section, a right-to-left traffic flow is analyzed.</t>
        <t>PE3 has learned a service route whose next hop is PE1. PE3 has an
        LDP label binding from the next-hop P8 for the FEC "PE1". Therefore, PE3
        sends its service packet to P8 as per classic LDP behavior.</t>
        <t>P8 has an LDP label binding from its next-hop P7 for the FEC "PE1"
        and therefore, P8 forwards to P7 as per classic LDP behavior.</t>
        <t>P7 has an LDP label binding from its next-hop P6 for the FEC "PE1"
        and therefore, P7 forwards to P6 as per classic LDP behavior.</t>
        <t>P6 does not have an LDP binding from its next-hop P5 for the FEC
        "PE1". However, P6 has an SR node segment to the IGP route "PE1".
        Hence, P6 forwards the packet to P5 and swaps its local LDP label for
        FEC "PE1" by the equivalent node segment (i.e., 101).</t>
        <t>P5 pops 101 (assuming PE1 advertised its node segment 101 with the
        penultimate-pop flag set) and forwards to PE1.</t>
        <t>PE1 receives the tunneled packet and processes the service
        label.</t>
        <t>The end-to-end MPLS tunnel is built by stitching an LDP LSP from PE3 to P6
        and the related node segment from P6 to PE1.</t>
        <section anchor="sec-4.1.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>LDP to SR Behavior</name>
          <t>It has to be noted that no additional signaling or state is
          required in order to provide interworking in the direction LDP to
          SR.</t>
          <t>An SR node having LDP neighbors <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> create LDP bindings for each
          Prefix-SID learned in the SR domain by treating SR-learned labels as
          if they were learned through an LDP neighbor. In addition, for each
          FEC, the SR node stitches the incoming LDP label to the outgoing SR
          label. This has to be done in both LDP-independent and ordered label
          distribution control modes as defined in <xref target="RFC5036" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-4.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR to LDP</name>
        <t>In this section, the left-to-right traffic flow is analyzed.</t>
        <t>This section defines the Segment Routing Mapping Server (SRMS). The
        SRMS is an IGP node advertising mapping between Segment Identifiers
        (SID) and prefixes advertised by other IGP nodes. The SRMS uses a
        dedicated IGP extension (IS-IS, OSPFv2, and OSPFv3), which is protocol
        specific and defined in <xref target="RFC8665" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8666" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC8667" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>The SRMS function of an SR-capable router allows distribution of
        mappings for prefixes not locally attached to the advertising router
        and therefore allows advertisement of mappings on behalf of
        non-SR-capable routers.</t>
        <t>The SRMS is a control-plane-only function that may be located
        anywhere in the IGP flooding scope. At least one SRMS server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        exist in a routing domain to advertise Prefix-SIDs on behalf of non‑SR
        nodes, thereby allowing non-LDP routers to send and receive labeled
        traffic from LDP-only routers. Multiple SRMSes may be present in the
        same network (for redundancy). This implies that there are multiple
        ways a prefix-to-SID mapping can be advertised. Conflicts resulting
        from inconsistent advertisements are addressed by <xref target="RFC8660" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>The example depicted in <xref target="ref-sr-and-ldp-interworking" format="default"/> assumes that the operator
        configures P5 to act as a Segment Routing Mapping Server and
        advertises the following mappings: (P7, 107), (P8, 108), (PE3, 103),
        and (PE4, 104).</t>
        <t>The mappings advertised by one or more SRMSes result from local
        policy information configured by the operator.</t>
        <t>If PE3 had been SR capable, the operator would have configured PE3
        with node segment 103. Instead, as PE3 is not SR capable, the operator
        configures that policy at the SRMS and it is the latter that
        advertises the mapping.</t>
        <t>The Mapping Server Advertisements are only understood by SR-capable
        routers. The SR-capable routers install the related node segments in
        the MPLS data plane exactly like the node segments had been advertised
        by the nodes themselves.</t>
        <t>For example, PE1 installs the node segment 103 with next-hop P5
        exactly as if PE3 had advertised node segment 103.</t>
        <t>PE1 has a service route whose next hop is PE3. PE1 has a node
        segment for that IGP route: 103 with next-hop P5. Hence, PE1 sends its
        service packet to P5 with two labels: the bottom label is the service
        label and the top label is 103.</t>
        <t>P5 swaps 103 for 103 and forwards to P6.</t>
        <t>P6's next hop for the IGP route "PE3" is not SR capable (P7 does
        not advertise the SR capability). However, P6 has an LDP label binding
        from that next hop for the same FEC (e.g., LDP label 1037). Hence, P6
        swaps 103 for 1037 and forwards to P7.</t>
        <t>P7 swaps this label with the LDP label received from P8 and
        forwards to P8.</t>
        <t>P8 pops the LDP label and forwards to PE3.</t>
        <t>PE3 receives the tunneled packet and processes the service
        label.</t>
        <t>The end-to-end MPLS tunnel is built by stitching an SR node segment from
        PE1 to P6 and an LDP LSP from P6 to PE3.</t>
        <t>SR-mapping advertisement for a given prefix provides no information
        about Penultimate Hop Popping. Other mechanisms, such as IGP-specific
        mechanisms (<xref target="RFC8665" format="default"/>,
        <xref target="RFC8666" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC8667" format="default"/>), <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be
        used to determine the Penultimate Hop Popping in such case.</t>
        <aside>
<t>Note: In the previous example, Penultimate Hop Popping is not
        performed at the SR-LDP border for segment 103 (PE3), because none of
        the routers in the SR domain are Penultimate Hop for segment 103. In
        this case, P6 requires the presence of the segment 103 such as to map
        it to the LDP label 1037.</t>
	</aside>
        <section anchor="sec-4.2.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Segment Routing Mapping Server (SRMS)</name>
          <t>This section specifies the concept and externally visible
          functionality of a Segment Routing Mapping Server (SRMS).</t>
          <t>The purpose of SRMS functionality is to support the
          advertisement of Prefix-SIDs to a prefix without the need to
          explicitly advertise such assignment within a prefix reachability
          advertisement. Examples of explicit Prefix-SID Advertisement are the
          Prefix-SID sub-TLVs defined in <xref target="RFC8665" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8666" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC8667" format="default"/>.</t>
          <t>The SRMS functionality allows assigning of Prefix-SIDs to
          prefixes owned by non-SR-capable routers as well as to prefixes
          owned by SR-capable nodes. It is the former capability that is
          essential to the SR-LDP interworking described later in this
          section.</t>
          <t>The SRMS functionality consists of two functional blocks: the
          Mapping Server (MS) and Mapping Client (MC).</t>
          <t>An MS is a node that advertises an SR mappings. Advertisements
          sent by an MS define the assignment of a Prefix-SID to a prefix
          independent of the advertisement of reachability to the prefix
          itself. An MS <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> advertise SR mappings for any prefix whether or
          not it advertises reachability for the prefix and irrespective of
          whether that prefix is advertised by or even reachable through any
          router in the network.</t>
          <t>An MC is a node that receives and uses the MS mapping
          advertisements. Note that a node may be both an MS and an MC. An MC
          interprets the SR-mapping advertisement as an assignment of a
          Prefix-SID to a prefix. For a given prefix, if an MC receives an
          SR-mapping advertisement from a Mapping Server and also has received
          a Prefix-SID Advertisement for that same prefix in a prefix
          reachability advertisement, then the MC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> prefer the SID
          advertised in the prefix reachability advertisement over the
          Mapping Server Advertisement, i.e., the Mapping Server Advertisement
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored for that prefix. Hence, assigning a Prefix-SID to a
          prefix using the SRMS functionality does not preclude assigning the
          same or different Prefix-SID(s) to the same prefix using explicit
          Prefix-SID Advertisement such as the aforementioned Prefix-SID
          sub-TLVs.</t>
          <t>For example, consider an IPv4 prefix advertisement received by an
          IS‑IS router in the Extended IP reachability TLV (TLV 135). Suppose
          TLV 135 contained the Prefix-SID sub-TLV. If the router that
          receives TLV 135 with the Prefix-SID sub-TLV also received an
          SR-mapping advertisement for the same prefix through the
          SID/Label Binding TLV, then the receiving router must prefer the
          Prefix-SID sub-TLV over the SID/Label Binding TLV for that
          prefix. Refer to <xref target="RFC8667" format="default"/> for details
          about the Prefix-SID sub-TLV and SID/Label Binding TLV.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec-4.2.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>SR to LDP Behavior</name>
          <t>SR to LDP interworking requires an SRMS as defined above.</t>
          <t>Each SR-capable router installs in the MPLS data-plane Node SIDs
          learned from the SRMS exactly as if these SIDs had been advertised
          by the nodes themselves.</t>
          <t>An SR node having LDP-only neighbors <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> stitch the incoming SR label
          (whose SID is advertised by the SRMS) to the outgoing LDP label.</t>
          <t>It has to be noted that the SR to LDP behavior does not propagate
          the status of the LDP FEC that was signaled by LDP when configured
          in ordered mode.</t>
          <t>It has to be noted that in the case of SR to LDP, the label
          binding is equivalent to the independent LDP Label Distribution
          Control Mode <xref target="RFC5036" format="default"/> where a label is bound to a
          FEC independently from the received binding for the same FEC.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sec-4.2.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Interoperability of Multiple SRMSes and Prefix-SID Advertisements</name>
          <t>In the case of SR-LDP interoperability through the use of an SRMS,
          mappings are advertised by one or more SRMSes.</t>
          <t>SRMS functionality is implemented in the link-state protocol (such as
          IS-IS and OSPF). Link-state protocols allow propagation of updates
          across area boundaries and, therefore, SRMS advertisements are
          propagated through the usual inter-area advertisement procedures in
          link-state protocols.</t>
          <t>Multiple SRMSes can be provisioned in a network for redundancy.
          Moreover, a preference mechanism may also be used among SRMSes to
          deploy a primary/secondary SRMS scheme allowing controlled
          modification or migration of SIDs.</t>
          <t>The content of SRMS advertisement (i.e., mappings) are a matter
          of local policy determined by the operator. When multiple SRMSes are
          active, it is necessary that the information (mappings) advertised
          by the different SRMSes is aligned and consistent. The following
          mechanism is applied to determine the preference of SRMS
          advertisements:</t>
          <t>If a node acts as an SRMS, it <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> advertise a preference to be
          associated with all SRMS SID Advertisements sent by that node. The
          means of advertising the preference is defined in the
          protocol-specific documents, e.g., <xref target="RFC8665" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8666" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC8667" format="default"/>. The
          preference value is an unsigned 8-bit integer with the following
          properties:</t>

<table anchor="table_1">
  <tbody> 
    <tr>
      <td align="center">0</td>
      <td align="left">Reserved value indicating advertisements from that
      node <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td align="center">1-255</td>
      <td align="left">Preference value (255 is most preferred)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  </table>


          <t>Advertisement of a preference value is optional. Nodes
          that do not advertise a preference value are assigned a preference
          value of 128.</t>
          <t>An MCC on a node receiving one or more SRMS mapping advertisements
          applies them as follows:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>For any prefix for which it did not receive a Prefix-SID
              Advertisement, the MCC applies the SRMS mapping advertisements
              with the highest preference. The mechanism by which a Prefix-SID
              is advertised for a given prefix is defined in the protocol
              specifications <xref target="RFC8665" format="default"/>,
              <xref target="RFC8666" format="default"/>, and
              <xref target="RFC8667" format="default"/>.</li>
            <li>If there is an incoming label collision as specified in <xref target="RFC8660" format="default"/>, apply the
              steps specified in <xref target="RFC8660" format="default"/> to resolve the
              collision.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>When the SRMS advertises mappings, an implementation should
          provide a mechanism through which the operator determines which of
          the IP2MPLS mappings are preferred among the one advertised by the
          SRMS and the ones advertised by LDP.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-5" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SR-LDP Interworking Use Cases</name>
      <t>SR can be deployed, for example, to enhance LDP transport. The SR
      deployment can be limited to the network region where the SR benefits
      are most desired.</t>
      <section anchor="sec-5.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Protection of LDP-Based Traffic</name>
        <t>In <xref target="ref-sr-ldp-interworking-example" format="default"/>, let us assume:
        </t>
        <ul empty="false" spacing="normal">
          <li>
          All link costs are 10 except FG, which is 30.</li>
          <li> All routers are LDP capable.</li>
          <li> X, Y, and Z are PEs participating in an important service S.</li>
          <li> The operator requires 50 msec link-based Fast Reroute (FRR) for service S.</li>
          <li> A, B, C, D, E, F, and G are SR capable.</li>
          <li> X, Y, and Z are not SR capable, e.g., as part of a
          staged migration from LDP to SR, the operator deploys SR first in
          a subpart of the network and then everywhere.</li>
        </ul>
        <figure anchor="ref-sr-ldp-interworking-example">
          <name>SR-LDP Interworking Example</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                                  X
                                  |
                           Y--A---B---E--Z
                              |   |    \
                              D---C--F--G
                                      30
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

<t>The operator would like to resolve the following issues:
</t>
<ul empty="false" spacing="normal">
<li>To protect the link BA along the shortest-path of the important flow XY,
B requires a Remote Loop-Free Alternate (RLFA; see <xref target="RFC7490"
format="default"/>) repair tunnel to D and, therefore, a targeted LDP session
from B to D. Typically, network operators prefer avoiding these dynamically
established multi-hop LDP sessions in order to reduce the number of protocols
running in the network and, therefore, simplify network operations.
</li>
<li>There is no LFA/RLFA solution to protect the link BE along the shortest
path of the important flow XZ. The operator wants a guaranteed link-based FRR solution.
</li>
</ul>

        <t>The operator can meet these objectives by deploying SR only on A,
        B, C, D, E, F, and G:</t>
<ul>

<li>The operator configures A, B, C, D, E, F, and G with SRGB [100, 200] and
with node segments 101, 102, 103, 104, 105, 106, and 107, respectively.
</li>
<li>The operator configures D as an SR Mapping Server with the following
policy mapping: (X, 201), (Y, 202), and (Z, 203).
</li>
<li>Each SR node automatically advertises a local adjacency segment for its
IGP adjacencies. Specifically, F advertises adjacency segment 9001 for its
adjacency FG.
</li>
</ul>

        <t>A, B, C, D, E, F, and G keep their LDP capability. Therefore, the
        flows XY and XZ are transported over end-to-end LDP LSPs.</t>
        <t>For example, LDP at B installs the following MPLS data-plane
        entries:</t>

<ul empty="true"><li><t>Incoming label: local LDP label bound by B for FEC Y</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: LDP label bound by A for FEC Y</li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: A</li>
 </ul>
</li>
 <li><t>Incoming label: local LDP label bound by B for FEC Z</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: LDP label bound by E for FEC Z </li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: E </li>
 </ul>
</li>
</ul>

        <t>The novelty comes from how the backup chains are computed for these
        LDP-based entries. While LDP labels are used for the primary next- hop
        and outgoing labels, SR information is used for the FRR construction.
        In steady state, the traffic is transported over LDP LSP. In transient
        FRR state, the traffic is backup thanks to the SR-enhanced
        capabilities.</t>
        <t>The RLFA paths are dynamically precomputed as defined in <xref target="RFC7490" format="default"/>. Typically, implementations allow to enable an RLFA
        mechanism through a simple configuration command that triggers both
        the precomputation and installation of the repair path. The details
        on how RLFA mechanisms are implemented and configured is outside the
        scope of this document and not relevant to the aspects of SR-LDP
        interwork explained in this document.</t>

<t>This helps meet the requirements of the operator:
</t>
<ul>
<li>Eliminate targeted LDP sessions.
</li>
<li>Provide guaranteed FRR coverage.
</li>
<li>Keep the traffic over LDP LSP in steady state.
</li>
<li>Partially deploy SR only where needed.
</li>
</ul>

      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-5.2" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Eliminating Targeted LDP Sessions</name>
        <t>B's MPLS entry to Y becomes:</t>
<ul empty="true"><li><t>Incoming label: local LDP label bound by B for FEC Y</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: LDP label bound by A for FEC Y</li>
 <li>Backup outgoing label: SR node segment for Y {202}</li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: A</li>
 <li>Backup next hop: repair tunnel: node segment to D {104} with outgoing
 next hop: C</li>
 </ul>
</li>
</ul>

        <t>It has to be noted that D is selected as a Remote Loop-Free Alternate
        (RLFA) as defined in <xref target="RFC7490" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>In steady state, X sends its Y-destined traffic to B with a top
        label, which is the LDP label bound by B for FEC Y. B swaps that top
        label for the LDP label bound by A for FEC Y and forwards to A. A pops
        the LDP label and forwards to Y.</t>
        <t>Upon failure of the link BA, B swaps the incoming top label with
        the node segment for Y (202) and sends the packet onto a repair tunnel
        to D (node segment 104). Thus, B sends the packet to C with the label
        stack {104, 202}.  C pops the node segment 104 and forwards to D. D
        swaps 202 for 202 and forwards to A. A's next hop to Y is not SR
        capable, and therefore, Node A swaps the incoming node segment 202 to the
        LDP label announced by its next hop (in this case, implicit NULL).</t>
        <t>After IGP convergence, B's MPLS entry to Y will become:</t>


 
<ul empty="true"><li><t>Incoming label: local LDP label bound by B for FEC Y</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: LDP label bound by C for FEC Y</li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: C</li>
 </ul>
</li>
</ul>

        <t>And the traffic XY travels again over the LDP LSP.</t>
        <t>Conclusion: the operator has eliminated the need for targeted LDP
        sessions (no longer required) and the steady-state traffic is still
        transported over LDP. The SR deployment is confined to the area where
        these benefits are required.</t>
        <t>Despite that, in general, an implementation would not require a
        manual configuration of targeted LDP sessions. However, it is always a
        gain if the operator is able to reduce the set of protocol sessions
        running on the network infrastructure.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-5.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Guaranteed FRR Coverage</name>
        <t>As mentioned in <xref target="sec-5.1" format="default"/>, in the example
        topology described in <xref target="ref-sr-ldp-interworking-example" format="default"/>, there is no RLFA-based solution for
        protecting the traffic flow YZ against the failure of link BE because
        there is no intersection between the extended P-space and Q-space (see
        <xref target="RFC7490" format="default"/> for details). However:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>G belongs to the Q space of Z.</li>
          <li>G can be reached from B via a "repair SR path" {106, 9001} that
            is not affected by failure of link BE. (The method by which G and
            the repair tunnel to it from B are identified are outside the scope of
            this document.)</li>
        </ul>
        <t>B's MPLS entry to Z becomes:</t>

<ul empty="true"><li><t>Incoming label: local LDP label bound by B for FEC Z</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: LDP label bound by E for FEC Z</li>
 <li>Backup outgoing label: SR node segment for Z {203}</li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: E</li>
 <li>Backup next hop: repair tunnel to G: {106, 9001}</li>
 </ul>
</li>
</ul>


       <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
              <li>
        G is reachable from B via the combination of a
        node segment to F {106} and an adjacency segment
        FG {9001}.
      </li>
              <li>
        Note that {106, 107} would have equally worked.
        Indeed, in many cases, P's shortest path to Q is
        over the link PQ.  The adjacency segment from P to
        Q is required only in very rare topologies where
        the shortest-path from P to Q is not via the link
        PQ.
</li>
            </ul>     

   <t>

        In steady state, X sends its Z-destined traffic to B with a top
        label, which is the LDP label bound by B for FEC Z. B swaps that top
        label for the LDP label bound by E for FEC Z and forwards to E. E pops
        the LDP label and forwards to Z.</t>
        <t>Upon failure of the link BE, B swaps the incoming top label with
        the node segment for Z (203) and sends the packet onto a repair tunnel
        to G (node segment 106 followed by adjacency segment 9001). Thus, B
        sends the packet to C with the label stack {106, 9001, 203}.  C pops
        the node segment 106 and forwards to F. F pops the adjacency segment
        9001 and forwards to G. G swaps 203 for 203 and forwards to E. E's
        next hop to Z is not SR capable, and thus, E swaps the incoming node
        segment 203 for the LDP label announced by its next hop (in this case,
        implicit NULL).</t>
        <t>After IGP convergence, B's MPLS entry to Z will become:</t>

<ul empty="true"><li><t>Incoming label: local LDP label bound by B for FEC Z</t>
 <ul empty="false">
 <li>Outgoing label: LDP label bound by C for FEC Z </li>
 <li>Outgoing next hop: C </li>
 </ul>
</li>
</ul>
        <t>And the traffic XZ travels again over the LDP LSP.</t>
        <t>Conclusions:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>the operator has eliminated its second problem: guaranteed FRR
            coverage is provided. The steady-state traffic is still
            transported over LDP. The SR deployment is confined to the area
            where these benefits are required.</li>
          <li>FRR coverage has been achieved without any signaling for
            setting up the repair LSP and without setting up a targeted LDP
            session between B and G.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-5.4" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Inter-AS Option C, Carrier's Carrier</name>
        <t>In inter-AS Option C <xref target="RFC4364" format="default"/>, two interconnected
        ASes sets up inter-AS MPLS connectivity. SR may be independently
        deployed in each AS.</t>
        <figure anchor="ref-inter-as-option-c">
          <name>Inter-AS Option C</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                    PE1---R1---B1---B2---R2---PE2
                    <----------->   <----------->
                         AS1            AS2
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>In Inter-AS Option C, B2 advertises to B1 a labeled BGP route <xref
        target="RFC8277" format="default"/> for PE2, and B1 reflects it to its
        internal peers, e.g., PE1. PE1 learns from a service route reflector a
        service route whose next hop is PE2. PE1 resolves that service route
        on the labeled BGP route to PE2. That labeled BGP route to PE2 is
        itself resolved on the AS1 IGP route to B1.</t>
        <t>If AS1 operates SR, then the tunnel from PE1 to B1 is provided by
        the node segment from PE1 to B1.</t>
        <t>PE1 sends a service packet with three labels: the top one is the
        node segment to B1, the next one is the label in the labeled BGP route
        provided by B1 for the route "PE2", and the bottom one is the service
        label allocated by PE2.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-6" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t> This document has no IANA actions. </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-7" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Manageability Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="sec-7.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR and LDP Coexistence</name>
        <t>When both SR and LDP coexist, the following applies:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>If both SR and LDP propose an IP2MPLS entry for the same IP
            prefix, then by default the LDP route <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be selected. This is
            because it is expected that SR is introduced into networks that
            contain routers that do not support SR. Hence, by having a behavior
            that prefers LDP over SR, traffic flow is unlikely to be
            disrupted.</li>
          <li>A local policy on a router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> allow to prefer the SR-provided
            IP2MPLS entry.</li>
          <li>Note that this policy <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be locally defined. There is no
            requirement that all routers use the same policy.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-7.3" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Data-Plane Verification</name>
        <t>When Label switch paths (LSPs) are defined by stitching LDP LSPs
        with SR LSPs, it is necessary to have mechanisms allowing the
        verification of the LSP connectivity as well as validation of the
        path. These mechanisms are described in <xref target="RFC8287" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-8" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document does not introduce any change to the MPLS data plane
      <xref target="RFC3031" format="default"/> and therefore no additional security of the
      MPLS data plane is required.</t>
    
      <t>
This document introduces another form of label binding advertisements. The
security associated with these advertisements is part of the security applied
to routing protocols such as IS-IS <xref target="RFC5304" format="default"/>
and OSPF <xref target="RFC5709" format="default"/>, which both optionally make
use of cryptographic authentication mechanisms. This form of advertisement is
more centralized, on behalf of the node advertising the IP reachability, which
presents a different risk profile. This document also specifies a mechanism by
which the ill effects of advertising conflicting label bindings can be
mitigated. In particular, advertisements from the node advertising the IP
reachability is more preferred than the centralized one. This document
recognizes that errors in configuration and/or programming may result in false
or conflicting label binding advertisements compromising traffic
forwarding. Therefore, this document recommends the operator implement strict
configuration/programmability control, the monitoring of the advertised SIDs,
the preference of an IP reachability SID Advertisement over a centralized SID
Advertisement, and the logging of any error message in order to avoid, or at
least significantly minimize, the possibility of such risk.
</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>


<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5036.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>




        <reference anchor="RFC8660"
		   target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8660">
          <front>
            <title>Segment Routing with MPLS Data Plane</title>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8660"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8660"/>
            <author initials="A" surname="Bashandy" fullname="Ahmed Bashandy"
		    role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="C" surname="Filsfils" fullname="Clarence
							      Filsfils"
		    role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S" surname="Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="B" surname="Decraene" fullname="Bruno Decraene">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S" surname="Litkowski" fullname="Stephane
							       Litkowski">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R" surname="Shakir" fullname="Rob Shakir">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="December" year="2019"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
 
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3031.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5304.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5709.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5960.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7490.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8277.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8287.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8355.xml"/>





        <reference anchor="RFC8665">
          <front>
            <title>OSPF Extensions for Segment Routing</title>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8665"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8665"/>
            <author initials="P" surname="Psenak" fullname="Peter Psenak"
		    role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S" surname="Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi"
		    role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="C" surname="Filsfils" fullname="Clarence
							      Filsfils">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="H" surname="Gredler" fullname="Hannes Gredler">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R" surname="Shakir" fullname="Rob Shakir">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="W" surname="Henderickx" fullname="Wim
								Henderickx">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J" surname="Tantsura" fullname="Jeff Tantsura">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="December" year="2019"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

   <reference anchor="RFC8666">
          <front>
            <title>OSPFv3 Extensions for Segment Routing</title>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8666"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8666"/>
            <author initials="P" surname="Psenak" fullname="Peter Psenak"
		    role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S" surname="Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="December" year="2019"/>
          </front>
   </reference>

    
        <reference anchor="RFC8667">
          <front>
            <title>IS-IS Extensions for Segment Routing</title>
            <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8667"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8667"/>
            <author initials="S" surname="Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="L" surname="Ginsberg" fullname="Les Ginsberg">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="C" surname="Filsfils" fullname="Clarence
							      Filsfils">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A" surname="Bashandy" fullname="Ahmed Bashandy">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="H" surname="Gredler" fullname="Hannes Gredler">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="B" surname="Decraene" fullname="Bruno Decraene">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="December" year="2019"/>
          </front>
        </reference>



      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Appendix-A" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Migration from LDP to SR</name>
      <figure anchor="ref-migration">
        <name>Migration</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                            PE2        PE4
                              \        /
                       PE1----P5--P6--P7---PE3
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>Several migration techniques are possible. The technique described
      here is inspired by the commonly used method to migrate from one IGP to
      another.</t>
      <t>At time T0, all the routers run LDP. Any service is tunneled from an
      ingress PE to an egress PE over a continuous LDP LSP.</t>
      <t>At time T1, all the routers are upgraded to SR. They are configured
      with the SRGB range [100, 300]. PE1, PE2, PE3, PE4, P5, P6, and P7 are
      respectively configured with the node segments 101, 102, 103, 104, 105,
      106, and 107 (attached to their service-recursing loopback).
</t>

<aside>

<t>
          Note: At this time, the service traffic is still tunneled over LDP LSPs.
          For example, PE1 has an SR node segment to PE3 and an LDP LSP to PE3.
          As seen earlier, however, the LDP IP2MPLS encapsulation is
          preferred by default. However, it has to be noted that the SR infrastructure is
          usable, e.g., for Fast Reroute (FRR) or IGP Loop-Free Convergence to
          protect existing IP and LDP traffic. FRR mechanisms are described in
          <xref target="RFC8355" format="default"/>.
</t>
</aside>

      <t>At time T2, the operator enables the local policy at PE1 to prefer SR
      IP2MPLS encapsulation over LDP IP2MPLS.</t>
<ul empty="true" indent="3">
        <li>The service from PE1 to any other PE is now riding over SR. All
          other service traffic is still transported over LDP LSPs.</li>
</ul>
      <t>At time T3, gradually, the operator enables the preference for SR
      IP2MPLS encapsulation across all the edge routers.</t>
<ul empty="true" indent="3">
        <li>All the service traffic is now transported over SR. LDP is still
          operational and services could be reverted to LDP.</li>
      </ul>
  
      <t>At time T4, LDP is unconfigured from all routers.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-9" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank Pierre Francois, Ruediger Geib, and
      Alexander Vainshtein for their contributions to the content of this
      document.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-10" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Edward Crabbe
Individual
Email: edward.crabbe@gmail.com]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Igor Milojevic
Email: milojevicigor@gmail.com]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Saku Ytti
TDC
Email: saku@ytti.fi]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Rob Shakir
Google
Email: robjs@google.com]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Martin Horneffer
Deutsche Telekom
Email: Martin.Horneffer@telekom.de]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Wim Henderickx
Nokia
Email: wim.henderickx@nokia.com]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Jeff Tantsura
Apstra, Inc.
Email: jefftant.ietf@gmail.com]]></artwork>

      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Les Ginsberg
Cisco Systems
Email: ginsberg@cisco.com]]></artwork>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
