<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>


<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-shmoo-cancel-meeting-06" number="9137" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" category="bcp" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Cancellation of IETF Meetings">Considerations for Cancellation of IETF
    Meetings</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9137"/>
    <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="226"/>
    <author initials="M." surname="Duke" fullname="Martin Duke">
      <organization>F5 Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>martin.h.duke@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2021" month="October"/>
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>shmoo</workgroup>

<keyword>virtualize</keyword>
<keyword>postpone</keyword>
<keyword>move</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The IETF ordinarily holds three in-person meetings per year to discuss issues
      and advance the Internet. However, various events can make a planned
      in-person meeting infeasible. This document provides criteria to aid the IETF
      Administration LLC (IETF LLC), the Internet Engineering Steering
      Group (IESG), and the Chair of the 
      Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) in deciding to relocate, virtualize, postpone, or
      cancel an in-person IETF meeting.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Among the highlights of the IETF calendar are in-person general meetings, which
      happen three times a year at various locations around the world.</t>
      <t>Various major events may affect the suitability of a scheduled in-person IETF
      meeting, though this may not be immediately obvious for some events. Examples of such events include the following:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>A meeting venue itself may unexpectedly close or otherwise be unable to meet
	IETF meeting requirements due to a health issue, legal violation, or other
	localized problem.</li>
        <li>A natural disaster could degrade the travel and meeting infrastructure in a
	planned location and make it unethical to further burden that infrastructure
	with a meeting.</li>
        <li>War, civil unrest, or a public health crisis could make a meeting unsafe and/or
	result in widespread national or corporate travel bans.</li>
        <li>An economic crisis could sharply reduce resources available for travel,
	resulting in lower expected attendance.</li>
        <li>Changes in visa policies or other unexpected governmental restrictions might
	make the venue inaccessible to numerous attendees.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>This document provides criteria to aid the IETF Administration
      LLC (IETF LLC), the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG), and the Chair of the
      Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) in deciding to relocate, virtualize, postpone, or
      cancel an in-person IETF meeting.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conventions" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Conventions</name>
      <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
      "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
      "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
      "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT
      RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"
      format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/>
      when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      <t>In this document, the term "venue" refers to both the facility that houses the
      sessions and the official meeting hotel(s), as defined in <xref target="RFC8718"
      format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="decision-criteria-and-roles" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Decision Criteria and Roles</name>
      <t>The IETF LLC assesses whether an in-person meeting is logistically and financially
      viable in light of events and assembles information about various travel
      restrictions that might impact attendance. The
      IESG and the Chair of the IRTF assess if the
      projected attendance is sufficient for a viable in-person meeting.</t>
      <section anchor="ietf-llc" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>IETF LLC</name>
        <t>The IETF LLC is responsible for assessing the suitability of a venue for an IETF
	meeting and is responsible for any reassessment in response to a major event
	that leaves the prior conclusion in doubt. If such an event occurs more than
	fourteen weeks before the start of the scheduled meeting, it is deemed a
	non-emergency situation. Later events, up to and including the week of a meeting
	itself, are deemed emergency situations.</t>


        <t>In non-emergency situations, if the IETF LLC determines the scheduled meeting
	clearly
	cannot proceed (e.g., the venue has permanently closed), then it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	share the reason(s) with the community and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> consult on its
	proposed remedy. In less clear cases, the IETF LLC <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> conduct a
	formal reassessment process that includes:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Consulting with the community on the timetable of the decision process.</li>
          <li>Consulting with the community on criteria to assess the impact of new
	  developments.</li>
          <li>Publishing an assessment report and recommended remedy.</li>
          <li>Seeking approval of the IESG and the Chair of the IRTF for the
	  recommendation.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>In emergency situations, which lack the time for a consultation process, this
	document provides criteria that have IETF consensus and that the IETF LLC
	<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> apply in its assessment.</t>
        <t>The IETF LLC will collect information about the likely impact to in-person
	attendance of national travel advisories, national and corporate travel bans,
	availability of transportation, quarantine requirements, etc., and report the
	results to the IESG and the Chair of the IRTF.</t>
        <t>These criteria, some of which are derived from <xref target="RFC8718"
	sectionFormat="of" section="3"/>, apply
	to venues that are re-evaluated due to an emergency:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Local safety guidelines allow the venue and hotels to host a meeting with the
	  expected number of participants and staff.</li>
          <li>It is possible to provision Internet access to the venue that allows those
	  attending in person to utilize the Internet for all their IETF, business, and
	  day-to-day needs; in addition, there must be sufficient bandwidth and access for
	  remote attendees.  Provisions include, but are not limited to, native and
	  unmodified IPv4 and IPv6 connectivity and global reachability; there may be no
	  additional limitation that would materially impact their Internet use.  To
	  ensure availability, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be possible to provision redundant
	  paths to the Internet.</li>
          <li>A reasonable number of food and drink establishments are open and available
	  within walking distance to provide for the expected number of participants and
	  staff.</li>
          <li>Local health and public safety infrastructure expects to have adequate
	  capacity to support an influx of visitors during the meeting week.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>Finally, the IETF LLC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> assess the impact on its own operations,
	including:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>The number of critical support staff, contractors, and volunteers who can be
	  at the venue.</li>
          <li>The financial impact of continuing a meeting or implementing any of the
	  possible remedies.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>The IETF LLC <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> cancel an in-person meeting and explore
	potential
	remedies if it judges a meeting to be logistically impossible or inconsistent with its
	fiduciary responsibilities.</t>
        <t>In the event of considerations this document does not foresee, the IETF LLC should
	protect the health and safety of attendees and staff, as well as the fiscal
	health of the organization, with approval from the IESG and the Chair of the IRTF. The
	IESG should pursue a later update of this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iesg-and-irtf-chair" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>The IESG and the Chair of the IRTF</name>
        <t>If the IETF LLC assesses there are no fundamental logistical or financial obstacles
	to holding a meeting in an emergency situation, the IESG and the Chair of the IRTF
	assess
	if projected attendance is high enough to achieve the benefit of an in-person
	meeting. The IESG and the Chair of the IRTF <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> cancel the in-person
	meeting if that benefit is insufficient.</t>
        <t>The IESG and the Chair of the IRTF are discouraged from relying on a simple head
	count of
	expected meeting attendance. Even dramatically smaller meetings with large
	remote participation may be successful.  In addition to the IETF LLC's estimate, the
	IESG and the Chair of the IRTF might consider:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>Are many working groups and research groups largely unaffected by the
	  restrictions, so that they can operate effectively?</li>
          <li>Is there a critical mass of key personnel at most working group meetings to
	  leverage the advantages of in-person meetings, even if many participants are
	  remote?</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="remedies" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Remedies</name>
      <t>If a meeting cannot be held at the scheduled time and place, the IETF LLC, IESG, and
      Chair of the IRTF have several options. The remedies in this section should be
      considered in light of four principles (presented in no particular order):</t>

      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Hold the scheduled sessions of a meeting in some format.</li>
        <li>Provide benefits of in-person interactions when possible.</li>
        <li>Avoid exorbitant additional travel expenses due to last-minute flight changes,
	etc.</li>
        <li>Ensure sufficient time and resources to adequately prepare an alternative.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>The following remedies are listed in approximate declining order of preference.</t>
      <section anchor="relocation" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Relocation</name>
        <t>For attendees, the least disruptive response is to retain the meeting week but
	move it to a more-accessible venue. To the maximum extent possible, this will be
	geographically close to the original venue. In particular, the IETF LLC
	<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> meet the criteria in <xref target="RFC8718" format="default"/>
	and <xref target="RFC8719" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Relocation that requires new air travel arrangements for attendees <bcp14>SHOULD
	NOT</bcp14> occur less than one month prior to the start of the meeting.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="virtualization" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Virtualization</name>
        <t>The second option, and one that has fewer issues with venue availability, is to
	make a meeting fully online. This requires different IETF processes and
	logistical operations that are outside the scope of this document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="postponement" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Postponement</name>
        <t>Although it is more disruptive to the schedules of participants, the next best
	option is to delay a meeting until a specific date, at the same venue, at
	which conditions are expected to improve. The new end date of a meeting must
	be at least 30 days before the beginning of the following IETF meeting, and a
	meeting <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> begin no earlier than 30 days after the postponement
	announcement.</t>
        <t>Due to scheduling constraints at the venue, this will usually not be feasible.
	However, it is more likely to allow attendees to recover at least some of their
	travel expenses than other options.</t>
        <t>Note that it is possible to both postpone and relocate a meeting, though this
	has the disadvantages of both.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="cancellation" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cancellation</name>
        <t>The IETF LLC, IESG, and Chair of the IRTF may cancel a meeting entirely in the
	event that
	worldwide conditions make it difficult for attendees to even attend online. Not
	holding a meeting at all can have wide implications, such as effects on the
	nomination process and seating of new officers.</t>
        <t>Cancellation is likely the only practical alternative when emergencies occur
	immediately before or during a meeting, so that there is no opportunity to
	make other arrangements.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="refunds" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Refunds</name>
      <t>The IETF <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> reimburse registered attendees for unrecoverable
      travel expenses (airfare, hotel deposits, etc.).</t>
      <t>However, there are several cases where full or partial refund of registration
      fees are appropriate:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Cancellation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> result in a full refund to all participants.
	It <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be prorated if some portion of the sessions completed without
	incident.</li>
        <li>Upon postponement, the IETF LLC <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> offer refunds to registered
	attendees who claim they cannot attend at the newly scheduled time. Attendees can opt
	out of receiving a refund.</li>
        <li>When a meeting is virtualized, the IETF LLC <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> offer to refund
	registered attendees the difference between their paid registration fee and the
	equivalent fee for an online meeting. The IETF LLC <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> offer
	refunds to
	registered attendees who do not wish to attend an online meeting.</li>
        <li>The IETF LLC <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> offer refunds to attendees whose government
	forbids, or has issued a safety advisory against, visits to the host venue, even if
	the in-person meeting will continue. It <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> refund
	cancellations due to employer policy or personal risk assessments.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>These provisions intend to maintain trust between the IETF and its participants.
      However, under extraordinary threats to the solvency of the organization, the
      IETF LLC may suspend them.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document introduces no new concerns for the security of Internet protocols.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8718.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8719.xml"/>

    </references>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t><contact fullname="Jay Daley"/> provided extensive input to make this document more
      usable by the IETF LLC. Many members of the IESG and the
      SHMOO Working Group also provided useful comments.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
