<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>


<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-dnssec-iana-cons-05" number="9157" updates="5155, 6014, 8624" obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IANA Revisions for DNSSEC">Revised IANA Considerations for DNSSEC</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9157"/>
    <author initials="P." surname="Hoffman" fullname="Paul Hoffman">
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <email>paul.hoffman@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2021" month="November"/>

<abstract>

      <t>This document changes the review requirements needed to get DNSSEC algorithms
      and resource records added to IANA registries.      
It updates RFC 6014 to include hash algorithms for Delegation Signer (DS) records
and NextSECure version 3 (NSEC3) parameters (for Hashed Authenticated Denial of Existence). It also updates RFCs 5155 and 6014, which have requirements for DNSSEC
algorithms, and updates RFC 8624 to clarify the implementation recommendation related to the algorithms described in RFCs that are not on the standards track.
The rationale for these changes is to bring the requirements for DS records
and hash algorithms used in NSEC3 in line with the requirements for
all other DNSSEC algorithms.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>DNSSEC is primarily described in <xref target="RFC4033" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC4034" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC4035" format="default"/>.
DNSSEC commonly uses another resource record beyond those defined in <xref target="RFC4034"/>:
NSEC3 <xref target="RFC5155" format="default"/>.
DS resource records were originally defined in <xref target="RFC3658" format="default"/>, and that definition
was obsoleted by <xref target="RFC4034"/>.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC6014" format="default"/> updates the requirements for how DNSSEC cryptographic algorithm
identifiers in the IANA registries are assigned, reducing the requirements
from "Standards Action" to "RFC Required".
However, the IANA registry requirements for hash algorithms for DS records
<xref target="RFC3658" format="default"/>
and for the hash algorithms used in NSEC3 records <xref target="RFC5155" format="default"/> are still "Standards Action".
This document updates those IANA registry requirements.
      (For a reference on how IANA registries can be updated in general, see <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>.)</t>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>      
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="update-to-rfc-6014" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Update to RFC 6014</name>
      <t><xref target="iana" format="default"/> updates <xref target="RFC6014"/> to bring the requirements for DS records
and NSEC3 hash algorithms in line with the rest of the DNSSEC cryptographic algorithms
by allowing any DS hash algorithms, NSEC3 hash algorithms,
NSEC3 parameters, and NSEC3 flags that are fully described in an RFC
to have identifiers assigned in the IANA registries.
This is an addition to the IANA considerations in <xref target="RFC6014"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="update-to-rfc-8624" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Update to RFC 8624</name>
      <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC8624" format="default"/> for all DNSKEY and DS algorithms that are not
on the standards track.</t>
      <t>The second paragraph of <xref target="RFC8624" sectionFormat="of" section="1.2"/> currently says:</t>
<blockquote><t>
   This document only provides recommendations with respect to
   mandatory-to-implement algorithms or algorithms so weak that they
   cannot be recommended.  Any algorithm listed in the [DNSKEY-IANA]
   and [DS-IANA] registries that are not mentioned in this document
   <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be implemented.  For clarification and consistency, an
   algorithm will be specified as <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> in this document only when it
   has been downgraded from a <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> or a <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to a <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>.</t>
</blockquote>
      <t>That paragraph is now replaced with the following:</t>
<blockquote><t>
   This document provides recommendations with respect to
   mandatory-to-implement algorithms, algorithms so weak that they
   cannot be recommended, and algorithms defined in RFCs
   that are not on the standards track. Any algorithm listed in the
   [DNSKEY-IANA] and [DS-IANA] registries that are not mentioned in
   this document <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be implemented. For clarification and
   consistency, an algorithm will be specified as <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> in this document only when it has been downgraded from a <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> or a
   <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to a <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>.</t>
 </blockquote>
      <t>This update is also reflected in the IANA considerations in <xref target="iana" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>In the "Domain Name System Security (DNSSEC) NextSECure3 (NSEC3) Parameters"
registry, the registration procedure for "DNSSEC NSEC3 Flags", "DNSSEC NSEC3
Hash Algorithms", and "DNSSEC NSEC3PARAM Flags" has been changed from "Standards
Action" to "RFC Required", and this document has been added as a reference.</t>
      <t>In the "DNSSEC Delegation Signer (DS) Resource Record (RR) Type Digest Algorithms" registry, the registration procedure for "Digest Algorithms" has been changed from "Standards Action" to "RFC Required", and this document has been added as a reference.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Changing the requirements for adding security algorithms to IANA
registries as described in this document will make it easier to add both good
and bad algorithms to the registries.
It is impossible to weigh the security impact of those two changes.</t>
      <t>Administrators of DNSSEC-signed zones and validating resolvers may have been making
security decisions based on the contents of the IANA registries.
This was a bad idea in the past, and now it is an even worse idea because there will be more
algorithms in those registries that may not have gone through IETF review.
Security decisions about which algorithms are safe and not safe should be made by
reading the security literature, not by looking in IANA registries.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5155.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6014.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8624.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3658.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t><contact fullname="Donald Eastlake"/>, <contact fullname="Murray Kucherawy"/>, <contact fullname="Dan Harkins"/>, <contact fullname="Martin Duke"/>, and
<contact fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/> contributed to this document.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
