<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-dprive-xfr-over-tls-12" number="9103" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" tocInclude="true" updates="1995, 5936, 7766">

<front>
<title abbrev="XFR over TLS">DNS Zone Transfer over TLS</title>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9103"/>
<author initials="W." surname="Toorop" fullname="Willem Toorop">
  <organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Science Park 400</street>
      <city>Amsterdam</city>
      <code>1098 XH</code>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
    </postal>
    <email>willem@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
  </address>
</author>
<author initials="S." surname="Dickinson" fullname="Sara Dickinson">
  <organization>Sinodun IT</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <extaddr>Magdalen Centre</extaddr>
      <street>Oxford Science Park</street>
      <city>Oxford</city>
      <code>OX4 4GA</code>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </postal>
      <email>sara@sinodun.com</email>
  </address>
</author>
<author initials="S." surname="Sahib" fullname="Shivan Sahib">
  <organization>Brave Software</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <city>Vancouver</city>
      <region>BC</region>
      <country>Canada</country>
      </postal>
      <email>shivankaulsahib@gmail.com</email>
  </address>
</author>
<author initials="P." surname="Aras" fullname="Pallavi Aras">
  <organization>Salesforce</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <city>Herndon</city>
      <region>VA</region>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </postal>
    <email>paras@salesforce.com</email>
  </address>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Mankin" fullname="Allison Mankin">
  <organization>Salesforce</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <city>Herndon</city>
      <region>VA</region>
      <country>United States of America</country>
    </postal>
    <email>allison.mankin@gmail.com</email>
  </address>
</author>
<date year="2021" month="August"></date>
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>dprive</workgroup>
<keyword>DNS</keyword>
<keyword>operations</keyword>
<keyword>privacy</keyword>

<abstract>
  <t>DNS zone transfers are transmitted in cleartext, which gives attackers the
  opportunity to collect the content of a zone by eavesdropping on network
  connections. The DNS Transaction Signature (TSIG) mechanism is specified to
  restrict direct zone transfer to authorized clients only, but it does not add
  confidentiality. This document specifies the use of TLS, rather than cleartext, 
  to prevent zone content collection via passive monitoring of zone
  transfers: XFR over TLS (XoT). Additionally, this specification updates RFC 1995
  and RFC 5936 with respect to efficient use of TCP connections and RFC 7766 with
  respect to the recommended number of connections between a client and server
  for each transport.</t>
</abstract>
</front>
<middle>
<section anchor="introduction">
  <name>Introduction</name>
  <t>DNS has a number of privacy vulnerabilities, as discussed in detail in
  <xref target="RFC9076"></xref>. Query privacy between stub resolvers and recursive resolvers has received
  the most attention to date, with Standards Track documents for both DNS over TLS
  (DoT) <xref target="RFC7858"></xref> and DNS over HTTPS (DoH) <xref target="RFC8484"></xref>
  and a proposal for
  DNS over QUIC <xref target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsoquic"></xref>. There is ongoing work on DNS
  privacy
  requirements for exchanges between recursive resolvers and authoritative
  servers and some suggestions for
  how signaling of DoT support by authoritative name servers might work. However, there is
  currently no RFC that specifically defines recursive-to-authoritative DNS over TLS
  (ADoT).</t>
  <t><xref target="RFC9076"></xref> establishes that a stub resolver's DNS query
  transactions are not public and that they need protection, but, on zone transfer
  <xref target="RFC1995"></xref> <xref target="RFC5936"></xref>, it says only:</t>
  <blockquote>Privacy risks for the holder of a zone (the risk that someone
  gets the data) are discussed in <xref target="RFC5155" format="default"/> and <xref
  target="RFC5936" format="default"/>.</blockquote>
  <t>In what way is exposing the full contents of a zone a privacy risk? The
  contents of the zone could include information such as names of persons used in
  names of hosts. Best practice is not to use personal information for domain
  names, but many such domain names exist. The contents of the zone could also
  include references to locations that allow inference about location information
  of the individuals associated with the zone's organization. It could also
  include references to other organizations. Examples of this could be:</t>
  <ul>
    <li>Person-laptop.example.org</li>
    <li>MX-for-Location.example.org</li>
    <li>Service-tenant-from-another-org.example.org</li>
  </ul>
  <t>Additionally, the full zone contents expose all the IP addresses of endpoints
  held in the DNS records, which can make reconnaissance and attack targeting easier,
  particularly
  for IPv6 addresses or private networks. There may also be regulatory, policy, or other
  reasons why the zone contents in full must be treated as private.</t>
  <t>Neither of the RFCs mentioned in <xref target="RFC9076"></xref>
  contemplate the risk that someone gets the data through eavesdropping on
  network connections, only via enumeration or unauthorized transfer, as described
  in the following paragraphs.</t>
  <t>Zone enumeration is trivially possible for DNSSEC zones that use NSEC, i.e.,
  queries for the authenticated denial-of-existence records allow a client to
  walk through the entire zone contents. <xref target="RFC5155"></xref> specifies NSEC3, a
  mechanism to provide measures against zone enumeration for DNSSEC-signed zones (a goal
  was to make it as hard to enumerate a DNSSEC-signed zone as an unsigned zone).
  Whilst this is widely used, it has been demonstrated that zone walking is
  possible for precomputed NSEC3 using attacks, such as those described in
  <xref target="NSEC3-attacks"></xref>. This prompted further work on an alternative
  mechanism for DNSSEC-authenticated denial of existence (NSEC5
  <xref target="I-D.vcelak-nsec5"></xref>); however, questions remain over the practicality of
  this mechanism.</t>
  <t><xref target="RFC5155"></xref> does not address data obtained outside zone enumeration (nor
  does <xref target="I-D.vcelak-nsec5"></xref>). Preventing eavesdropping of zone transfers (as
  described in this document) is orthogonal to preventing zone enumeration, though they aim to
  protect the same information.</t>
  <t><xref target="RFC5936"></xref> specifies using TSIG <xref target="RFC8945"></xref> for
  authorization of the clients
  of a zone transfer and for data integrity but does not express any need for
  confidentiality, and TSIG does not offer encryption.</t>
  <t>Section 8 of the NIST document "Secure Domain Name System (DNS) Deployment Guide"
  <xref target="NIST-GUIDE"></xref> discusses restricting access for zone transfers using
  Access Control Lists (ACLs) and
  TSIG in more detail. It also discusses the possibility that specific deployments
  might choose to use a lower-level network layer to protect zone transfers, e.g., IPsec.</t>
  <t>It is noted that in all the common open-source implementations
  such ACLs are applied on a per-query basis (at the time of writing). Since requests
  typically occur on TCP connections, authoritative servers must therefore accept any TCP connection
  and then handle the authentication of each zone transfer (XFR) request individually.</t>
  <t>Because both AXFR (authoritative transfer) and IXFR (incremental zone transfer) are
  typically carried out over TCP
  from authoritative DNS protocol implementations, encrypting zone transfers
  using TLS <xref target="RFC8499"></xref> -- based closely on DoT <xref
  target="RFC7858"></xref> -- seems like a simple step forward.
  This document specifies how to use TLS (1.3 or later) as a transport to prevent zone
  collection from zone transfers.</t>
  <t>This document also updates the previous specifications for zone transfers to
  clarify and extend them, mainly with respect to TCP usage:</t>
  <ul>
    <li><xref target="RFC1995" format="default"/> (IXFR) and <xref target="RFC5936"
    format="default"/> (AXFR) are both updated to add further
    specification on efficient use of TCP connections.</li>
    <li><xref target="RFC7766" sectionFormat="of" section="6.2.2"/> ("DNS Transport over TCP -
    Implementation Requirements") is updated with a new recommendation about 
    the number of connections between a client and server for each transport.</li>
  </ul>
</section>
<section anchor="terminology">
  <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
	<t>Privacy terminology is as described in <xref target="RFC6973" sectionFormat="of"
	section="3"/>.</t>
	<t>DNS terminology is as described in <xref target="RFC8499"></xref>. Note that, as in
	<xref target="RFC8499"></xref>, the
	terms 'primary' and 'secondary' are used for two servers engaged in zone transfers.</t>
	<dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="7">
	  <dt>DoT:</dt> 
	  <dd>DNS over TLS, as specified in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref></dd>
	  <dt>XFR over TCP:</dt> 
	  <dd>Used to mean both IXFR over TCP <xref target="RFC1995"></xref> 
	  and AXFR over TCP <xref target="RFC5936"></xref></dd>
	  <dt>XoT:</dt> 
	  <dd>XFR-over-TLS mechanisms, as specified in this document, which apply 
	  to both AXFR over TLS and IXFR over TLS (XoT is pronounced 'zot' since X here
	  stands for 'zone transfer')</dd>
	  <dt>AXoT:</dt> 
	  <dd>AXFR over TLS</dd>
	  <dt>IXoT:</dt> 
	  <dd>IXFR over TLS</dd>
	</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="threat-model">
  <name>Threat Model</name>
  <t>The threat model considered here is one where the current contents and size of the zone are
  considered sensitive and should be protected during transfer.</t>
  <t>The threat model does not, however, consider the existence of a zone, the act of
  zone transfer between two entities, nor the identities of the name servers
  hosting a zone (including both those acting as hidden primaries/secondaries
  or directly serving the zone) as sensitive information. The proposed mechanism
  does not attempt to obscure such information. The reasons for this include:</t>
  <ul>
    <li>much of this information can be obtained by various methods, 
    including active scanning of the DNS, and</li>
    <li>an attacker who can monitor network traffic can rather 
    easily infer relations between name servers simply from traffic 
    patterns, even when some or all of the traffic is encrypted
    (in terms of current deployments).</li>
  </ul>
  <t>The model does not consider attacks on the mechanisms that trigger a zone transfer, e.g.,
  NOTIFY messages.</t>
  <t>It is noted that simply using XoT will indicate a desire by the zone owner that the
  contents of the zone remain confidential and so could be subject to blocking (e.g., via
  blocking of port 853) if an attacker had
  such capabilities. However, this threat is likely true of any such mechanism that attempts to
  encrypt data passed between name servers, e.g., IPsec.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="design-considerations-for-xot">
  <name>Design Considerations for XoT</name>
  <t>The following principles were considered in the design for XoT:</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Confidentiality:</dt> 
    <dd>Clearly using an encrypted transport for zone transfers will
    defeat zone content leakage that can occur via passive surveillance.</dd>
    <dt>Authentication:</dt> 
    <dd>Use of single or mutual TLS (mTLS) authentication (in combination
    with ACLs) can complement and potentially be an 
    alternative to TSIG.</dd>
    <dt>Performance:</dt>
    <dd>
      <ul>
	<li>Existing AXFR and IXFR mechanisms have the burden of backwards
	compatibility with older implementations based on the original specifications
	in <xref target="RFC1034"></xref> and <xref target="RFC1035"></xref>. For example, 
	some older AXFR servers don't
	support using a TCP connection for multiple AXFR sessions or XFRs of different
	zones because they have not been updated to follow the guidance in <xref
	target="RFC5936"></xref>.
	Any implementation of XoT would obviously be required to
	implement optimized and interoperable transfers, as described in <xref
	target="RFC5936"></xref>,
	e.g., transfer of multiple zones over one connection.</li>
	<li>Current usage of TCP for IXFR is suboptimal in some cases, i.e.,
	connections are frequently closed after a single IXFR.</li>
      </ul>
    </dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="connection-and-data-flows-in-existing-xfr-mechanisms">
  <name>Connection and Data Flows in Existing XFR Mechanisms</name>
  <t>The original specification for zone transfers in <xref target="RFC1034"></xref> and <xref
  target="RFC1035"></xref> was
  based on a polling mechanism: a secondary performed a periodic query for the SOA (start of
  zone authority) record (based
  on the refresh timer) to determine if an AXFR was required.</t>
  <t><xref target="RFC1995"></xref> and <xref target="RFC1996"></xref> introduced the concepts
  of IXFR and NOTIFY,
  respectively, to provide for prompt propagation of zone updates. This has
  largely replaced AXFR where possible, particularly for dynamically updated
  zones.</t>
  <t><xref target="RFC5936"></xref> subsequently redefined the specification of AXFR to improve
  performance and interoperability.</t>
  <t>In this document, the term 'XFR mechanism' is used to describe the entire set of
  message exchanges between a secondary and a primary that concludes with a
  successful AXFR or IXFR request/response. This set may or may not include:</t>
  <ul>
    <li>NOTIFY messages</li>
    <li>SOA queries</li>
    <li>Fallback from IXFR to AXFR</li>
    <li>Fallback from IXFR over UDP to IXFR over TCP</li>
  </ul>
  <t>The term is used to encompass the range of permutations that are possible and
  is useful to distinguish the 'XFR mechanism' from a single XFR
  request/response exchange.</t>

<section anchor="axfr-mechanism">
  <name>AXFR Mechanism</name>
  <t>The figure below provides an outline of an AXFR mechanism including NOTIFYs.</t>
  <figure anchor="fig1">
    <name>AXFR Mechanism</name>
<artwork name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
   Secondary                            Primary

       |              NOTIFY               |
       | <-------------------------------- |  UDP
       | --------------------------------> |
       |          NOTIFY Response          |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            SOA Request            |
       | --------------------------------> |  UDP (or part of
       | <-------------------------------- |  a TCP session)
       |           SOA Response            |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            AXFR Request           | ---
       | --------------------------------> |   |
       | <-------------------------------- |   |
       |          AXFR Response 1          |   |
       |             (Zone data)           |   |
       |                                   |   |
       | <-------------------------------- |   | TCP
       |          AXFR Response 2          |   | Session
       |             (Zone data)           |   |
       |                                   |   |
       | <-------------------------------- |   |
       |          AXFR Response 3          |   |
       |             (Zone data)           | ---
       |                                   |
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<ol>
  <li>An AXFR is often (but not always) preceded by a NOTIFY (over UDP) from the
  primary to the secondary. A secondary may also initiate an AXFR based on a
  refresh timer or scheduled/triggered zone maintenance.</li>
  <li>The secondary will normally (but not always) make an SOA query to the primary
  to obtain the serial number of the zone held by the primary.</li>
  <li>If the primary serial is higher than the secondary's serial (using Serial
  Number Arithmetic <xref target="RFC1982"></xref>), the secondary makes an AXFR request
  (over TCP)
  to the primary, after which the AXFR data flows in one or more AXFR responses on
  the TCP connection. <xref target="RFC5936"></xref> defines this specific step as an 'AXFR
  session',
  i.e., as an AXFR query message and the sequence of AXFR response messages
  returned for it.</li>
</ol>
<t><xref target="RFC5936"></xref> re-specified AXFR, providing additional guidance beyond that
provided in <xref target="RFC1034"></xref> and <xref target="RFC1035"></xref> and importantly
specified that AXFR must use TCP as the transport protocol.</t>
<t>Additionally, Sections <xref target="RFC5936" section="4.1" sectionFormat="bare"/>, <xref target="RFC5936" section="4.1.1" sectionFormat="bare"/>, and <xref target="RFC5936" section="4.1.2" sectionFormat="bare"/> of <xref target="RFC5936"></xref> provide improved
guidance for AXFR clients and servers with regard to reuse of TCP connections
for multiple AXFRs and AXFRs of different zones. However, <xref target="RFC5936"></xref> was
constrained by having to be backwards compatible with some very early basic
implementations of AXFR. For example, it outlines that the SOA query can also
happen on this connection. However, this can cause interoperability problems
with older implementations that support only the trivial case of one AXFR per
connection.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ixfr-mechanism">
  <name>IXFR Mechanism</name>
  <t>The figure below provides an outline of the IXFR mechanism including NOTIFYs.</t>
  <figure anchor="fig2">
    <name>IXFR Mechanism</name>
<artwork name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
   Secondary                            Primary

       |              NOTIFY               |
       | <-------------------------------- |  UDP
       | --------------------------------> |
       |          NOTIFY Response          |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            SOA Request            |
       | --------------------------------> |  UDP or TCP
       | <-------------------------------- |  
       |           SOA Response            |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            IXFR Request           |
       | --------------------------------> |  UDP or TCP
       | <-------------------------------- |
       |            IXFR Response          |
       |             (Zone data)           |
       |                                   |
       |                                   | ---
       |            IXFR Request           |    |
       | --------------------------------> |    | Retry over
       | <-------------------------------- |    | TCP if 
       |            IXFR Response          |    | required
       |             (Zone data)           | ---
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<ol>
  <li>An IXFR is normally (but not always) preceded by a NOTIFY (over UDP) from the
  primary to the secondary. A secondary may also initiate an IXFR based on a
  refresh timer or scheduled/triggered zone maintenance.</li>
  <li>The secondary will normally (but not always) make an SOA query to the primary
  to obtain the serial number of the zone held by the primary.</li>
  <li>If the primary serial is higher than the secondary's serial (using Serial
  Number Arithmetic <xref target="RFC1982"></xref>), the secondary makes an IXFR request to
  the primary, after which the primary sends an IXFR response.</li>
</ol>
<t><xref target="RFC1995"></xref> specifies that IXFR may use UDP if the entire IXFR
response can be contained in a single DNS packet, otherwise, TCP is used. In
fact, it says:</t>
<blockquote>Thus, a client should first make an IXFR query using UDP.</blockquote>
<t>So there may be a fourth step above where the client falls back to IXFR over TCP.
There may also be an additional step where the secondary must fall back to AXFR
because, e.g., the primary does not support IXFR.</t>
<t>However, it is noted that most of the widely used open-source implementations of authoritative name servers
(including both <xref target="BIND"></xref> and <xref target="NSD"></xref>) do IXFR using TCP by default
in their latest releases. For BIND, TCP connections are sometimes used for SOA
queries, but, in general, they are not used persistently and are closed after an IXFR
is completed.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="data-leakage-of-notify-and-soa-message-exchanges">
  <name>Data Leakage of NOTIFY and SOA Message Exchanges</name>
  <t>This section presents a rationale for considering the encryption of the other
  messages in the XFR mechanism.</t>
  <t>Since the SOA of the published zone can be trivially discovered by simply
  querying the publicly available authoritative servers, leakage of this resource record (RR)
  via such a
  direct query is not discussed in the following sections.</t>

<section anchor="notify">
  <name>NOTIFY</name>
  <t>Unencrypted NOTIFY messages identify configured secondaries on the primary.</t>
  <t><xref target="RFC1996"></xref> also states:</t>
  <blockquote>If ANCOUNT&gt;0, then the answer section represents an
  unsecure hint at the new RRset for this &lt;QNAME,QCLASS,QTYPE&gt;.</blockquote>
  
  <t>But since the only query type (QTYPE) for NOTIFY defined at the time of this writing
  is SOA, this does not pose a
  potential leak.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="soa">
  <name>SOA</name>
  <t>For hidden XFR servers (either primaries or secondaries), an SOA response
  directly from that server only additionally leaks the degree of SOA serial
  number lag of any downstream secondary of that server.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="updates-to-existing-specifications">
  <name>Updates to Existing Specifications</name>
  <t>For convenience, the term 'XFR over TCP' is used in this document to mean both
  IXFR over TCP and AXFR over TCP; therefore, statements that use that term update
  both <xref target="RFC1995"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5936"></xref> and implicitly also
  apply to XoT. Differences in behavior specific to XoT are discussed in
  <xref target="xot-specification"></xref>.</t>
  <t>Both <xref target="RFC1995"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5936"></xref> were published
  sometime before TCP became a widely supported transport for DNS. <xref
  target="RFC1995"></xref>, in fact, says nothing
  with respect to optimizing IXFRs over TCP or reusing already open TCP
  connections to perform IXFRs or other queries. Therefore, there arguably is an
  implicit assumption that a TCP connection is used for
  one and only one IXFR request. Indeed, many major open-source implementations
  take this approach (at the time of this writing). And whilst <xref target="RFC5936"></xref>
  gives guidance on
  connection reuse for AXFR, it predates more recent specifications describing
  persistent TCP connections (e.g., <xref target="RFC7766"></xref>, <xref
  target="RFC7828"></xref>), and AXFR implementations again
  often make less-than-optimal use of open connections.</t>
  <t>Given this, new implementations of XoT will clearly benefit from specific guidance on
  TCP/TLS connection usage for XFR, because this will:</t>  
<ul>
  <li>result in more consistent XoT implementations with better interoperability and</li>
  <li>remove any need for XoT implementations to support legacy behavior for XoT connections
  that XFR-over-TCP implementations have historically often supported.</li>
</ul>
<t>Therefore, this document updates both the previous specifications for
XFR over TCP (<xref target="RFC1995" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC5936" format="default"/>) to clarify that:</t>

<ul>
  <li>Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use <xref target="RFC7766"></xref> ("DNS Transport
  over TCP - Implementation Requirements") to optimize the use of TCP connections.</li>
  <li>Whilst <xref target="RFC7766" format="default"/> states that "DNS clients
  <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> pipeline their queries"
  on TCP connections, it did not distinguish between XFRs and other queries for this
  behavior. It is now recognized that XFRs are not as latency sensitive as
  other queries and can be significantly more complex for clients to handle,
  both because of the large amount of state that must be kept and because there
  may be multiple messages in the responses. For these reasons, it is clarified
  here that a valid reason for not pipelining queries is when they are all XFR
  queries, i.e., clients sending multiple XFRs <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose not to pipeline those
  queries. Clients that do not pipeline XFR queries therefore have no
  additional requirements to handle out-of-order or intermingled responses (as
  described later), since they will never receive them.</li>
  <li>Implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use the
  edns-tcp-keepalive EDNS(0) option <xref target="RFC7828"></xref> to manage 
  persistent connections. This is
  more flexible than the alternative of simply using fixed timeouts.</li>
</ul>
<t>The following sections include detailed clarifications on the updates to XFR
behavior implied in <xref target="RFC7766"></xref> and how the use of <xref target="RFC7828"></xref> applies
specifically to XFR exchanges. They also discuss how IXFR and AXFR can reuse
the same TCP connection.</t>
<t>For completeness, the recent specification of extended
DNS error (EDE) codes <xref target="RFC8914"></xref> is also mentioned here. For zone transfers, when returning REFUSED to a
zone transfer request from an 'unauthorized' client (e.g., where the client is not
listed in an ACL for zone transfers or does not sign the request with a
valid TSIG key), the extended DNS error code 18 - Prohibited can also be sent.</t>

<section anchor="update-to-rfc1995-for-ixfr-over-tcp">
  <name>Update to RFC 1995 for IXFR over TCP</name>
  <t>For clarity, an IXFR-over-TCP server compliant with this specification
  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
  able to handle multiple concurrent IXoT requests on a single TCP connection
  (for the same and different zones) and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> send the responses as soon as
  they are available, which might be out of order compared to the requests.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="update-to-rfc5936-for-axfr-over-tcp">
  <name>Update to RFC 5936 for AXFR over TCP</name>
  <t>For clarity, an AXFR-over-TCP server compliant with this specification
  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
  able to handle multiple concurrent AXoT sessions on a single TCP connection
  (for the same and different zones). The response streams for concurrent AXFRs
  <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be intermingled, and AXFR-over-TCP clients compliant with this
  specification, which pipeline AXFR requests, <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be able to handle this.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc1995-and-rfc5936-for-xfr-over-tcp">
  <name>Updates to RFCs 1995 and 5936 for XFR over TCP</name>
  <section anchor="connection-reuse">
    <name>Connection Reuse</name>
    <t>As specified, XFR-over-TCP clients <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> reuse any existing open TCP
    connection when
    starting any new XFR request to the same primary, and for issuing SOA queries,
    instead of opening a new connection. The number of TCP connections between a
    secondary and primary <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be minimized (also see <xref
    target="update-to-rfc7766"></xref>).</t>
    <t>Valid reasons for not reusing existing connections might include:</t>
    <ul>
      <li>As already noted in <xref target="RFC7766"></xref>, separate connections for
      different zones might be preferred for operational reasons. In this case, the number of
      concurrent connections for zone transfers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be limited to the total
      number of zones transferred between the client and server.</li>
      <li>A configured limit for the number of outstanding queries or XFR requests
      allowed on a single TCP connection has been reached.</li>
      <li>The message ID pool has already been exhausted on an open connection.</li>
      <li>A large number of timeouts or slow responses have occurred on an open
      connection.</li>
      <li>An edns-tcp-keepalive EDNS(0) option with a timeout of 0 has been received from the
      server, and the client is in the process of closing the connection (see <xref
      target="the-edns-tcp-keepalive-edns0-option"></xref>).</li>
    </ul>
    <t>If no TCP connections are currently open, XFR clients <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> send SOA
    queries over UDP or a new TCP connection.</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="axfrs-and-ixfrs-on-the-same-connection">
    <name>AXFRs and IXFRs on the Same Connection</name>
    <t>Neither <xref target="RFC1995"></xref> nor <xref target="RFC5936"></xref> explicitly
    discuss the use of a single TCP
    connection for both IXFR and AXFR requests. <xref target="RFC5936"></xref> does make the
    general statement:</t>
    <blockquote>Non-AXFR session traffic can also use an open connection.</blockquote>
    <t>In this document, the above is clarified to indicate that implementations capable of both AXFR and IXFR and
    compliant with this specification <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>:</t>
    <ul>
      <li>use the same TCP connection for both AXFR and IXFR requests to the same
      primary,</li>
      <li>pipeline such requests (if they pipeline XFR requests in general) and
      <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> intermingle them, and</li>
      <li>send the response(s) for each request as soon as they are available, i.e.,
      responses <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be sent intermingled.</li>
    </ul>
    <t>For some current implementations, adding all the above functionality would introduce
    significant code complexity. In such a case, there will need to be an assessment of the
    trade-off between that and the performance benefits of the above for XFR.</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="xfr-limits">
    <name>XFR Limits</name>
    <t>The server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> limit the number of concurrent IXFRs, AXFRs, or total XFR
    transfers in progress (or from a given secondary) to protect server resources.
    Servers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> return SERVFAIL if this limit is hit, since it is a
    transient error and a retry at a later time might succeed (there is no previous
    specification for this behavior).</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="the-edns-tcp-keepalive-edns0-option">
    <name>The edns-tcp-keepalive EDNS(0) Option</name>
    <t>XFR clients that send the edns-tcp-keepalive EDNS(0) option on every XFR request provide
    the server with maximum opportunity to update the edns-tcp-keepalive timeout. The XFR
    server may use the frequency of recent XFRs to calculate an average update rate as
    input to the decision of what edns-tcp-keepalive timeout to use. If the server
    does not support edns-tcp-keepalive, the client <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> keep the connection
    open for a few seconds (<xref target="RFC7766"></xref> recommends that servers use
    timeouts of at least a few seconds).</t>
    <t>Whilst the specification for EDNS(0)  <xref target="RFC6891"></xref>  does not
    specifically mention AXFRs, it does say:</t>
    <blockquote>If an OPT record is present in a received request, compliant
    responders <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include an OPT record in their respective
    responses.</blockquote>
    <t>In this document, the above is clarified to indicate that if an OPT record is present in a received AXFR request,
    compliant responders <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include an OPT record in each of the subsequent
    AXFR responses. Note that this requirement, combined with the use of
    edns-tcp-keepalive, enables AXFR servers to signal the desire to close a
    connection (when existing transactions have competed) due to low resources by
    sending an edns-tcp-keepalive EDNS(0) option with a timeout of 0 on any AXFR
    response. This does not signal that the AXFR is aborted, just that the server
    wishes to close the connection as soon as possible.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="backwards-compatibility">
    <name>Backwards Compatibility</name>
    <t>Certain legacy behaviors were noted in <xref target="RFC5936"></xref>, with provisions
    that implementations may want to offer options to fallback to legacy behavior when
    interoperating with servers known to not support <xref target="RFC5936"></xref>. For
    purposes of interoperability, IXFR and AXFR implementations may want to continue offering
    such configuration options, as well as supporting some behaviors that were
    underspecified prior to this work (e.g., performing IXFR and AXFRs on separate
    connections). However, XoT connections should have no need to do so.</t>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="update-to-rfc7766">
  <name>Update to RFC 7766</name>
  <t><xref target="RFC7766"></xref> made general implementation
  recommendations with regard to TCP/TLS connection handling:</t>
  <blockquote>To mitigate the risk of unintentional server overload, DNS
  clients <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> take care to minimize the number of concurrent TCP
  connections made to any individual server. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>
  that for any given client/server interaction there <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be no
  more than one connection for regular queries, one for zone
  transfers, and one for each protocol that is being used on top
  of TCP (for example, if the resolver was using TLS). However,
  it is noted that certain primary/ secondary configurations with
  many busy zones might need to use more than one TCP connection
  for zone transfers for operational reasons (for example, to
  support concurrent transfers of multiple zones).</blockquote>

  <t>Whilst this recommends a particular behavior for the clients using TCP, it
  does not relax the requirement for servers to handle 'mixed' traffic (regular
  queries and zone transfers) on any open TCP/TLS connection. It also overlooks the
  potential that other transports might want to take the same approach with regard to
  using separate connections for different purposes.</t>
  <t>This specification updates the above general guidance in <xref target="RFC7766"></xref>
  to provide the same separation of connection purpose (regular queries and zone transfers) for
  all transports being used on top of TCP.</t>
  <t>Therefore, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that for
  each protocol used on top of TCP in any given client/server interaction there
  <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be no more than one connection for regular queries and one for zone
  transfers.</t>
  <t>As an illustration, it could be imagined that in the future such an
  interaction could hypothetically include one or all of the following:</t>
  
  <ul>
    <li>one TCP connection for regular queries</li>
    <li>one TCP connection for zone transfers</li>
    <li>one TLS connection for regular queries</li>
    <li>one TLS connection for zone transfers</li>
    <li>one DoH connection for regular queries</li>
    <li>one DoH connection for zone transfers</li>
  </ul>
  
  <t><xref target="connection-reuse"></xref> provides specific details of the reasons why
  more than one connection for a given transport might be required for zone transfers from
  a particular client.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="xot-specification">
  <name>XoT Specification</name>

  <section anchor="connection-establishment">
    <name>Connection Establishment</name>
    <t>During connection establishment, the Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) token
    "dot" <xref target="DoT-ALPN"></xref> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be selected in the TLS
    handshake.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="tls-versions">
    <name>TLS Versions</name>
    <t>All implementations of this specification <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use only TLS 1.3 <xref
    target="RFC8446"></xref> or later.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="port-selection">
    <name>Port Selection</name>
    <t>The connection for XoT <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be established using port 853, as
    specified in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref>, unless there is mutual agreement between the
    primary and secondary to use a port other than port 853 for XoT. There <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
    be agreement to use different ports for AXoT and IXoT or for different zones.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="high-level-xot-descriptions">
    <name>High-Level XoT Descriptions</name>
    <t>It is useful to note that in XoT it is the secondary that initiates
    the TLS connection to the primary for an XFR request so that, in terms of
    connectivity, the secondary is the TLS client and the primary is the TLS server.</t>
    <t>The figure below provides an outline of the AXoT mechanism including NOTIFYs.</t>
    <figure anchor="fig3">
      <name>AXoT Mechanism</name>
<artwork name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
   Secondary                            Primary

       |              NOTIFY               |
       | <-------------------------------- |  UDP
       | --------------------------------> |
       |          NOTIFY Response          |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            SOA Request            |
       | --------------------------------> |  UDP (or part of
       | <-------------------------------- |  a TCP/TLS session)
       |           SOA Response            |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            AXFR Request           | ---
       | --------------------------------> |   |
       | <-------------------------------- |   |
       |          AXFR Response 1          |   |
       |             (Zone data)           |   |
       |                                   |   |
       | <-------------------------------- |   | TLS
       |          AXFR Response 2          |   | Session
       |             (Zone data)           |   |
       |                                   |   |
       | <-------------------------------- |   |
       |          AXFR Response 3          |   |
       |             (Zone data)           | ---
       |                                   |
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<t>The figure below provides an outline of the IXoT mechanism including NOTIFYs.</t>
<figure anchor="fig4">
  <name>IXoT Mechanism</name>
<artwork name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
   Secondary                            Primary

       |              NOTIFY               |
       | <-------------------------------- |  UDP
       | --------------------------------> |
       |          NOTIFY Response          |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            SOA Request            |
       | --------------------------------> |  UDP (or part of
       | <-------------------------------- |  a TCP/TLS session)
       |           SOA Response            |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |                                   |
       |            IXFR Request           | ---
       | --------------------------------> |    |
       | <-------------------------------- |    |
       |            IXFR Response          |    |
       |             (Zone data)           |    |
       |                                   |    | TLS
       |                                   |    | session
       |            IXFR Request           |    |
       | --------------------------------> |    |
       | <-------------------------------- |    |
       |            IXFR Response          |    |
       |             (Zone data)           | ---     
]]></artwork>
</figure>
</section>

<section anchor="xot-transfers">
  <name>XoT Transfers</name>
  <t>For a zone transfer between two endpoints to be considered protected with XoT,
  all XFR requests and responses for that zone <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be sent over TLS connections,
  where at a minimum:</t>

  <ul>
    <li>The client <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> authenticate the server by use of an authentication
    domain name using a Strict Privacy profile, as described in <xref
    target="RFC8310"></xref>.</li>
    <li><t>The server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate the client is authorized to request or proxy
    a zone transfer by using one or both of the following methods:</t>
    <ul>
      <li>mutual TLS (mTLS)</li>
      <li>an IP-based ACL (which can be either per message or per connection)
      combined with a valid TSIG/SIG(0) signature on the XFR request</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <t>If only one method is selected, then mTLS is preferred because it provides strong
  cryptographic protection at both endpoints.</t>
  <t>Authentication mechanisms are discussed in full in <xref
  target="authentication-mechanisms"></xref>,
  and the rationale for the above requirement is discussed in <xref
  target="xot-authentication"></xref>.
  Transfer group policies are discussed in <xref
  target="policies-for-both-axot-and-ixot"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="xot-connections">
  <name>XoT Connections</name>
  <t>The details in <xref target="updates-to-existing-specifications"></xref> about, e.g.,
  persistent connections and XFR message handling, are fully applicable to XoT connections as
  well. However, any behavior specified here takes precedence for XoT.</t>
  <t>If no TLS connections are currently open, XoT clients <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> send SOA queries
  over UDP, TCP, or TLS.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="xot-vs-adot">
  <name>XoT vs. ADoT</name>
  <t>As noted earlier, there is currently no specification for encryption of
  connections from recursive resolvers to authoritative servers. Some
  authoritative servers are experimenting with ADoT, and opportunistic encryption
  has also been raised as a possibility; therefore, it is highly likely that use
  of encryption by authoritative servers will evolve in the coming years.</t>
  <t>This raises questions in the short term with regard to TLS connection and
  message handling for authoritative servers. In particular, there is likely to be
  a class of authoritative servers that wish to use XoT in the near future with a
  small number of configured secondaries but that do not wish to support DoT for
  regular queries from recursives in that same time frame. These servers have to
  potentially cope with probing and direct queries from recursives and from test
  servers and also potential attacks that might wish to make use of TLS to
  overload the server.</t>
  <t><xref target="RFC5936"></xref> clearly states that non-AXFR session traffic can use an
  open connection; however, this requirement needs to be reevaluated when considering
  the application of the same model to XoT. Proposing that a server should also start
  responding to all queries received over TLS just because it has enabled XoT
  would be equivalent to defining a form of authoritative DoT. This specification
  does not propose that, but it also does not prohibit servers from answering
  queries unrelated to XFR exchanges over TLS. Rather, this specification
  simply outlines in later sections:</t>

  <ul>
    <li>the utilization of EDE codes by XoT servers in response to queries on TLS
    connections that they are not willing to answer (see <xref
    target="response-rcodes"></xref>)</li>
    <li>the operational and policy options that an operator of a XoT server has
    with regard to managing TLS connections and messages (see <xref
    target="xot-server-connection-handling"></xref>)</li>
  </ul>
</section>

<section anchor="response-rcodes">
  <name>Response RCODES</name>
  <t>XoT clients and servers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> implement EDE codes. If a XoT server receives
  non-XoT traffic it is not willing to answer on a TLS connection, it <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
  respond with REFUSED and the extended DNS error code 21 - Not Supported
  <xref target="RFC8914"></xref>. XoT clients should not send any further
  queries of this type to the server for a reasonable period of time (for
  example, one hour), i.e., long enough that the server configuration or policy
  might be updated.</t>
  <t>Historically, servers have used the REFUSED RCODE for many situations; therefore,
  clients often had no detailed information on which to base an error or fallback
  path when queries were refused. As a result, the client behavior could vary
  significantly. XoT servers that refuse queries must cater to the fact that
  client behavior might vary from continually retrying queries regardless of
  receiving REFUSED to every query or, at the other extreme, clients may decide to
  stop using the server over any transport. This might be because those clients are
  either non-XoT clients or do not implement EDE codes.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="axot-specifics">
  <name>AXoT Specifics</name>
  <section anchor="padding-axot-responses">
    <name>Padding AXoT Responses</name>
    <t>The goal of padding AXoT responses is two fold:</t>

    <ul>
      <li>to obfuscate the actual size of the transferred zone to minimize information
      leakage about the entire contents of the zone</li>
      <li>to obfuscate the incremental changes to the zone between SOA updates to
      minimize information leakage about zone update activity and growth</li>
    </ul>
    <t>Note that the reuse of XoT connections for transfers of multiple different
    zones slightly complicates any attempt to analyze the traffic size and timing to
    extract information.  Also, effective padding may require the state to be kept
    because zones may grow and/or shrink over time.</t>
    <t>It is noted here that, depending on the padding policies eventually developed for XoT,
    the requirement to obfuscate the total zone size might
    require a server to create 'empty' AXoT responses, that is, AXoT responses that
    contain no RRs apart from an OPT RR containing the EDNS(0) option for padding.
    For example, without this capability, the maximum size that a tiny zone could be padded to
    would theoretically be limited if there had to be a minimum of 1 RR per packet.</t>
    <t>However, as with existing AXFR, the last AXoT response message sent <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
    contain the same SOA that was in the first message of the AXoT response series
    in order to signal the conclusion of the zone transfer.</t>
    <t><xref target="RFC5936"></xref> says:</t>
    <blockquote>Each AXFR response message <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> contain a sufficient number
    of RRs to reasonably amortize the per-message overhead, up to
    the largest number that will fit within a DNS message (taking
    the required content of the other sections into account, as
    described below).</blockquote>

    <t>'Empty' AXoT responses generated in order to meet a padding requirement will be
    exceptions to the above statement. For flexibility, for future proofing, and in
    order to guarantee support for future padding policies, it is stated here that
    secondary implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be resilient to receiving padded AXoT
    responses, including 'empty' AXoT responses that contain only an OPT RR containing the
    EDNS(0) option for padding.</t>
    <t>Recommendations of specific policies for padding AXoT responses are out of scope
    for this specification. Detailed considerations of such policies and the
    trade-offs involved are expected to be the subject of future work.</t>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="ixot-specifics">
  <name>IXoT Specifics</name>

  <section anchor="condensation-of-responses">
    <name>Condensation of Responses</name>
    <t><xref target="RFC1995"></xref> says that condensation of responses is optional and
    <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be done. Whilst
    it does add complexity to generating responses, it can significantly reduce the
    size of responses. However, any such reduction might be offset by increased
    message size due to padding. This specification does not update the optionality
    of condensation for XoT responses.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="fallback-to-axfr">
    <name>Fallback to AXFR</name>
    <t>Fallback to AXFR can happen, for example, if the server is not able to provide
    an IXFR for the requested SOA. Implementations differ in how long they store
    zone deltas and how many may be stored at any one time.</t>
    <t>Just as with IXFR over TCP, after a failed IXFR, an IXoT client <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
    request the AXFR on the already open XoT connection.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="padding-of-ixot-responses">
    <name>Padding of IXoT Responses</name>
    <t>The goal of padding IXoT responses is to obfuscate the incremental
    changes to the zone between SOA updates to minimize information leakage about
    zone update activity and growth. Both the size and timing of the IXoT responses could
    reveal information.</t>
    <t>IXFR responses can vary greatly in size from the order of 100 bytes for one or
    two record updates to tens of thousands of bytes for large, dynamic DNSSEC-signed zones.
    The frequency of IXFR responses can also depend greatly on if and how the zone is DNSSEC
    signed.</t>
    <t>In order to guarantee support for future padding policies, it is stated here
    that
    secondary implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be resilient to receiving padded IXoT
    responses.</t>
    <t>Recommendation of specific policies for padding IXoT responses are out of scope
    for this specification. Detailed considerations of such padding policies, the
    use of traffic obfuscation techniques (such as generating fake XFR traffic), and
    the trade-offs involved are expected to be the subject of future work.</t>
  </section>
</section>

<section anchor="name-compression-and-maximum-payload-sizes">
  <name>Name Compression and Maximum Payload Sizes</name>
  <t>It is noted here that name compression <xref target="RFC1035"></xref> can be used in XFR
  responses to reduce the size of the payload; however, the maximum value of the offset that
  can be used in the name compression pointer structure is 16384. For some DNS
  implementations, this limits the size of an individual XFR response used in
  practice to something around the order of 16 KB. In principle, larger
  payload sizes can be supported for some responses with more sophisticated
  approaches (e.g., by precalculating the maximum offset required).</t>
  <t>Implementations may wish to offer options to disable name compression for XoT
  responses to enable larger payloads. This might be particularly helpful when
  padding is used, since minimizing the payload size is not necessarily a useful
  optimization in this case and disabling name compression will reduce the
  resources required to construct the payload.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="multi-primary-configurations">
  <name>Multi-primary Configurations</name>
  <t>This model can provide flexibility
  and redundancy, particularly for IXFR. A secondary will receive one or more
  NOTIFY messages and can send an SOA to all of the configured primaries. It can
  then choose to send an XFR request to the primary with the highest SOA (or
  based on other criteria, e.g., RTT).</t>
  <t>When using persistent connections, the secondary may have a XoT connection
  already open to one or more primaries. Should a secondary preferentially
  request an XFR from a primary to which it already has an open XoT connection
  or the one with the highest SOA (assuming it doesn't have a connection open to
  it already)?</t>
  <t>Two extremes can be envisaged here. The first one can be considered a 'preferred
  primary connection' model. In this case, the secondary continues to use one
  persistent connection to a single primary until it has reason not to. Reasons
  not to might include the primary repeatedly closing the connection, long query/response RTTs
  on transfers, or the SOA of the primary being an unacceptable lag behind the SOA of
  an alternative primary.</t>
  <t>The other extreme can be considered a 'parallel primary connection' model. Here,
  a secondary could keep multiple persistent connections open to all available
  primaries and only request XFRs from the primary with the highest serial number.
  Since normally the number of secondaries and primaries in direct contact in a
  transfer group is reasonably low, this might be feasible if latency is the most
  significant concern.</t>
<t>Recommendation of a particular scheme is out of scope of this document, but
implementations are encouraged to provide configuration options that allow
operators to make choices about this behavior.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="authentication-mechanisms">
  <name>Authentication Mechanisms</name>
  <t>To provide context to the requirements in <xref target="xot-transfers"></xref>, this
  section provides a brief summary of some of the existing authentication and
  validation mechanisms (both transport independent and TLS specific) that are
  available when performing zone transfers.
  <xref target="xot-authentication"></xref> then discusses in more detail specifically how a
  combination of TLS authentication, TSIG, and IP-based ACLs interact for XoT.</t>
  <t>In this document, the mechanisms are classified based on the following properties:</t>

  <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Data Origin Authentication (DO):</dt>
    <dd>Authentication 1) of the fact that the DNS message originated
    from the party with whom credentials were shared and 2) of the data integrity
    of the message contents (the originating party may or may not be the party
    operating the far end of a TCP/TLS connection in a 'proxy' scenario).</dd>
    <dt>Channel Confidentiality (CC):</dt> 
    <dd>Confidentiality of the communication channel between the
    client and server (i.e., the two endpoints of a TCP/TLS connection) from passive
    surveillance.</dd>
    <dt>Channel Authentication (CA):</dt> 
    <dd>Authentication of the identity of the party to whom a TCP/TLS
    connection is made (this might not be a direct connection between the primary
    and secondary in a proxy scenario).</dd>
  </dl>

<section anchor="tsig">
  <name>TSIG</name>
  <t>TSIG <xref target="RFC8945"></xref> provides a mechanism for two or more parties to use
  shared secret keys that can then be used to create a message digest to protect
  individual DNS messages. This allows each party to authenticate that a request
  or response (and the data in it) came from the other party, even if it was
  transmitted over an unsecured channel or via a proxy.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Properties:</dt> 
    <dd>Data origin authentication.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="sig-0">
  <name>SIG(0)</name>
  <t>SIG(0) <xref target="RFC2931"></xref> similarly provides a mechanism to digitally sign a
  DNS message but uses public key authentication, where the public keys are stored in
  DNS as KEY RRs and a private key is stored at the signer.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Properties:</dt> 
    <dd>Data origin authentication.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="tls">
  <name>TLS</name>
  <section anchor="opportunistic-tls">
    <name>Opportunistic TLS</name>
    <t>Opportunistic TLS for DoT is defined in <xref target="RFC8310"></xref> and can provide a
    defense against passive
    surveillance, providing on-the-wire confidentiality. Essentially:</t>
    <ul spacing="normal">
      <li>if clients know authentication information for a server, they
      <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> try to authenticate the server,</li>
      <li>if this fails or clients do not know the information, they <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
      fallback to using TLS without authentication, or</li>
      <li>clients <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> fallback to using cleartext if TLS is not
      available.</li>
    </ul>
    <t>As such, it does not offer a defense against active attacks (e.g., an on-path active
    attacker on the connection from client to server) and is not considered as useful for
    XoT.</t>
    <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
      <dt>Properties:</dt> 
      <dd>None guaranteed.</dd>
    </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="strict-tls">
  <name>Strict TLS</name>
  <t>Strict TLS for DoT <xref target="RFC8310"></xref> requires that a client is configured
  with an authentication domain name (and/or Subject Public Key Info (SPKI) pin set) that
  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used to
  authenticate the TLS handshake with the server. If authentication of the server
  fails, the client will not proceed with the connection. This provides a defense
  for the client against active surveillance, providing client-to-server
  authentication and end-to-end channel confidentiality.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
    <dt>Properties:</dt> 
    <dd>Channel confidentiality and channel authentication (of the server).</dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="mutual-tls">
  <name>Mutual TLS</name>
  <t>This is an extension to Strict TLS <xref target="RFC8310"></xref> that requires that a
  client is configured with an authentication domain name (and/or SPKI pin set) and a client
  certificate. The client offers the certificate for authentication by the server,
  and the client can authenticate the server the same way as in Strict TLS. This
  provides a defense for both parties against active surveillance, providing
  bidirectional authentication and end-to-end channel confidentiality.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
    <dt>Properties:</dt> 
    <dd>Channel confidentiality and mutual channel authentication.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="ip-based-acl-on-the-primary">
  <name>IP-Based ACL on the Primary</name>
  <t>Most DNS server implementations offer an option to configure an IP-based 
  ACL, which is often used in combination with TSIG-based ACLs to
  restrict access to zone transfers on primary servers on a per-query basis.</t>
  <t>This is also possible with XoT, but it must be noted that, as with TCP, the
  implementation of such an ACL cannot be enforced on the primary until an XFR
  request is received on an established connection.</t>
  <t>As discussed in <xref target="xot-server-connection-handling"></xref>, an 
  IP-based per-connection ACL could also be implemented where only TLS connections from
  recognized secondaries are accepted.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Properties:</dt>
    <dd>Channel authentication of the client.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="zonemd">
  <name>ZONEMD</name>
  <t>For completeness, ZONEMD
  <xref target="RFC8976" format="default"/> ("Message Digest for DNS Zones") is described here. 
  The ZONEMD message digest
  is a mechanism that can be used to verify the content of a standalone zone. It
  is designed to be independent of the transmission channel or mechanism, allowing
  a general consumer of a zone to do origin authentication of the entire zone
  contents. Note that the current version of <xref target="RFC8976"></xref>
  states:</t>
  <blockquote>As specified herein, ZONEMD is impractical for large, dynamic zones due to the
  time and resources required for digest calculation. However, the ZONEMD record
  is extensible so that new digest schemes may be added in the future to support
  large, dynamic zones.</blockquote>
  <t>It is complementary but orthogonal to the above mechanisms and can be used in
  conjunction with XoT but is not considered further here.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="xot-authentication">
  <name>XoT Authentication</name>
  <t>It is noted that zone transfer scenarios can vary from a simple single
  primary/secondary relationship where both servers are under the control of a
  single operator to a complex hierarchical structure that includes proxies and
  multiple operators. Each deployment scenario will require specific analysis to
  determine which combination of authentication methods are best suited to the
  deployment model in question.</t>
  <t>The XoT authentication requirement specified in <xref target="xot-transfers"></xref>
  addresses the
  issue of ensuring that the transfers are encrypted between the two endpoints
  directly involved in the current transfers. The following table summarizes the
  properties of a selection of the mechanisms discussed in
  <xref target="authentication-mechanisms"></xref>. The two-letter abbreviations for the properties
  are used below: (S) indicates the secondary and (P) indicates
  the primary.</t>
  <table anchor="table1">
    <name>Properties of Authentication Methods for XoT</name>
    <thead>
      <tr>
	<th align="left">Method</th>
	<th align="center">DO(S)</th>
	<th align="center">CC(S)</th>
	<th align="center">CA(S)</th>
	<th align="center">DO(P)</th>
	<th align="center">CC(P)</th>
	<th align="center">CA(P)</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    
    <tbody>
      <tr>
	<td align="left">Strict TLS</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
	<td align="left">Mutual TLS</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
	<td align="left">ACL on primary</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
	<td align="left">TSIG</td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center">Y</td>
	<td align="center"></td>
	<td align="center"></td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <t>Based on this analysis, it can be seen that:</t>
  <ul>
    <li>Using just mutual TLS can be considered a standalone solution since both endpoints are
    cryptographically authenticated.</li>
    <li>Using secondary-side Strict TLS with a primary-side IP-based ACL and TSIG/SIG(0) combination
    provides sufficient protection to be acceptable.</li>
  </ul>

  <t>Using just an IP-based ACL could be susceptible to attacks that can spoof TCP IP
  addresses; using TSIG/SIG(0) alone could be susceptible to attacks that were
  able to capture such messages should they be accidentally sent in cleartext by any server
  with the key.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="policies-for-both-axot-and-ixot">
  <name>Policies for Both AXoT and IXoT</name>
  <t>Whilst the protection of the zone contents in a transfer between two endpoints
  can be provided by the XoT protocol, the protection of all the transfers of a
  given zone requires operational administration and policy management.</t>
  <t>The entire group of servers involved in XFR for a particular set of
  zones (all the primaries and all the secondaries) is called the 'transfer group'.</t>
  <t>In order to assure the confidentiality of the zone information, the entire
  transfer group <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have a consistent policy of using XoT. If any do not, this
  is a weak link for attackers to exploit. For clarification, this means that
  within any transfer group both AXFRs and IXFRs for a zone <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> all use
  XoT.</t>
  <t>An individual zone transfer is not considered protected by XoT unless
  both the client and server are configured to use only XoT, and the overall zone
  transfer is not considered protected until all members of the transfer group
  are configured to use only XoT with all other transfers servers (see <xref
  target="implementation-considerations"></xref>).</t>
  <t>A XoT policy <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> specify if:</t>
  <ul>
    <li>mutual TLS is used and/or</li>
    <li>an IP-based ACL and TSIG/SIG(0) combination is used.</li>
  </ul>
  <t>Since this may require configuration of a number of servers who may be under
  the control of different operators, the desired consistency could be hard to
  enforce and audit in practice.</t>
  <t>Certain aspects of the policies can be relatively easy to test independently,
  e.g., by requesting zone transfers without TSIG, from unauthorized IP addresses
  or over cleartext DNS. Other aspects, such as if a secondary will accept data
  without a TSIG digest or if secondaries are using Strict as opposed to
  Opportunistic TLS, are more challenging.</t>
  <t>The mechanics of coordinating or enforcing such policies are out of the scope
  of this document but may be the subject of future operational guidance.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="implementation-considerations">
  <name>Implementation Considerations</name>
  <t>Server implementations may want to also offer options that allow ACLs on a zone
  to specify that a specific client can use either XoT or TCP. This would allow
  for flexibility while clients are migrating to XoT.</t>
  <t>Client implementations may similarly want to offer options to cater to the
  multi-primary case where the primaries are migrating to XoT.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="operational-considerations">
  <name>Operational Considerations</name>
  <t>If the options described in <xref target="implementation-considerations"></xref> are
  available,
  such configuration options <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be used in a 'migration mode' and
  therefore should be used with great care.</t>
  <t>It is noted that use of a TLS proxy in front of the primary server is a simple
  deployment solution that can enable server-side XoT.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations">
  <name>IANA Considerations</name>
  <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations">
<name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>This document specifies a security measure against a DNS risk: the risk that an
attacker collects entire DNS zones through eavesdropping on cleartext DNS zone
transfers.</t>
<t>This does not mitigate:</t>

<ul>
  <li>the risk that some level of zone activity might be inferred by observing zone
  transfer sizes and timing on encrypted connections (even with padding
  applied), in combination with obtaining SOA records by directly querying
  authoritative servers,</li>
  <li>the risk that hidden primaries might be inferred or identified via
  observation of encrypted connections, or</li>
  <li>the risk of zone contents being obtained via zone enumeration techniques.</li>
</ul>
<t>Security concerns of DoT are outlined in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref> and <xref target="RFC8310"></xref>.</t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>

  <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsoquic" to="DPRIVE-DNSOQUIC"/>
  <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-tls-esni" to="TLS-ESNI"/>
  <displayreference target="I-D.vcelak-nsec5" to="NSEC5"/>

<references>
  <name> References</name>
<references>
  <name>Normative References</name>
  <reference anchor="DoT-ALPN"	   target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-extensiontype-values/">
    <front>
      <title>TLS Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation (ALPN) Protocol IDs</title>
      <author>
	<organization>IANA</organization>
      </author>
    </front>
  </reference>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1995.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1996.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2931.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5936.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7766.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7828.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8310.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8914.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8945.xml"/>
</references>
<references>
<name>Informative References</name>

<reference anchor="BIND" target="https://www.isc.org/bind/">
  <front>
    <title>BIND 9.16.16</title>
    <author>
      <organization>ISC</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>

<xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-ietf-dprive-dnsoquic-03.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9076.xml"/>

<xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tls-esni-13.xml"/>

<reference anchor="I-D.vcelak-nsec5">
   <front>
      <title>NSEC5, DNSSEC Authenticated Denial of Existence</title>
      <author initials="J." surname="Vcelak" fullname="Jan Vcelak">
         <organization>CZ.NIC</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="S." surname="Goldberg" fullname="Sharon Goldberg">
         <organization>Boston University</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="D." surname="Papadopoulos" fullname="Dimitrios Papadopoulos">
         <organization>HKUST</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="S." surname="Huque" fullname="Shumon Huque">
         <organization>Salesforce</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="D." surname="Lawrence" fullname="David C Lawrence">
         <organization>Dyn</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="December" day="29" year="2018" />
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-vcelak-nsec5-08" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="NSD" target="https://www.nlnetlabs.nl/projects/nsd/about/">
  <front>
    <title>NSD 4.3.6</title>
    <author>
      <organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="NSEC3-attacks" target="https://www.cs.bu.edu/~goldbe/papers/nsec3attacks.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Stretching NSEC3 to the Limit: Efficient Zone Enumeration Attacks on NSEC3
    Variants</title>
    <author fullname="Sharon Goldberg" initials="S." surname="Goldberg">
      <organization> Boston University, Department of Computer Science</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Moni Naor" initials="N." surname="Naor">
      <organization>Weizmann Institute of Science, Department of Computer Science and Applied
      Mathematics</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Dimitrios Papadopoulos" initials="D." surname="Papadopoulos">
      <organization> Boston University, Department of Computer Science</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Leonid Reyzin" initials="L." surname="Reyzin">
      <organization> Boston University, Department of Computer Science</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Sachin Vasant" initials="S." surname="Vasant">
      <organization> Boston University, Department of Computer Science</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Asaf Ziv" initials="A." surname="Ziv">
      <organization>Weizmann Institute of Science, Department of Computer Science and Applied
      Mathematics</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2015"></date>
  </front>
</reference>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1982.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5155.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6891.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8484.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8976.xml"/>

<reference anchor="NIST-GUIDE" target="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/SpecialPublications/NIST.SP.800-81-2.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Secure Domain Name System (DNS) Deployment Guide</title>
    <author fullname="Ramaswamy Chandramouli" initials="R." surname="Chandramouli">
      <organization>NIST</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Scott Rose" initials="S." surname="Rose">
      <organization>NIST</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year="2013"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
</references>
</references>

<section anchor="xot-server-connection-handling">
  <name>XoT Server Connection Handling</name>
  <t>This appendix provides a non-normative outline of the pros and cons of XoT server
  connection-handling options.</t>
  <t>For completeness, it is noted that an earlier draft version of this document
  suggested using a XoT-specific ALPN to negotiate TLS connections that supported
  only a limited set of queries (SOA, XFRs); however, this did not gain support.
  Reasons given included additional code complexity and the fact that XoT and ADoT are both
  DNS wire format and so should share the <tt>dot</tt> ALPN.</t>

<section anchor="only-listen-on-tls-on-a-specific-ip-address">
  <name>Listening Only on a Specific IP Address for TLS</name>
  <t>Obviously, a name server that hosts a zone and services queries for the zone on
  an IP address published in an NS record may wish to use a separate IP address
  for XoT to listen for TLS, only publishing that address to its secondaries.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Pros:</dt> 
    <dd>Probing of the public IP address will show no support for TLS. ACLs will
    prevent zone transfer on all transports on a per-query basis.</dd>
    <dt>Cons:</dt> 
    <dd>Attackers passively observing traffic will still be able to observe TLS
    connections to the separate address.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="client-specific-tls-acceptance">
  <name>Client-Specific TLS Acceptance</name>
  <t>Primaries that include IP-based ACLs and/or mutual TLS in their authentication models
  have the option of only accepting TLS connections from authorized clients. This
  could be implemented either using a proxy or directly in the DNS implementation.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Pros:</dt> 
    <dd>Connection management happens at setup time. The maximum number of TLS
    connections a server will have to support can be easily assessed. Once the
    connection is accepted, the server might well be willing to answer any query on
    that connection since it is coming from a configured secondary, and a specific
    response policy on the connection may not be needed (see below).</dd>
    <dt>Cons:</dt> 
    <dd>Currently, none of the major open-source 
    implementations of a DNS authoritative server support such an option.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="sni-based-tls-acceptance">
  <name>SNI-Based TLS Acceptance</name>
  <t>Primaries could also choose to only accept TLS connections based on a Server Name
  Indication (SNI) that was published only to their secondaries.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Pros:</dt> 
    <dd>Reduces the number of accepted connections.</dd>
    <dt>Cons:</dt> 
    <dd>As above. Also, this is not a recommended use of SNI. For SNIs sent in the
    clear, this would still allow attackers passively observing traffic to
    potentially abuse this mechanism. The use of Encrypted Client Hello
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-esni"></xref> may be of use here.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>

<section anchor="transport-specific-response-policies">
  <name>Transport-Specific Response Policies</name>
  <t>Some primaries might rely on TSIG/SIG(0) combined with per-query, IP-based
  ACLs to authenticate secondaries. In this case, the primary must accept all
  incoming TLS/TCP connections and then apply a transport-specific response policy on a
  per-query basis.</t>
  <t>As an aside, whilst <xref target="RFC7766"></xref> makes a general purpose distinction in
  the advice to clients
  about their usage of connections (between regular queries and zone transfers), this is
  not strict, and nothing in the DNS protocol prevents using the same connection
  for both types of traffic. Hence, a server cannot know the intention of any
  client that connects to it; it can only inspect the messages it receives on
  such a connection and make per-query decisions about whether or not to answer
  those queries.</t>
  <t>Example policies a XoT server might implement are:</t>

  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="12">
    <dt>strict:</dt> 
    <dd>REFUSE all queries on TLS connections, except SOA and authorized XFR requests</dd>
    <dt>moderate:</dt> 
    <dd>REFUSE all queries on TLS connections until one is received that is
    signed by a recognized TSIG/SIG(0) key, then answer all queries on the
    connection after that</dd>
    <dt>complex:</dt> 
    <dd>apply a heuristic to determine which queries on a TLS connections to REFUSE</dd>
    <dt>relaxed:</dt> 
    <dd>answer all non-XoT queries on all TLS connections with the same policy applied to TCP
    queries</dd>
  </dl>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Pros:</dt> 
    <dd>Allows for flexible behavior by the server that could be changed over time.</dd>
    <dt>Cons:</dt> 
    <dd>The server must handle the burden of accepting all TLS connections just
    to perform XFRs with a small number of secondaries. Client behavior to a REFUSED
    response is not clearly defined (see <xref target="response-rcodes"></xref>). Currently,
    none of the major open-source implementations of a DNS authoritative server offer an option for different response
    policies in different transports (but such functionality could potentially be implemented
    using a proxy).</dd>
  </dl>

<section anchor="sni-based-response-policies">
  <name>SNI-Based Response Policies</name>
  <t>In a similar fashion, XoT servers might use the presence of an SNI in the
  Client Hello to determine which response policy to initially apply to the TLS
  connections.</t>
  <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
    <dt>Pros:</dt> 
    <dd>This has the potential to allow a clean distinction between a XoT service
    and any future DoT-based service for answering recursive queries.</dd>
    <dt>Cons:</dt> 
    <dd>As above.</dd>
  </dl>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false">
  <name>Acknowledgements</name>
  <t>The authors thank <contact fullname="Tony Finch"/>, <contact fullname="Benno
  Overeinder"/>, <contact fullname="Shumon Huque"/>,
  <contact fullname="Tim Wicinski"/>, and many other members of DPRIVE for review and
  discussions.</t>
  <t>The authors particularly thank <contact fullname="Peter van Dijk"/>, 
  <contact fullname="Ondrej Sury"/>, <contact fullname="Brian Dickson"/>, and
  several other open-source DNS implementers for valuable discussion and
  clarification on the issue associated with pipelining XFR queries and handling
  out-of-order/intermingled responses.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="contributors" numbered="false">
  <name>Contributors</name>
  <t>Significant contributions to the document were made by:</t>
  <contact fullname="Han Zhang">
    <organization>Salesforce</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
	<street/>
	<city>San Francisco</city> 
	<region>CA</region>
	<country>United States of America</country>
      </postal>
      <email>hzhang@salesforce.com</email>
    </address>
  </contact>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
