<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-stir-rph-emergency-services-07" number="9027" obsoletes="" updates=""
submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.5.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RPH Values for Emergency Services">Assertion Values for Resource Priority Header and SIP Priority Header Claims in Support of Emergency Services Networks</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9027"/>
    <author initials="M." surname="Dolly" fullname="Martin Dolly">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
      <address>
        <email>md3135@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Wendt" fullname="Chris Wendt">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Comcast Technology Center</street>
	  <city>Philadelphia</city>
	  <region>PA</region>
	  <code>19103</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>chris-ietf@chriswendt.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2021" month="June"/>
    <area>ART</area>
    <workgroup>STIR</workgroup>
    <keyword>rph</keyword>
    <keyword>PASSporT</keyword>
    <keyword>esnet</keyword>

<abstract>
      <t>This document adds new assertion values for a Resource Priority Header ("rph") claim and a new SIP Priority Header ("sph") claim for protection of the "psap-callback" value as part of the "rph" Personal Assertion Token (PASSporT) extension in support of the security of emergency services networks for emergency call origination and callback.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>"Personal Assertion Token (PASSporT) Extension for Resource Priority Authorization" <xref target="RFC8443" format="default"/> extended the Personal Assertion Token (PASSporT) specification defined in <xref target="RFC8225" format="default"/> to allow the inclusion of cryptographically signed assertions of authorization for the values populated in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) 'Resource-Priority' header field <xref target="RFC4412" format="default"/>. <xref target="I-D.rosen-stir-emergency-calls" format="default"/> introduces the need and justification for the protection of both the SIP 'Resource-Priority' and 'Priority' header fields, used for categorizing the priority use of the call in the telephone network, specifically for emergency calls.</t>
      <t>Compromise of the SIP 'Resource-Priority' or 'Priority' header fields could lead to misuse of network resources (i.e., during congestion scenarios), impacting the application services supported using the SIP 'Resource-Priority' header field and the handling of Public Safety Answering Point (PSAP) callbacks.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8225" format="default"/> allows extensions by which an authority on the originating side verifying the authorization of a particular communication for the SIP 'Resource-Priority' header field or the SIP 'Priority' header field can use PASSporT claims to cryptographically sign the information associated with either the SIP 'Resource-Priority' or the 'Priority' header field and convey assertion of those values by the signing party authorization.  A signed SIP 'Resource-Priority' or 'Priority' header field will allow a receiving entity (including entities located in different network domains/boundaries) to verify the validity of assertions to act on the information with confidence that it has not been spoofed or compromised.</t>

      <t>This document adds new "auth" array key values for a Resource Priority Header ("rph") claim defined in <xref target="RFC8443" format="default"/>, in support of emergency services networks for emergency call origination and callback. This document additionally defines a new PASSporT claim, "sph", including protection of the SIP 'Priority' header field for the indication of an emergency service callback assigned the value "psap-callback", as defined in <xref target="RFC7090" format="default"/>.
The use of the newly defined claim and key values corresponding to the SIP 'Resource-Priority' and 'Priority' header fields for emergency services is introduced in <xref target="I-D.rosen-stir-emergency-calls" format="default"/> but otherwise is out of scope of this document.  In addition, the PASSporT claims and values defined in this document are intended for use in environments where there are means to verify that the signer of the SIP 'Resource-Priority' and 'Priority' header fields is authoritative.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="terminology" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="new-assertion-values-for-rph-claim" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>New Assertion Values for "rph" Claim</name>
      <t>This specification defines the ability to sign the SIP 'Resource-Priority' header field namespace for local emergency communications defined in <xref target="RFC7135" format="default"/> and represented by the string "esnet.x", where x is the priority level allowed in the esnet namespace. As of the writing of this specification, the priority level is between 0 and 4, inclusive, but may be extended by future specifications.</t>
      <t>Similar to the values defined by <xref target="RFC8443" format="default"/> for the "auth" JSON object key inside the "rph" claim, the string "esnet.x" with the appropriate value should be used when resource priority is required for local emergency communications corresponding and exactly matching the SIP 'Resource-Priority' header field representing the namespace invoked in the call.</t>
      <t>When using "esnet.x" as the "auth" assertion value in emergency-service-destined calls, the "orig" claim of the PASSporT <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> represent the calling party number that initiates the call to emergency services.  The "dest" claim <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be either a country- or region-specific dial string (e.g., "911" for North America or a "112" GSM-defined string used in Europe and other countries) or "urn:service:sos", as defined in <xref target="RFC5031" format="default"/>, representing the emergency services destination of the call.</t>
      <t>The following is an example of an "rph" claim for the SIP 'Resource-Priority' header field with an "esnet.1" assertion:</t>


<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
  {
    "dest":{"uri":["urn:service:sos"]},
    "iat":1615471428,
    "orig":{"tn":"12155551212"},
    "rph":{"auth":["esnet.1"]}
  }
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>For emergency services callbacks, the "orig" claim of the "rph" PASSporT <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> represent the Public Safety Answering Point (PSAP) telephone number. The "dest" claim <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the telephone number representing the original calling party of the emergency service call that is being called back.</t>
      <t>The following is an example of an "rph" claim for the SIP 'Resource-Priority' header field with an "esnet.0" assertion:</t>
<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
  {
    "dest":{"tn":["12155551212"]},
    "iat":1615471428,
    "orig":{"tn":"12155551213"},
    "rph":{"auth":["esnet.0"]}
  }
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>After the header and claims PASSporT objects have been constructed, their signature is generated normally per the guidance in <xref target="RFC8225" format="default"/>, using the full form of PASSporT.  The credentials (i.e., Certificate) used to create the signature must have authority over the namespace of the "rph" claim, and there is only one authority per claim. The authority <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use its credentials associated with the specific service supported by the resource priority namespace in the claim. If r-values are added or dropped by the intermediaries along the path, the intermediaries must generate a new "rph" identity header and sign the claim with their own authority.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="the-sip-priority-header-sph-claim" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>The SIP Priority Header ("sph") Claim</name>
      <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC7090" format="default"/>, the SIP 'Priority' header field may be set to the value "psap-callback" for emergency services callback calls.  Because some SIP networks may act on this value and provide priority or other special routing based on this value, it is important to protect and validate the authoritative use associated with it.</t>
      <t>Therefore, we define a new claim key as part of the "rph" PASSporT, "sph".  This is an optional claim that <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only be used with an "auth" claim with an "esnet.x" value indicating an authorized emergency callback call and corresponding to a SIP 'Priority' header field with the value "psap-callback".</t>
      <t>The value of the "sph" claim key should only be "psap-callback", which <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match the SIP 'Priority' header field value for authorized emergency services callbacks. If the value is anything other than "psap-callback", the PASSporT validation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered a failure case.</t>
      <t>Note that because the intended use of this specification is only for emergency services, there is also an explicit assumption that the signer of the "rph" PASSporT can authoritatively represent both the content of the 'Resource-Priority' header field and 'Priority' header field information associated specifically with an emergency services callback case where both could exist. This document is not intended to be a general mechanism for protecting the SIP 'Priority' header fields; this could be accomplished as part of future work with a new PASSporT extension or new claim added to either an existing PASSporT or PASSporT extension usage.</t>
      <t>The following is an example of an "sph" claim for the SIP 'Priority' header field with the value "psap-callback":</t>
<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
  {
    "dest":{"tn":["12155551212"]},
    "iat":1615471428,
    "orig":{"tn":"12155551213"},
    "rph":{"auth":["esnet.0"]},
    "sph":"psap-callback"
  }
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
    <section anchor="order-of-claim-keys" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Order of Claim Keys</name>
      <t>The order of the claim keys <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> follow the rules of <xref target="RFC8225" sectionFormat="of" section="9"/>, which defines the deterministic JSON serialization used for signature generation (and validation); the claim keys <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> appear in lexicographic order. Therefore, the claim keys discussed in this document appear in the PASSporT Payload in the following order:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>dest</li>
        <li>iat</li>
        <li>orig</li>
        <li>rph</li>
        <li>sph</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="compact-form-of-passport" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Compact Form of PASSporT</name>
      <t>The use of the compact form of PASSporT is not specified in this document or recommended for "rph" PASSporTs.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="json-web-token-claims" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>JSON Web Token Claims</name>
        <t>This specification requests that the IANA add one new claim to the "JSON Web Token Claims" registry, as defined in <xref target="RFC7519" format="default"/>.</t>
<dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
        <dt>Claim Name:</dt>
	<dd>sph</dd>
        <dt>Claim Description:</dt>
	<dd>SIP Priority header field</dd>
        <dt>Change Controller:</dt>
	<dd>IESG</dd>
        <dt>Specification Document(s):</dt>
	<dd>RFC 9027</dd>
</dl>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security considerations discussed in <xref target="RFC8224" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8225" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC8443" format="default"/> are applicable here.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

<displayreference target="I-D.rosen-stir-emergency-calls" to="EMERGENCY-CALLS"/>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4412.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5031.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7090.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7135.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8224.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8225.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7519.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8443.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.rosen-stir-emergency-calls.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Brian Rosen"/>, <contact fullname="Terry Reese"/>, and <contact fullname="Jon Peterson"/> for helpful suggestions, comments, and corrections.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
