<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-detnet-tsn-vpn-over-mpls-07" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3" consensus="true" number="9024">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="TSN over DetNet MPLS">
    Deterministic Networking (DetNet) Data Plane: IEEE 802.1 Time-Sensitive Networking over MPLS</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9024"/>
    <author role="editor" fullname="Balázs Varga" initials="B." surname="Varga">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Magyar Tudosok krt. 11.</street>
          <city>Budapest</city>
          <country>Hungary</country>
          <code>1117</code>
        </postal>
        <email>balazs.a.varga@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="János Farkas" initials="J." surname="Farkas">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Magyar Tudosok krt. 11.</street>
          <city>Budapest</city>
          <country>Hungary</country>
          <code>1117</code>
        </postal>
        <email>janos.farkas@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Andrew G. Malis" initials="A." surname="Malis">
      <organization>Malis Consulting</organization>
      <address>
        <email>agmalis@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S." surname="Bryant">
      <organization>Futurewei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <email>sb@stewartbryant.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Don Fedyk" initials="D." surname="Fedyk">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dfedyk@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2021"/>
    <workgroup>DetNet</workgroup>

<keyword>interconnecting TSN networks</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
     This document specifies the Deterministic Networking data plane
     when Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN) networks are interconnected over a DetNet MPLS network.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="sec_intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        The Time-Sensitive Networking Task Group (TSN TG) within the IEEE 802.1 Working 
        Group deals with deterministic services through IEEE 802 networks. 
    Deterministic Networking (DetNet) defined by the IETF is a service that can be 
        offered by an L3 network to DetNet flows.  General background and concepts 
        of DetNet can be found in <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document specifies the use of a DetNet MPLS network to interconnect TSN 
        nodes/network segments. The DetNet MPLS data plane is defined in 
           <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Terms Used in This Document</name>
        <t>
        This document uses the terminology and concepts established in the DetNet 
        architecture <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/> 
        <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/> 
        <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>.  TSN-specific terms are defined in the TSN TG 
		of the IEEE 802.1 Working Group. The reader is assumed 
        to be familiar with these documents and their terminology.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Abbreviations</name>
        <t>
   The following abbreviations are used in this document:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="14">
          <dt>AC</dt>
          <dd>Attachment Circuit</dd>
          <dt>CE</dt>
          <dd>Customer Edge equipment</dd>
          <dt>d-CW</dt>
          <dd>DetNet Control Word</dd>
          <dt>DetNet</dt>
          <dd>Deterministic Networking</dd>
          <dt>DF</dt>
          <dd>DetNet Flow</dd>
          <dt>FRER</dt>
          <dd>Frame Replication and Elimination for Redundancy 
        (TSN function)</dd>
          <dt>L2</dt>
          <dd>Layer 2</dd>
          <dt>L2VPN</dt>
          <dd>Layer 2 Virtual Private Network</dd>
          <dt>L3</dt>
          <dd>Layer 3</dd>
          <dt>LSP</dt><dd>Label Switched Path</dd>
          <dt>LSR</dt>
          <dd>Label Switching Router</dd>
          <dt>MPLS</dt>
          <dd>Multiprotocol Label Switching</dd>
          <dt>MPLS-TE</dt>
          <dd>Multiprotocol Label Switching - Traffic Engineering</dd>
          <dt>NSP</dt>
          <dd>Native Service Processing</dd>
          <dt>OAM</dt>
          <dd>Operations, Administration, and Maintenance</dd>
          <dt>PE</dt>
          <dd>Provider Edge</dd>
          <dt>PREOF</dt>
          <dd>Packet Replication, Elimination and Ordering Functions</dd>
          <dt>PW</dt>
          <dd>Pseudowire</dd>
          <dt>S-PE</dt>
          <dd>Switching Provider Edge</dd>
          <dt>T-PE</dt>
          <dd>Terminating Provider Edge</dd>
          <dt>TSN</dt>
          <dd>Time-Sensitive Network</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

<section anchor="sec_tsn_mpls_dt_dp_scen" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IEEE 802.1 TSN over DetNet MPLS Data Plane Scenario</name>
      <t>
   <xref target="fig_tsn_mpls_detnet" format="default"/> shows IEEE 802.1 TSN end
   stations operating over a TSN-aware DetNet service running over an MPLS
   network.  DetNet edge nodes sit at the boundary of a DetNet domain. They are
   responsible for mapping non-DetNet-aware L2 traffic to DetNet services.
   They also support the imposition and disposition of the required DetNet
   encapsulation.  These are functionally similar to PW
   T-PE nodes, which use MPLS-TE LSPs.  In this
   example, TSN Streams are simple applications over DetNet flows.  The specifics
   of this operation are discussed later in this document.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="fig_tsn_mpls_detnet">
        <name>A TSN over DetNet MPLS-Enabled Network</name>
        <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
   TSN           Edge          Transit         Edge          TSN
End System       Node           Node           Node       End System
                (T-PE)         (LSR)          (T-PE)

+----------+                                             +----------+
|   TSN    | <-------- End-to-End TSN Service ---------> |   TSN    |
|  Applic. |                                             |  Applic. |
+----------+  +.........+                   +.........+  +----------+
|          |  | \S-Proxy:                   :S-Proxy/ |  |          |
|   TSN    |  |   +.+---+<-- DetNet flow -->+---+ |   |  |   TSN    |
|          |  |TSN| |Svc|                   |Svc| |TSN|  |          |
+----------+  +---+ +---+    +----------+   +---+ +---+  +----------+
|   L2     |  | L2| |Fwd|    |Forwarding|   |Fwd| |L2 |  |   L2     |
+------.---+  +-.-+ +-.-+    +---.----.-+   +--.+ +-.-+  +---.------+
       :  Link  :     /  ,-----.  \   :  Link  :   /  ,-----. \
       +........+     +-[  Sub- ]-+   +........+   +-[  TSN  ]-+
                        [Network]                    [Network]
                         `-----'                      `-----'

                    |<------ DetNet MPLS ------>|
        |<---------------------- TSN   --------------------->|

]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        In this example, edge nodes provide a service proxy function that 
        "associates" the DetNet flows and native flows (i.e., TSN Streams) at
        the edge of the DetNet domain.  TSN Streams are treated as App-flows 
		for DetNet. The whole DetNet domain behaves as a TSN relay node for 
		the TSN Streams. The service proxy behaves as a port of that TSN 
		relay node. 
      </t>
      <t>

   <xref target="fig_8021_detnet" format="default"/> illustrates how DetNet can provide services 
   for IEEE 802.1 TSN end systems, CE1 and CE2, over a DetNet-enabled MPLS 
   network.  Edge nodes E1 and E2 insert and remove the required DetNet data
   plane encapsulation.  The 'X' in the edge nodes and relay node, R1, 
   represent a potential DetNet compound flow packet replication and 
   elimination point.  This conceptually parallels L2VPN services and could
   leverage existing related solutions as discussed below.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="fig_8021_detnet">
        <name>IEEE 802.1TSN over DetNet</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
     TSN    |<------- End-to-End DetNet Service ------>|  TSN
    Service |         Transit          Transit         | Service
TSN  (AC)   |        |<-Tnl->|        |<-Tnl->|        |  (AC)  TSN
End    |    V        V    1  V        V   2   V        V   |    End
System |    +--------+       +--------+       +--------+   |  System
+---+  |    |   E1   |=======|   R1   |=======|   E2   |   |   +---+
|   |--|----|._X_....|..DF1..|.._ _...|..DF3..|...._X_.|---|---|   |
|CE1|  |    |    \   |       |   X    |       |   /    |   |   |CE2|
|   |       |     \_.|..DF2..|._/ \_..|..DF4..|._/     |       |   |
+---+       |        |=======|        |=======|        |       +---+
    ^       +--------+       +--------+       +--------+       ^
    |        Edge Node       Relay Node        Edge Node       |
    |          (T-PE)           (S-PE)          (T-PE)         |
    |                                                          |
    |<- TSN -> <------- TSN over DetNet MPLS -------> <- TSN ->|
    |                                                          |
    |<-------- Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN) Service ------->|

    X   = Service protection
    DFx = DetNet member flow x over a TE LSP
	AC  = Attachment Circuit
	Tnl = Tunnel
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

 <section anchor="sec_dt_dp" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>DetNet MPLS Data Plane</name>
      <section anchor="sec_dt_dp_ov" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Overview</name>
        <t>
        The basic approach defined in <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>
        supports the DetNet service sub-layer based on existing PW
        encapsulations and mechanisms and supports the DetNet forwarding 
        sub-layer based on existing MPLS Traffic Engineering encapsulations 
        and mechanisms. 
        </t>
        <t>
        A node operating on a DetNet flow in the DetNet service sub-layer, i.e., a node processing a DetNet packet that has the S-Label as top of stack, 
        uses the local context associated with that S-Label. For example, a received 
        F-Label can be used to determine what local DetNet operation(s) is applied to that 
        packet. An S-Label may be unique when taken from the platform
        label space <xref target="RFC3031" format="default"/>, which would enable correct DetNet flow
        identification regardless of which input interface or LSP the packet arrives 
        on. The service sub-layer functions (i.e., PREOF) use a DetNet control word 
        (d-CW).
        </t>
        <t>
    The DetNet MPLS data plane builds on MPLS Traffic Engineering
    encapsulations and mechanisms to provide a forwarding sub-layer that
    is responsible for providing resource allocation and explicit
    routes.  The forwarding sub-layer is supported by one or more
    forwarding labels (F-Labels).
        </t>
        <t>
        DetNet edge/relay nodes are DetNet service sub-layer
        aware, understand the particular needs of DetNet flows, and
        provide both DetNet service and forwarding sub-layer functions.
        They add, remove, and process d-CWs, S-Labels, and F-Labels as
        needed.  MPLS DetNet nodes and transit nodes include
        DetNet forwarding sub-layer functions -- notably, support for 
		explicit routes and resource allocation to eliminate (or 
		reduce) congestion loss and jitter. Unlike other DetNet node types, 
		transit nodes provide no service sub-layer processing.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="tom-encap" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>TSN over DetNet MPLS Encapsulation</name>
        <t>
        The basic encapsulation approach is to treat a TSN Stream as an App-flow 
        from the DetNet MPLS perspective. The corresponding example is shown in 
        <xref target="fig_tsn_mpls_ex" format="default"/>. Note that three example flows are 
		shown in the figure.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="fig_tsn_mpls_ex">
          <name>Examples of TSN over MPLS Encapsulation Formats</name>
          <artwork align="center" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[

           /->     +------+  +------+  +------+   TSN      ^ ^
  MPLS     |       |  X   |  |  X   |  |  X   |<- Appli    : :
App-Flow <-+       +------+  +------+  +------+   cation   : :(1)
           |       |TSN-L2|  |TSN-L2|  |TSN-L2|            : v
           \-> +---+======+--+======+--+======+-----+      :
                   | d-CW |  | d-CW |  | d-CW |            :
DetNet-MPLS        +------+  +------+  +------+            :(2)
                   |Labels|  |Labels|  |Labels|            v
               +---+======+--+======+--+======+-----+
Link/Sub-Network   |  L2  |  | TSN  |  | UDP  |
                   +------+  +------+  +------+
                                       |  IP  |
                                       +------+
                                       |  L2  |
                                       +------+
    (1) TSN Stream 
    (2) DetNet MPLS Flow
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        In the figure, "Application" indicates the application payload carried by 
        the TSN network. "MPLS App-Flow" indicates that the TSN Stream is the 
        payload from the perspective of the DetNet MPLS data plane defined in 
        <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>. A single DetNet MPLS flow 
        can aggregate multiple TSN Streams.
        </t>
<aside>
        <t>
		Note: Network fragmentation for DetNet is not supported and MUST be avoided. The reason for this is that network fragmentation is not  consistent with the packet delivery times needed for DetNet. Therefore, when IP is used as the sub-network, IPv6 fragmentation MUST NOT be used, and IPv4 packets MUST be sent with the DF bit set. This means that the network operator MUST ensure that all the DetNet encapsulation overhead plus the maximum TSN App-flow frame size does not exceed the DetNet network's MTU.
        </t></aside>
      </section>
    </section>

 <section anchor="tom_proc" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>TSN over MPLS Data Plane Procedures</name>
      <t>
        The description of edge node procedures and functions for TSN over DetNet MPLS
        scenarios follows the concepts from <xref target="RFC3985" format="default"/> and covers the 
        edge node components shown in <xref target="fig_tsn_mpls_detnet" format="default"/>. In 
        this section, the following procedures of DetNet edge nodes are described:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
                        TSN related (<xref target="tom_tsn_proc" format="default"/>)
                </li>
        <li>
                        DetNet Service Proxy (<xref target="tom_svc_prx_proc" format="default"/>)
                </li>
        <li>
                        DetNet service and forwarding sub-layer (<xref target="tom_dn_sub_proc" format="default"/>)
                </li>
      </ul>
      <t>  
		The subsections describe procedures for forwarding packets by DetNet 
		edge nodes, where such packets are received from either directly 
		connected CEs (TSN nodes) or some other DetNet edge nodes.
      </t>
      <section anchor="tom_tsn_proc" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Edge Node TSN Procedures</name>
        <t>
        The TSN TG of the IEEE 802.1 
                Working Group has defined (and is defining) a number of amendments 
                to <xref target="IEEE8021Q" format="default"/> that provide zero 
                congestion loss and bounded latency in bridged networks.
        <xref target="IEEE8021CB" format="default"/> defines packet 
                replication and elimination functions for a TSN network.
        </t>
        <t>
		  	  The implementation of a TSN entity (i.e., TSN packet processing 
			  functions) must be compliant with the relevant IEEE 802.1 
			  standards.
        </t>
        <t>
                TSN-specific functions are executed on the data received by 
                the DetNet edge node from the connected CE before being forwarded to 
				connected CE(s) or presented to the DetNet service proxy function for 
                transmission across the DetNet domain. TSN-specific functions 
				are also executed on the data received from a DetNet PW by a PE 
				before the data is output on the AC(s). 
        </t>
        <t>
                The TSN packet processing function(s) of edge nodes (T-PE) belongs to the 
                NSP <xref target="RFC3985" format="default"/> 
                block. This is similar to other functionalities being defined by standards 
                bodies other than the IETF (for example, in the case of Ethernet, stripping, 
                overwriting, or adding VLAN tags, etc.). Depending on the TSN role of 
                the edge node in the end-to-end TSN service, selected TSN functions 
                are supported. 
        </t>
        <t>		
			When a PE receives a packet from a CE on a given AC with DetNet service,
			it first checks via Stream identification 
			(see Clause 6 of <xref target="IEEE8021CB" format="default"/> and
            <xref target="IEEEP8021CBdb" format="default"/>) 
			whether the packet belongs 
			to a configured TSN Stream (i.e., App-flow from the DetNet perspective). 
			If no Stream ID is matched and no other (VPN) service is configured 
			for the AC, then the packet <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be dropped. If there is a matching TSN 
			Stream, then the Stream-ID-specific TSN functions are executed 
			(e.g., ingress policing, header field manipulation in the case 
			of active Stream identification, FRER, etc.). Source Media Access Control (MAC) lookup 
			may also be used for local MAC address learning.
        </t>
        <t>		
			If the PE decides to forward the packet, the packet <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be forwarded 
			according to the TSN-Stream-specific configuration to connected CE(s) 
			(in case of local bridging) and/or to the DetNet service proxy 
			(in case of forwarding to remote CE(s)). If there are no 
			TSN-Stream-specific forwarding configurations, the PE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> flood 
			the packet to other locally attached CE(s) and to the DetNet service 
			proxy. If the administrative policy on the PE does not allow 
			flooding, the PE <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> drop the packet.
        </t>
        <t>		
			When a TSN entity of the PE receives a packet from the DetNet 
			service proxy, it first checks via Stream identification 
			(see Clause 6 of <xref target="IEEE8021CB" format="default"/> and
            <xref target="IEEEP8021CBdb" format="default"/>) whether 
			the packet belongs to a configured TSN Stream. If no Stream ID is 
			matched, then the packet is dropped. If there is a matching TSN 
			Stream, then the Stream-ID-specific TSN functions are executed 
			(e.g., header field manipulation in case of active Stream 
			identification, FRER, etc.). Source MAC lookup may also be used for 
			local MAC address learning.
        </t>
        <t>		
			If the PE decides to forward the packet, the packet is forwarded 
			according to the TSN-Stream-specific configuration to connected CE(s).
			If there are no TSN-Stream-specific forwarding configurations, the 
			PE floods the packet to locally attached CE(s). If the 
			administrative policy on the PE does not allow flooding, the PE  
			drops the packet.
        </t>
        <t>
            Implementations of this document <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> use management and
            control information to ensure TSN-specific functions of the edge node
            according to the expectations of the connected TSN network. 
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="tom_svc_prx_proc" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Edge Node DetNet Service Proxy Procedures</name>
        <t>
                The service proxy
                function maps between App-flows and DetNet flows.
				The DetNet edge node TSN entity <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support the TSN Stream
                identification functions (as defined in Clause 6 of <xref target="IEEE8021CB" format="default"/> and <xref target="IEEEP8021CBdb" format="default"/>) and the related managed objects (as
                defined in Clause 9 of <xref target="IEEE8021CB" format="default"/> and <xref target="IEEEP8021CBdb" format="default"/>)	to
                recognize the packets related to App-flow.  The service proxy
                presents TSN Streams as an App-flow to a DetNet flow.
        </t>
        <t>		
			When a DetNet service proxy receives a packet from the TSN entity,
			it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> check whether such an App-flow is present in its mapping table.
			If present, it associates the internal DetNet flow ID to the packet and 
			<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> forward it to the DetNet service and forwarding sub-layers. If 
			no match is found, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> drop the packet.
        </t>
        <t>		
			When a DetNet service proxy receives a packet from the DetNet service 
			and forwarding sub-layers, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be forwarded to the edge node 
			TSN entity. 
        </t>
        <t>
                Implementations of this document <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> use management and
                control information to map a TSN Stream to a DetNet flow. 
                N:1 mapping (aggregating multiple TSN Streams in a single
                DetNet flow) <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be supported. The management or control
                function that provisions flow mapping <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> ensure that
                adequate resources are allocated and configured to 
                fulfill the service requirements of the mapped flows.
        </t>
        <t>
                Due to the (intentional) similarities of the DetNet PREOF and
                TSN FRER functions, service protection function interworking is
                possible between the TSN and the DetNet domains. Such service
                protection interworking scenarios might require copying of sequence
                number fields from TSN (L2) to PW (MPLS) encapsulation.
                However, such interworking is out of scope in this document and
                is left for further study.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="tom_dn_sub_proc" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Edge Node DetNet Service and Forwarding Sub-Layer Procedures</name>
        <t>
                In the design presented in <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>, an MPLS service 
                label (the S-Label), similar to a PW label 
                <xref target="RFC3985" format="default"/>, is used to identify both the DetNet flow 
                identity and the MPLS payload type.  The DetNet sequence 
                number is carried in the d-CW, which carries the 
                Data/OAM discriminator as well. In 
                <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>, two sequence number sizes 
                are supported: a 16-bit sequence number and a 28-bit sequence number.
        </t>
        <t>
                PREOF functions and the provided service recovery are available
                only within the DetNet domain as the DetNet flow ID and the DetNet
                sequence number are not valid outside the DetNet network.  MPLS
                (DetNet) edge nodes terminate all related information elements 
                encoded in the MPLS labels.
        </t>
        <t>		
			When a PE receives a packet from the service proxy function, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> 
			handle the packet as defined in <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>.
        </t>
        <t>		
			When a PE receives an MPLS packet from a remote PE, then, after 
			processing the MPLS label stack, if the top MPLS label ends up being 
			a DetNet S-Label that was advertised by this node, then the PE 
			<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> forward the packet according to the configured DetNet service and 
			forwarding sub-layer rules to other PE nodes or via the DetNet service 
			proxy function towards locally connected CE(s). 
        </t>
        <t>
                For further details on DetNet service and forwarding sub-layers, 
				see <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

 <section anchor="cp_considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Controller Plane (Management and Control) Considerations</name>
      <t>
        Information related to TSN Stream(s) to DetNet flow mapping is
        required only for the service proxy function of MPLS (DetNet) edge nodes. 
        From the data plane perspective, there is no practical difference
		based on the origin of flow-mapping-related information	(management 
		plane or control plane).
      </t>
      <t>
            The following summarizes the set of information that is needed to
            configure TSN over DetNet MPLS:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>TSN-related configuration information according to the 
			     TSN role of the DetNet MPLS node, as per 
				 <xref target="IEEE8021Q" format="default"/>, <xref target="IEEE8021CB" format="default"/>, and
			     <xref target="IEEEP8021CBdb" format="default"/>. </li>
        <li>DetNet MPLS-related configuration information according to the 
			     DetNet role of the DetNet MPLS node, as per 
			     <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>. </li>
        <li>App-flow identification information to map received TSN 
			  Stream(s) to the DetNet flow. Parameters of TSN Stream 
			  identification are defined in <xref target="IEEE8021CB" format="default"/> and 
			  <xref target="IEEEP8021CBdb" format="default"/>. </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
            This information <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provisioned per DetNet flow.
      </t>
      <t>
			Mappings between DetNet and TSN management and control planes are 
			out of scope of the document. Some of the challenges are 
			highlighted below.
      </t>
      <t>
        MPLS DetNet edge nodes are a member of both the DetNet domain and the
        connected TSN network. From the TSN network perspective, the MPLS
        (DetNet) edge node has a "TSN relay node" role, so TSN-specific
        management and control plane functionalities must be implemented.
        There are many similarities in the management plane techniques used in
        DetNet and TSN, but that is not the case for the control plane
        protocols. For example, RSVP-TE and MSRP behave differently.  
		Therefore, management and control plane design is an important aspect 
		of scenarios where mapping between DetNet and TSN is required.
      </t>
      <t>
        Note that as the DetNet network is just a portion of the end-to-end TSN
        path (i.e., single hop from the Ethernet perspective), some parameters
        (e.g., delay) may differ significantly.  Since there is no interworking
        function, the bandwidth of the DetNet network is assumed to be set large enough to
        handle all TSN flows it will support.  At the egress of the DetNet domain, the MPLS
        headers are stripped, and the TSN flow continues on as a normal TSN
        flow. 
      </t>

      <t>
        In order to use a DetNet network to interconnect TSN segments,
        TSN-specific information must be converted to DetNet-domain-specific information. TSN Stream ID(s) and stream-related
        parameters/requirements must be converted to a DetNet flow ID and 
        flow-related parameters/requirements.
      </t>

      <t>
        In some cases, it may be challenging to determine some information related to the egress-node. For example, it may be not trivial to
        locate the egress point/interface of a TSN Stream with a 
        multicast destination MAC address. Such scenarios may
        require interaction between control and management plane
        functions and between DetNet and TSN domains.
      </t>
      <t>
        Mapping between DetNet flow identifiers and TSN Stream
        identifiers, if not provided explicitly, can be done by the service
        proxy function of an MPLS (DetNet) edge node locally based on information
        provided for the configuration of the TSN Stream identification functions 
        (e.g., Mask-and-Match Stream identification).
      </t>
      <t>
        Triggering the setup/modification of a DetNet flow in the
        DetNet network is an example where management and/or
        control plane interactions are required between the DetNet
        and the TSN network. 
      </t>
      <t>
        Configuration of TSN-specific functions (e.g., FRER)
        inside the TSN network is a TSN-domain-specific decision 
        and may not be visible in the DetNet domain. Service protection
        interworking scenarios are left for further study.
      </t>
    </section>

<section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
     Security considerations for DetNet are described in detail in <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-security" format="default"/>. General security
     considerations are described in <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/>.  
      </t>
      <t>     
     Considerations specific to the DetNet MPLS data plane are summarized and 
	 described in <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>, including any 
	 application flow types. This document focuses on a scenario where TSN Streams are the application flows for DetNet, which is already covered 
	 by those DetNet MPLS data plane security considerations. 
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
   This document has no IANA actions.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
<displayreference target="I-D.ietf-detnet-security" to="DETNET-SEC"/>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3031.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8938.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8964.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="IEEE8021CB" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8091139">
          <front>
            <title>Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks -- Frame Replication and Elimination for Reliability</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="October" year="2017"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="802.1CB-2017"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2017.8091139"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IEEEP8021CBdb" target=" https://1.ieee802.org/tsn/802-1cbdb">
          <front>
            <title>Draft Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Frame Replication and Elimination for Reliability - Amendment: Extended Stream Identification Functions</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="April" year="2021"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="IEEE P802.1CBdb" value="D1.3"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3985.xml"/>

<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-detnet-security'>
<front>
<title>Deterministic Networking (DetNet) Security Considerations</title>

<author initials='E' surname='Grossman' fullname='Ethan Grossman' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='T' surname='Mizrahi' fullname='Tal Mizrahi'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Hacker' fullname='Andrew Hacker'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='2' year='2021' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-detnet-security-16' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-detnet-security.txt' />
</reference>


      <reference anchor="IEEE8021Q" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8403927">
          <front>
            <title>Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks--Bridges
          and Bridged Networks</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2018" month="July"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="IEEE Std." value="802.1Q-2018"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2018.8403927"/>

        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="acks" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
    The authors wish to thank <contact fullname="Norman Finn"/>, <contact fullname="Lou Berger"/>, <contact fullname="Craig Gunther"/>,
	<contact fullname="Christophe Mangin"/>, and <contact fullname="Jouni Korhonen"/> for their various contributions
	to this work.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
