<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

 <rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-nsec-ttl-05" number="9077" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" updates="4034, 4035, 5155, 8198" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" tocInclude="true">

   <front>

 <title abbrev="NSEC TTL">NSEC and NSEC3: TTLs and Aggressive Use</title>

 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9077"/>

 <author initials="P." surname="van Dijk" fullname="Peter van Dijk"><organization>PowerDNS</organization>
 <address>
 <postal>
 <street></street>
 <city>Den Haag</city>
 <country>Netherlands</country>
 </postal>
 <email>peter.van.dijk@powerdns.com</email>
 </address>
 </author>
 <date year="2021" month="July" />
 <area>General</area>
 <workgroup>dnsop</workgroup>
<keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
<keyword>negative cache</keyword>
<keyword>Denial of Existence</keyword>

 <abstract>
 <t>Due to a combination of unfortunate wording in earlier documents, aggressive use of NSEC and NSEC3 records may deny the existence of names far beyond the intended lifetime of a denial.
 This document changes the definition of the NSEC and NSEC3 TTL to correct that situation.
 This document updates RFCs 4034, 4035, 5155, and 8198.</t>
 </abstract>

 </front>

 <middle>

 <section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
 <t><xref target="RFC2308"></xref> defines the TTL of the Start of Authority (SOA) record that must be returned in negative answers (NXDOMAIN or NODATA):</t>
 
 <blockquote><t>The TTL of this record is set from the minimum of the MINIMUM field of the SOA record and the TTL of the SOA itself, and indicates how long a resolver may cache the negative answer.</t>
 </blockquote>

 <t>Thus, if the TTL of the SOA in the zone is lower than the SOA MINIMUM value (the last number in the SOA record),
 the authoritative server sends that lower value as the TTL of the returned SOA record.
 The resolver always uses the TTL of the returned SOA record when setting the negative TTL in its cache.</t>
 
 <t>However, <xref target="RFC4034" sectionFormat="comma" section="4"></xref> has this unfortunate text:</t>

 <blockquote><t>The NSEC RR <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> have the same TTL value as the SOA minimum TTL field. This is in the spirit of negative caching (<xref target="RFC2308"/>).</t>
 </blockquote>

 <t>This text, while referring to <xref target="RFC2308"/>, can cause NSEC records to have much higher TTLs than the appropriate negative TTL for a zone.
 <xref target="RFC5155"></xref> contains equivalent text.</t>
 
 <t><xref target="RFC8198" sectionFormat="comma" section="5.4"></xref> tries to correct this:</t>
 
 <blockquote><t><xref target="RFC2308" sectionFormat="of" section="5"/> also states that a negative cache entry TTL is taken from the minimum of the SOA.MINIMUM field and SOA's TTL.  This can be less than the TTL of an NSEC or NSEC3 record, since their TTL is equal to the SOA.MINIMUM field (see <xref target="RFC4035" sectionFormat="comma" section="2.3"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5155" sectionFormat="comma" section="3"/>).</t>
 
 <t>A resolver that supports aggressive use of NSEC and NSEC3 <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> reduce the TTL of NSEC and NSEC3 records to match the SOA.MINIMUM field in the authority section of a negative response, if SOA.MINIMUM is smaller.</t>
 </blockquote>

 <t>But the NSEC and NSEC3 RRs should, according to <xref target="RFC4034"/> and  <xref target="RFC5155"/>, already be at the value of the MINIMUM field in the SOA. Thus, the advice from  <xref target="RFC8198"/> would not actually change the TTL used for the NSEC and NSEC3 RRs for authoritative servers that follow the RFCs.</t>

<t>As a theoretical exercise, consider a top-level domain (TLD) named .example with an SOA record like this:</t>

<artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
example.    900 IN  SOA primary.example. dnsadmin.example. ( 
                                         1 1800 900 604800 86400 )
]]></artwork>
 
 <t>The SOA record has a 900-second TTL and an 86400-second MINIMUM TTL.
 Negative responses from this zone have a 900-second TTL, but the NSEC or NSEC3 records in those negative responses have an 86400-second TTL.
 If a resolver were to use those NSEC or NSEC3 records aggressively, they would be considered valid for a day instead of the intended 15 minutes.</t>
 </section>

 <section anchor="conventions-and-definitions"><name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
	 <t>
     The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
     NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
     "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
     described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
     when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
	 </t>
 </section>

 <section anchor="nsec-and-nsec3-ttl-changes"><name>NSEC and NSEC3 TTL Changes</name>

<t><xref target="RFC4034"></xref>, <xref target="RFC4035"></xref>, and <xref target="RFC5155"></xref> use the <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> requirement level, but they were written prior to the publication of <xref target="RFC8198"></xref> when <xref target="RFC4035"></xref> still said: </t>

<blockquote><t>However, it seems prudent for resolvers to avoid blocking new authoritative data or synthesizing new data on their own.</t></blockquote>
<t>
  
<xref target="RFC8198"></xref> updated that text to contain:</t> <blockquote><t>...DNSSEC-enabled validating resolvers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use wildcards and NSEC/NSEC3 resource records to generate positive and negative responses until the effective TTLs or signatures for those records expire.</t></blockquote><t>

This means that the correctness of NSEC and NSEC3 records and their TTLs has become much more important.

Because of that, the updates in this document upgrade the requirement level to <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>.</t>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc4034"><name>Updates to RFC 4034</name>
<t><xref target="RFC4034"></xref> says:</t>


<blockquote><t>The NSEC RR <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> have the same TTL value as the SOA minimum TTL field.  This is in the spirit of negative caching (<xref target="RFC2308"/>).</t>
</blockquote><t>This is updated to say:</t>
<blockquote>

  <t>The TTL of the NSEC RR that is returned <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the lesser of the MINIMUM field of the SOA record and the TTL of the SOA itself.  This matches the definition of the TTL for negative responses in <xref target="RFC2308"></xref>. Because some signers incrementally update the NSEC chain, a transient inconsistency between the observed and expected TTL <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> exist.</t>
</blockquote></section>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc4035"><name>Updates to RFC 4035</name>
<t><xref target="RFC4035"></xref> says:</t>

<blockquote><t>The TTL value for any NSEC RR <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be the same as the minimum TTL value field in the zone SOA RR.</t>
</blockquote><t>This is updated to say:</t>
<blockquote>

  <t>The TTL of the NSEC RR that is returned <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the lesser of the MINIMUM field of the SOA record and the TTL of the SOA itself.  This matches the definition of the TTL for negative responses in <xref target="RFC2308"></xref>. Because some signers incrementally update the NSEC chain, a transient inconsistency between the observed and expected TTL <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> exist.</t>
</blockquote></section>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc5155"><name>Updates to RFC 5155</name>
<t><xref target="RFC5155"></xref> says:</t>
<blockquote><t>The NSEC3 RR <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> have the same TTL value as the SOA minimum TTL field.  This is in the spirit of negative caching <xref target="RFC2308"/>.</t>
</blockquote><t>This is updated to say:</t>
<blockquote><t>The TTL of the NSEC3 RR that is returned <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the lesser of the MINIMUM field of the SOA record and the TTL of the SOA itself.  This matches the definition of the TTL for negative responses in <xref target="RFC2308"></xref>. Because some signers incrementally update the NSEC3 chain, a transient inconsistency between the observed and expected TTL <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> exist.</t>
</blockquote><t>Where <xref target="RFC5155"></xref> says:</t>
<blockquote>
<ul empty="false">
<li>The TTL value for any NSEC3 RR <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be the same as the minimum TTL value field in the zone SOA RR.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<t>This is updated to say:</t>
<blockquote>
<ul empty="false">
<li>The TTL value for each NSEC3 RR <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the lesser of the MINIMUM field of the zone SOA RR and the TTL of the zone SOA RR itself. Because some signers incrementally update the NSEC3 chain, a transient inconsistency between the observed and expected TTL <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> exist.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote></section>

<section anchor="updates-to-rfc8198"><name>Updates to RFC 8198</name>
<t><xref target="RFC8198" sectionFormat="comma" section="5.4"></xref> ("Consideration on TTL") is completely replaced by the following text:</t>
<blockquote><t>The TTL value of negative information is especially important,
   because newly added domain names cannot be used while the negative
   information is effective.</t>
<t><xref target="RFC2308" sectionFormat="of" section="5"/> suggests a maximum default negative cache TTL
   value of 3 hours (10800).  It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that validating
   resolvers limit the maximum effective TTL value of negative responses
   (NSEC/NSEC3 RRs) to this same value.</t>
<t>A resolver that supports aggressive use of NSEC and NSEC3 <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
   limit the TTL of NSEC and NSEC3 records to the lesser of the SOA.MINIMUM
   field and the TTL of the SOA in a response, if present.
   It <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also use a previously cached SOA for a zone to find these values.</t>
</blockquote><t>(The third paragraph of the original is removed, and the fourth paragraph is updated to allow resolvers to also take the lesser of the SOA TTL and SOA MINIMUM.)</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="zone-operator-considerations"><name>Zone Operator Considerations</name>
<t>If signers and DNS servers for a zone cannot immediately be updated to conform to this document, zone operators are encouraged to consider setting their SOA record TTL and the SOA MINIMUM field to the same value.
That way, the TTL used for aggressive NSEC and NSEC3 use matches the SOA TTL for negative responses.</t>
<t>Note that some signers might use the SOA TTL or MINIMUM as a default for other values, such as the TTL for DNSKEY records.
Operators should consult documentation before changing values.</t>

<section anchor="a-note-on-wildcards"><name>A Note on Wildcards</name>
<t>Validating resolvers consider an expanded wildcard valid for the wildcard's TTL, capped by the TTLs of the NSEC or NSEC3 proof that shows that the wildcard expansion is legal.
Thus, changing the TTL of NSEC or NSEC3 records (explicitly, or by implementation of this document implicitly) might affect (shorten) the lifetime of wildcards.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>An attacker can delay future records from appearing in a cache by seeding the cache with queries that cause NSEC or NSEC3 responses to be cached for aggressive use purposes.
This document reduces the impact of that attack in cases where the NSEC or NSEC3 TTL is higher than the zone operator intended.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
<t>IANA has added a reference to this document in the &quot;Resource Record (RR) TYPEs&quot; subregistry of the &quot;Domain Name System (DNS) Parameters&quot; registry for the NSEC and NSEC3 types.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2308.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5155.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8198.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
</references>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t>This document was made possible with the help of the following people:</t>

<ul spacing="normal">
<li><t><contact fullname="Ralph Dolmans"/></t></li>
<li><t><contact fullname="Warren Kumari"/></t></li>
<li><t><contact fullname="Matthijs Mekking"/></t></li>
<li><t><contact fullname="Vladimir Cunat"/></t></li>
<li><t><contact fullname="Matt Nordhoff"/></t></li>
<li><t><contact fullname="Josh Soref"/></t></li>
<li><t><contact fullname="Tim Wicinski"/></t></li>
</ul>
<t>The author would like to explicitly thank <contact fullname="Paul Hoffman"/> for the extensive reviews, text contributions, and help in navigating WG comments.</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
