<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" docName="draft-atkins-suit-cose-walnutdsa-07" number="9021" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="independent" category="info"
xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">



  <front>

    <title abbrev="WalnutDSA COSE Sigs">Use of the Walnut Digital Signature Algorithm with CBOR Object Signing and Encryption (COSE) </title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9021"/>

    <author fullname="Derek Atkins" initials="D" surname="Atkins">
      <organization>Veridify Security</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	    <street>100 Beard Sawmill Rd, Suite 350</street>

          <city>Shelton</city>
          <region>CT</region>
          <code>06484</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 617 623 3745</phone>
        <email>datkins@veridify.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="May" year="2021"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>COSE</keyword>
    <keyword>WalnutDSA</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the conventions for using the Walnut Digital
      Signature Algorithm (WalnutDSA) for digital signatures with the CBOR
      Object Signing and Encryption (COSE) syntax.  WalnutDSA is a
      lightweight, quantum-resistant signature scheme based on Group Theoretic
      Cryptography with implementation and computational efficiency of
      signature verification in constrained environments, even on 8- and
      16-bit platforms.</t>


      <t>The goal of this publication is to document a way to use the
      lightweight, quantum-resistant WalnutDSA signature algorithm in
      COSE in a way that would allow multiple developers to build
      compatible implementations.  As of this publication, the
      security properties of WalnutDSA have not been evaluated by the
      IETF and its use has not been endorsed by the IETF.
      </t>
      <t>WalnutDSA and the Walnut Digital Signature Algorithm are
      trademarks of Veridify Security Inc.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document specifies the conventions for using the Walnut Digital
      Signature Algorithm (WalnutDSA) <xref target="WALNUTDSA"
      format="default"/> for digital signatures with the CBOR Object Signing
      and Encryption (COSE) syntax <xref target="RFC8152" format="default"/>.
      WalnutDSA is a Group Theoretic signature scheme <xref target="GTC" format="default"/> where signature validation is both computationally and
      space efficient, even on very small processors.  Unlike many hash-based
      signatures, there is no state required and no limit on the number of
      signatures that can be made.  WalnutDSA private and public keys are
      relatively small; however, the signatures are larger than RSA and
      Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC), but still smaller than most all other
      quantum-resistant schemes (including all hash-based schemes).</t>
      <t>COSE provides a lightweight method to encode structured data.
      WalnutDSA is a lightweight, quantum-resistant digital
      signature algorithm.  The goal of this specification is to
      document a method to leverage WalnutDSA in COSE in a way that
      would allow multiple developers to build compatible
      implementations.</t>
      <t>As with all cryptosystems, the initial versions of WalnutDSA
      underwent significant cryptanalysis, and, in some cases, identified
      potential issues. For more discussion on this topic, a summary of all
      published cryptanalysis can be found in <xref
      target="meth_sec"/>. Validated issues were addressed by
      reparameterization in updated versions of WalnutDSA.  Although the IETF
      has neither evaluated the security properties of WalnutDSA nor endorsed
      WalnutDSA as of this publication, this document provides a method to use
      WalnutDSA in conjunction with IETF protocols.  As always, users of any
      security algorithm are advised to research the security properties of
      the algorithm and make their own judgment about the risks involved.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Motivation</name>
        <t>Recent advances in cryptanalysis <xref target="BH2013"
        format="default"/> and progress in the development of quantum
        computers <xref target="NAS2019" format="default"/> pose a threat to
        widely deployed digital signature algorithms.  As a result, there is a
        need to prepare for a day that cryptosystems such as RSA and DSA,
        which depend on discrete logarithm and factoring, cannot be depended
        upon.</t>
        <t>If large-scale quantum computers are ever built, these computers
        will be able to break many of the public key cryptosystems currently
        in use.  A post-quantum cryptosystem <xref target="PQC"
        format="default"/> is a system that is secure against quantum
        computers that have more than a trivial number of quantum bits
        (qubits).  It is open to conjecture when it will be feasible to build
        such computers; however, RSA, DSA, the Elliptic Curve Digital
        Signature Algorithm (ECDSA), and the Edwards-Curve Digital Signature
        Algorithm (EdDSA) are all vulnerable if large-scale quantum computers
        come to pass.</t>

        <t>WalnutDSA does not depend on the difficulty of discrete
	logarithms or factoring.  As a result, this algorithm is
	considered to be resistant to post-quantum attacks.</t>
        <t>Today, RSA and ECDSA are often used to digitally sign
	software updates.  Unfortunately, implementations of RSA and
	ECDSA can be relatively large, and verification can take a
	significant amount of time on some very small processors.
	Therefore, we desire a digital signature scheme that verifies
	faster with less code.  Moreover, in preparation for a day
	when RSA, DSA, and ECDSA cannot be depended upon, a digital
	signature algorithm is needed that will remain secure even if
	there are significant cryptanalytic advances or a large-scale
	quantum computer is invented.  WalnutDSA, specified in <xref target="WALNUTSPEC" format="default"/>, is a quantum-resistant algorithm
	that addresses these requirements.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Trademark Notice</name>
        <t>WalnutDSA and the Walnut Digital Signature Algorithm are
	trademarks of Veridify Security Inc.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>



        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>

    </section>
    <section anchor="alg_overview" numbered="true" toc="default">

      <name>WalnutDSA Algorithm Overview</name>
      <t>This specification makes use of WalnutDSA signatures as
      described in <xref target="WALNUTDSA" format="default"/> and more concretely
      specified in <xref target="WALNUTSPEC" format="default"/>.  WalnutDSA is a
      Group Theoretic cryptographic signature scheme that leverages
      infinite group theory as the basis of its security and maps that
      to a one-way evaluation of a series of matrices over small
      finite fields with permuted multiplicants based on the group
      input.  WalnutDSA leverages the SHA2-256 and SHA2-512 one-way
      hash algorithms <xref target="SHA2" format="default"/> in a hash-then-sign
      process.</t>
      <t>WalnutDSA is based on a one-way function, E-multiplication,
      which is an action on the infinite group.  A single
      E-multiplication step takes as input a matrix and permutation, a
      generator in the group, and a set of T-values (entries in the
      finite field) and outputs a new matrix and permutation.  To
      process a long string of generators (like a WalnutDSA
      signature), E-multiplication is iterated over each generator.
      Due to its structure, E-multiplication is extremely easy to
      implement.</t>


      <t>In addition to being quantum resistant, the two main benefits
      of using WalnutDSA are that the verification implementation is
      very small and WalnutDSA signature verification is extremely
      fast, even on very small processors (including 16- and even
      8-bit microcontrollers).  This lends it well to use in constrained and/or
      time-sensitive environments.</t>
      <t>WalnutDSA has several parameters required to process a signature.
      The main parameters are N and q.  The parameter N defines the size of
      the group by defining the number of strands in use and implies working
      in an NxN matrix.  The parameter q defines the number of elements in the
      finite field.  Signature verification also requires a set of T-values,
      which is an ordered list of N entries in the finite field F_q.</t>
      <t>A WalnutDSA signature is just a string of generators in the
      infinite group, packed into a byte string.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="alg_ids" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>WalnutDSA Algorithm Identifiers</name>
      <t>The CBOR Object Signing and Encryption (COSE) syntax <xref target="RFC8152" format="default"/> supports two signature algorithm schemes.
      This specification makes use of the signature with appendix scheme for
      WalnutDSA signatures.</t>

      <t>The signature value is a large byte string.  The byte string is
      designed for easy parsing, and it includes a length (number of
      generators) and type codes that indirectly provide all of the
      information that is needed to parse the byte string during
      signature validation.</t>
      <t>When using a COSE key for this algorithm, the following checks are
      made:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The "kty" field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present, and it
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "WalnutDSA".</li>
        <li>If the "alg" field is present, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "WalnutDSA".</li>
        <li>If the "key_ops" field is present, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include "sign" when
	creating a WalnutDSA signature.</li>
        <li>If the "key_ops" field is present, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include "verify"
	when verifying a WalnutDSA signature.</li>
        <li>If the "kid" field is present, it <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used to identify the
	WalnutDSA Key.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec_consider" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Implementation Security Considerations</name>
        <t>Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> protect the private keys.  Use of a hardware
	security module (HSM) is one way to protect the private keys.
	Compromising the private keys may result in the ability to forge
	signatures.  As a result, when a private key
	is stored on non-volatile media or stored in a virtual machine
	environment, care must be taken to preserve confidentiality and
	integrity.</t>
        <t>The generation of private keys relies on random numbers.  The use of
	inadequate pseudorandom number generators (PRNGs) to generate these
	values can result in little or no security.  An attacker may find it
	much easier to reproduce the PRNG environment that produced the keys,
	searching the resulting small set of possibilities, rather than brute
	force searching the whole key space.  The generation of quality
	random numbers is difficult, and <xref target="RFC4086" format="default"/>
	offers important guidance in this area.</t>
        <t>The generation of WalnutDSA signatures also depends on random
        numbers.  While the consequences of an inadequate PRNG to generate
        these values are much less severe than the generation of private keys,
        the guidance in <xref target="RFC4086" format="default"/> remains
        important.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default" anchor="meth_sec">
        <name>Method Security Considerations</name>
        <t>The Walnut Digital Signature Algorithm has undergone
	significant cryptanalysis since it was first introduced, and
	several weaknesses were found in early versions of the method,
	resulting in the description of several attacks with exponential
	computational complexity.
	A full writeup of all the analysis can be found in
	<xref target="WalnutDSAAnalysis" format="default"/>.  In summary,
	the original suggested parameters (N=8, q=32) were too small, leading to
	many of these exponential-growth attacks being practical.  However, current
	parameters render these attacks impractical.  The following
	paragraphs summarize the analysis and how the current
	parameters defeat all the previous attacks.</t>

        <t>First, the team of Hart et al. found a universal forgery attack
        based on a group-factoring problem that runs in O(q<sup>(N-1)/2</sup>)
        with a memory complexity of log_2(q) N<sup>2</sup>
        q<sup>(N-1)/2</sup>.  With parameters N=10 and q=M31 (the Mersenne
        prime 2<sup>31</sup> - 1), the runtime is 2<sup>139</sup> and memory
        complexity is 2<sup>151</sup>.  W.&nbsp;Beullens found a modification
        of this attack but its runtime is even longer.</t>
        <t>Next, Beullens and Blackburn found several issues with the
	original method and parameters.  First, they used a Pollard-Rho
	attack and discovered the original public key space was too
	small.  Specifically, they require that q<sup>N(N-1)-1</sup> &gt;
	2<sup>2*Security Level</sup>.  One can clearly see that (N=10, q=M31)
	provides 128-bit security and (N=10, q=M61) provides 256-bit
	security.</t>
        <t>Beullens and Blackburn also found two issues with the
	original message encoder of WalnutDSA.  First, the original
	encoder was non-injective, which reduced the available
	signature space.  This was repaired in an update.  Second,
	they pointed out that the dimension of the vector space
	generated by the encoder was too small.  Specifically, they
	require that q<sup>dimension</sup> &gt; 2<sup>(2*Security Level)</sup>.  With N=10,
	the current encoder produces a dimension of 66, which clearly
	provides sufficient security with q=M31 or q=M61.</t>
        <t>The final issue discovered by Beullens and Blackburn was a process
        to theoretically "reverse" E-multiplication.  First, their process
        requires knowing the initial matrix and permutation (which are known
        for WalnutDSA).  But more importantly, their process runs at
        O(q<sup>((N-1)/2)</sup>), which for (N=10, q=M31) is greater than
        2<sup>128</sup>.</t>
        <t>A team at Steven's Institute leveraged a length-shortening
	attack that enabled them to remove the cloaking elements and
	then solve a conjugacy search problem to derive the private
	keys.  Their attack requires both knowledge of the permutation
	being cloaked and also that the cloaking elements themselves
	are conjugates.  By adding additional concealed cloaking
	elements, the attack requires an N! search for each cloaking
	element.  By inserting k concealed cloaking elements, this
	requires the attacker to perform (N!)<sup>k</sup> work.  This allows
	k to be set to meet the desired security level.</t>
        <t>Finally, Merz and Petit discovered that using a Garside
	Normal Form of a WalnutDSA signature enabled them to find
	commonalities with the Garside Normal Form of the encoded
	message.  Using those commonalities, they were able to splice
	into a signature and create forgeries.  Increasing the number
	of cloaking elements, specifically within the encoded message,
	sufficiently obscures the commonalities and blocks this
	attack.</t>

        <t>In summary, most of these attacks are exponential in runtime and it
        can be shown that current parameters put the runtime beyond the
        desired security level.  The final two attacks are also sufficiently
        blocked to the desired security level.</t>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has added entries for WalnutDSA signatures in the
      "COSE Algorithms" registry and WalnutDSA public keys in the "COSE
      Key Types" and "COSE Key Type Parameters" registries.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>COSE Algorithms Registry Entry</name>
        <t>The following new  entry has been registered in the "COSE Algorithms" registry:</t>

<dl>
<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>WalnutDSA
</dd>

<dt>Value:
</dt>
<dd>-260
</dd>

<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>WalnutDSA signature
</dd>

<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021
</dd>

<dt>Recommended:
</dt>
<dd>No
</dd>

</dl>

      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>COSE Key Types Registry Entry</name>
        <t>The following new entry has been registered in the "COSE Key Types" registry:</t>

<dl>
<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>WalnutDSA
</dd>

<dt>Value:
</dt>
<dd>6
</dd>

<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>WalnutDSA public key
</dd>

<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021

</dd>

</dl>

      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>COSE Key Type Parameters Registry Entries</name>
        <t>The following sections detail the additions to the "COSE Key Type Parameters" registry.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>WalnutDSA Parameter: N</name>
          <t>The new entry, N, has been registered in the "COSE Key Type Parameters" registry
	    as follows:</t>
   
<dl>

<dt>Key Type:
</dt>
<dd>6
</dd>

<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>N
</dd>

<dt>Label:
</dt>
<dd>-1
</dd>

<dt>CBOR Type:
</dt>
<dd>uint
</dd>

<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>Group and Matrix (NxN) size
</dd>

<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021
</dd>

</dl>

        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>WalnutDSA Parameter: q</name>
          <t>The new entry, q, has been registered in the "COSE Key Type Parameters" registry
	    as follows:</t>

<dl>

<dt>Key Type:
</dt>
<dd>6
</dd>

<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>q
</dd>

<dt>Label:
</dt>
<dd>-2
</dd>

<dt>CBOR Type:
</dt>
<dd>uint
</dd>

<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>Finite field F_q
</dd>

<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021
</dd>

</dl>


        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>WalnutDSA Parameter: t-values</name>
          <t>The new entry, t-values, has been registered in the "COSE Key Type Parameters" registry
	    as follows:</t>


<dl>

<dt>Key Type:
</dt>
<dd>6
</dd>


<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>t-values
</dd>


<dt>Label:
</dt>
<dd>-3
</dd>


 <dt>CBOR Type:
 </dt>
<dd>array (of uint)
</dd>


<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>List of T-values, entries in F_q
</dd>


<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021
</dd>

</dl>


        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>WalnutDSA Parameter: matrix 1</name>
          <t>The new entry, matrix 1, has been registered in the "COSE Key Type Parameters" registry
	    as follows:</t>

<dl>

<dt>Key Type:
</dt>
<dd>6
</dd>

<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>matrix 1
</dd>

<dt>Label:
</dt>
<dd>-4
</dd>

<dt>CBOR Type:
</dt>
<dd>array (of array of uint)
</dd>

<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>NxN Matrix of entries in F_q in column-major form
</dd>

<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021
</dd>

</dl>





        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>WalnutDSA Parameter: permutation 1</name>
          <t>The new entry, permutation 1, has been registered in the "COSE Key Type Parameters" registry
	    as follows:</t>

<dl>

<dt>Key Type: 
</dt>
<dd>6
</dd>

<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>permutation 1
</dd>

<dt>Label:
</dt>
<dd>-5
</dd>

<dt>CBOR Type:
</dt>
<dd>array (of uint)
</dd>

<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>Permutation associated with matrix 1
</dd>

<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021
</dd>

</dl>

        </section>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>WalnutDSA Parameter: matrix 2</name>
          <t>The new entry, matrix 2, has been registered in the "COSE Key Type Parameters" registry
	    as follows:</t>

<dl>

<dt>Key Type:
</dt>
<dd>6
</dd>

<dt>Name:
</dt>
<dd>matrix 2
</dd>

<dt>Label:
</dt>
<dd>-6
</dd>

<dt>CBOR Type:
</dt>
<dd>array (of array of uint)
</dd>

<dt>Description:
</dt>
<dd>NxN Matrix of entries in F_q in column-major form
</dd>

<dt>Reference:
</dt>
<dd>RFC 9021
</dd>

</dl>


        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>


  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8152.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="SHA2">
          <front>
            <title>Secure Hash Standard (SHS)</title>
            <author initials="" surname="" fullname="">
              <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="2015"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.6028/NIST.FIPS.180-4"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="WALNUTDSA">
          <front>
            <title>WalnutDSA(TM): A group theoretic digital signature algorithm</title>
            <author initials="I" surname="Anshel" fullname="Iris Anshel">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D" surname="Atkins" fullname="Derek Atkins">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D" surname="Goldfeld" fullname="Dorian Goldfeld">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="P" surname="Gunnells" fullname="Paul E. Gunnells">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="November" year="2020"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1080/23799927.2020.1831613"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

      <reference anchor="WALNUTSPEC" target="https://csrc.nist.gov/projects/post-quantum-cryptography/round-1-submissions">
          <front>
            <title>The Walnut Digital Signature Algorithm Specification</title>
            <author initials="I" surname="Anshel" fullname="Iris Anshel">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D" surname="Atkins" fullname="Derek Atkins">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D" surname="Goldfeld" fullname="Dorian Goldfeld">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="P" surname="Gunnells" fullname="Paul Gunnells">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="November" year="2018"/>
          </front>
<refcontent>Post-Quantum Cryptography</refcontent>
      </reference>


        <reference anchor="GTC" target="https://www.crcpress.com/Group-Theoretic-Cryptography/Vasco-Steinwandt/p/book/9781584888369">
          <front>
            <title>Group Theoretic Cryptography</title>
            <author initials="M" surname="Vasco" fullname="Maria Isabel Gonzalez Vasco">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R" surname="Steinwandt" fullname="Rainer Steinwandt">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="April" year="2015"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="ISBN" value="9781584888369"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="WalnutDSAAnalysis" target="https://eprint.iacr.org/2019/472">
          <front>
            <title>Defeating the Hart et al, Beullens-Blackburn, Kotov-Menshov-Ushakov, and Merz-Petit Attacks on WalnutDSA(TM)</title>
            <author initials="I" surname="Anshel" fullname="Iris Anshel">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D" surname="Atkins" fullname="Derek Atkins">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D" surname="Goldfeld" fullname="Dorian Goldfeld">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="P" surname="Gunnells" fullname="Paul E Gunnells">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="May" year="2019"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4086.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="BH2013" target="https://www.slideshare.net/astamos/bh-slides">
          <front>
            <title>The Factoring Dead: Preparing for the Cryptopocalypse</title>
            <author initials="T" surname="Ptacek" fullname="Thomas Ptacek">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J" surname="Ritter" fullname="Tom Ritter,  ">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J" surname="Samuel" fullname="Javed Samue">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A" surname="Stamos" fullname="Alex Stamos">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="2013"/>
          </front>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="NAS2019">
          <front>
            <title>Quantum Computing: Progress and Prospects</title>
            <author>
              <organization>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019"/>
          </front>
	    <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17226/25196"/>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="PQC">
          <front>
            <title>Introduction to post-quantum cryptography</title>
            <author initials="D" surname="Bernstein" fullname="Daniel J. Bernstein">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2009"/>
          </front>
	    <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/978-3-540-88702-7"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>A big thank you to <contact fullname="Russ Housley"/> for his input
      on the concepts and text of this document.</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
