<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-core-dev-urn-11" number="9039" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" category="std" consensus="true" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DEV URN">Uniform Resource Names for Device Identifiers</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9039"/>
    <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <code>02420</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 421-9990</phone>
        <email>fluffy@iii.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="Z." surname="Shelby" fullname="Zach Shelby">
      <organization>
             Edge Impulse
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3031 Tisch Way</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
          <code>95128</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>zach@edgeimpulse.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2021"/>
    <keyword>URN</keyword>
    <keyword>device identifier</keyword>
    <keyword>IMEI</keyword>
    <keyword>1-Wire</keyword>
    <keyword>MAC address</keyword>
    <keyword>EUI-48</keyword>
    <keyword>EUI-64</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a new Uniform Resource Name (URN) namespace for
  hardware device identifiers. A general representation of device
  identity can be useful in many applications, such as in sensor data
  streams and storage or in equipment inventories. A URN-based
  representation can be passed along in applications that
  need the information.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>This document describes a new Uniform Resource Name (URN) <xref target="RFC8141" format="default"/> namespace for hardware
    device identifiers. A general representation of device identity
    can be useful in many applications, such as in sensor data streams
    and storage 
     or in equipment inventories <xref target="RFC7252" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8428" format="default"/> <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>A URN-based representation can be passed along in applications
    that need the information. It fits particularly well for protocols
    mechanisms that are designed to carry URNs <xref target="RFC7230" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC7540" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC3261" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC7252" format="default"/>. Finally, URNs can
    also be easily carried and stored in formats such as XML <xref target="W3C.REC-xml-19980210" format="default"/>, JSON <xref target="RFC8259" format="default"/>, or
    SenML <xref target="RFC8428" format="default"/>.  Using URNs in these formats is
    often preferable as they are universally recognized and
    self-describing and therefore avoid the need to agree to
    interpret an octet string as a specific form of a Media Access Control (MAC) address, for
    instance. Passing URNs may consume additional bytes compared to,
    for instance, passing 4-byte binary IPv4 addresses, but the former offers
    some flexibility in return.</t>
      <t>This document defines identifier URN types for situations where no
    such convenient type already exists. For instance, <xref target="RFC6920" format="default"/> defines cryptographic identifiers, <xref target="RFC7254" format="default"/> defines International Mobile station Equipment
    Identity (IMEI) identifiers for use with 3GPP cellular systems,
    and <xref target="RFC8464" format="default"/> defines Mobile
    Equipment Identity (MEID) identifiers for use with 3GPP2 cellular
    systems. Those URN types should be employed when such identifiers
    are transported; this document does not redefine these identifiers in
    any way.</t>


      <t>Universally Unique Identifier (UUID) URNs <xref target="RFC4122" format="default"/> are another alternative way to represent
    device identifiers and already support MAC addresses as one type
    of identifier. However, UUIDs can be inconvenient in
    environments where it is important that the identifiers be as
    simple as possible and where additional requirements on stable
    storage, real-time clocks, and identifier length can be
    prohibitive. Often, UUID-based identifiers are preferred for
    general purpose uses instead of the MAC-based device URNs defined in
    this document. The device URNs are recommended for constrained
    environments.</t>
      <t>Future device identifier types can extend the device URN
    type defined in this document (see <xref target="iana" format="default"/>), or they can define their own URNs.</t>
      <t>Note that long-term stable unique identifiers are problematic
    for privacy reasons and should be used with care as
    described in <xref target="RFC7721" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The rest of this document is organized as follows. <xref target="devurn" format="default"/> defines the "DEV" URN type, and <xref target="subtypes" format="default"/> defines subtypes for IEEE MAC-48, EUI-48 and
    EUI-64 addresses, and 1-Wire device identifiers.  <xref target="ex" format="default"/> gives examples. <xref target="sec" format="default"/> discusses the
    security and privacy considerations of the new URN type. Finally, <xref target="iana" format="default"/> specifies the IANA registration for the new URN
    type and sets requirements for subtype allocations within this
    type.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="kwd" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="devurn" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>DEV URN Definition</name>
<dl>
      <dt>Namespace Identifier:</dt><dd>"dev"</dd>
      <dt>Version:</dt><dd>1</dd>
      <dt>Date:</dt><dd>2020-06-24</dd>
      <dt>Registrant:</dt><dd>IETF and the CORE Working Group. Should the working
      group cease to exist, discussion should be directed to the 
      Applications and Real-Time Area or general IETF discussion forums, or the IESG.</dd></dl>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Purpose</name>
        <t>The DEV URNs identify devices with device-specific
	identifiers such as network card hardware addresses. DEV URNs
	are scoped to be globally applicable (see <xref target="RFC8141" sectionFormat="comma" section="6.4.1"/>) and, in general, enable
	systems to use these identifiers from multiple sources in an
	interoperable manner. Note that in some deployments, ensuring
	uniqueness requires care if manual or local assignment
	mechanisms are used, as discussed in <xref target="assignment" format="default"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	Some typical DEV URN applications include equipment
	inventories and smart object systems.
	</t>
	<t>
	DEV URNs can be used in various ways in applications, software
	systems, and network components, in tasks ranging from
	discovery (for instance, when discovering 1-Wire network
	devices or detecting MAC-addressable devices on a LAN) to
	intrusion detection systems and simple catalogues of system
	information.
	</t>
	<t>
	While it is possible to implement resolution systems for specific
	applications or network locations, DEV URNs are typically not used in
	a way that requires resolution beyond direct observation of the
	relevant identifier fields in local link communication. However, it is
	often useful to be able to pass device identifier information in generic
	URN fields in databases or protocol fields, which makes the use of
	URNs for this purpose convenient.
	</t>
	<t>
	The DEV URN namespace complements existing namespaces such as those
	involving IMEI or UUID identifiers. DEV URNs are expected to be a part
	of the IETF-provided basic URN types, covering identifiers that have
	previously not been possible to use in URNs.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="syntax" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Syntax</name>
        <t>The identifier is expressed in
	ASCII characters and has a hierarchical structure as
	follows:</t>
        <sourcecode name="" type="abnf"><![CDATA[
devurn = "urn:dev:" body componentpart
body = macbody / owbody / orgbody / osbody / opsbody / otherbody
macbody = %s"mac:" hexstring
owbody = %s"ow:" hexstring
orgbody = %s"org:" posnumber "-" identifier *( ":" identifier )
osbody = %s"os:" posnumber "-" serial *( ":" identifier )
opsbody = %s"ops:" posnumber "-" product "-" serial
          *( ":" identifier )
otherbody = subtype ":" identifier *( ":" identifier )
subtype = LALPHA *(DIGIT / LALPHA)
identifier = 1*devunreserved
identifiernodash = 1*devunreservednodash
product = identifiernodash
serial = identifier
componentpart = *( "_" identifier )
devunreservednodash = ALPHA / DIGIT / "."
devunreserved = devunreservednodash / "-"
hexstring = 1*(hexdigit hexdigit)
hexdigit = DIGIT / "a" / "b" / "c" / "d" / "e" / "f"
posnumber = NZDIGIT *DIGIT
ALPHA =  %x41-5A / %x61-7A 
LALPHA =  %x41-5A
NZDIGIT = %x31-39
DIGIT =  %x30-39
]]></sourcecode>
        <t>The above syntax is represented in Augmented Backus-Naur
	Form (ABNF) as defined in <xref target="RFC5234" format="default"/> and
	<xref target="RFC7405" format="default"/>. The syntax also copies the DIGIT and
	ALPHA rules originally defined in <xref target="RFC5234" format="default"/>,
	exactly as defined there.</t>
        <t>The device identifier namespace includes five subtypes (see
	<xref target="subtypes" format="default"/>), and more may be defined in the future as
	specified in <xref target="iana" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>The optional underscore-separated components at the end of
        the DEV URN depict individual aspects of a
	device. The specific strings and their semantics are up to the
	designers of the device but could be used to refer to
	specific interfaces or functions within the device.</t>
        <t>With the exception of the MAC address and 1-Wire DEV URNs,
        each DEV URN may also contain optional colon-separated
        identifiers. These are provided for extensibility.</t>
        <t>There are no special character encoding rules or
	considerations for conforming with the URN syntax beyond
	those applicable for URNs in general <xref target="RFC8141" format="default"/>
	or the context where these URNs are carried (e.g., inside JSON
	<xref target="RFC8259" format="default"/> or SenML <xref target="RFC8428" format="default"/>). Due to the SenML rules in <xref target="RFC8428" sectionFormat="comma" section="4.5.1"/>, it is not desirable to use percent-encoding in DEV
	URNs, and the subtypes defined in this specification do not
	really benefit from percent-encoding. However, this
	specification does not deviate from the general syntax of URNs
	or their processing and normalization rules as specified in
	<xref target="RFC3986" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8141" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>DEV URNs do not use r-, q-, or f-components as defined in
        <xref target="RFC8141" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Specific subtypes of DEV URNs may be validated through
	mechanisms discussed in <xref target="subtypes" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>The string representation of the device
	identifier URN is fully compatible with
	the URN syntax.</t>
        <section numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Character Case and URN-Equivalence</name>
          <t>The DEV URN syntax allows both uppercase and lowercase
	characters. The URN-equivalence of the DEV URNs is defined per
	<xref target="RFC8141" sectionFormat="comma" section="3.1"/>, i.e., two URNs are
	URN-equivalent if their assigned-name portions are
	octet-by-octet equal after applying case normalization to the
	URI scheme ("urn") and namespace identifier ("dev").
	The rest of the DEV URN is
	compared in a case-sensitive manner. It should be noted that
	URN-equivalence matching merely quickly shows that two URNs
	are definitely the same for the purposes of caching and other
	similar uses. Two DEV URNs may still refer to the same entity and may not be found to be URN-equivalent according to the <xref target="RFC8141" format="default"/>
	definition. For instance, in ABNF, strings are
	case insensitive (see <xref target="RFC5234" sectionFormat="comma" section="2.3"/>),
	and a MAC address could be represented either with uppercase
	or lowercase hexadecimal digits.</t>
          <t>Character case is not otherwise significant for the DEV URN
        subtypes defined in this document.  However, future subtypes
        might include identifiers that use encodings such as base64,
        which encodes strings in a larger variety of characters and
        might even encode binary data.</t>
          <t>To facilitate equivalence checks, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that
	implementations always use lowercase letters where they have
	a choice in case, unless there is a reason otherwise. (Such a
	reason might be, for instance, the use of a subtype that
	requires the use of both uppercase and lowercase
	letters.)</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="assignment" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Assignment</name>
        <t>The process for identifier
	assignment is dependent on the used subtype and is documented in the
	specific subsection under <xref target="subtypes" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Device identifiers are generally expected to identify a
        unique device,
	barring the accidental issue of multiple devices with the same
	identifiers. In many cases, device identifiers can also be
	changed by users or are sometimes assigned in an algorithmic
	or local fashion. Any potential conflicts arising from such
	assignments are not something that the DEV URNs as such
	manage; they simply are there to refer to a particular
	identifier. And, of course, a single device may (and often
        does) have multiple identifiers, e.g., identifiers associated
        with different link technologies it supports.</t>
        <t>The DEV URN type <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> only be used for 
	hardware-based identifiers that are expected to be
        persistent (with some limits, as discussed above).</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Security and Privacy</name>
        <t>As discussed in <xref target="sec" format="default"/>,
	care must be taken in the use of device-identifier-based
	identifiers due to their nature as long-term identifiers that
	are not normally changeable.  Leakage of these identifiers
	outside systems where their use is justified should be
	controlled.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Interoperability</name>
        <t>There are no specific interoperability
	concerns.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Resolution</name>
        <t>The device identifiers are not expected to be globally
	resolvable. No identifier resolution system is expected. Systems may
	perform local matching of identifiers to previously seen identifiers
	or configured information, however.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Documentation</name>
        <t>See RFC 9039.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Additional Information</name>
        <t>See <xref target="intro" format="default"/> for a discussion of related namespaces.</t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Revision Information</name>
        <t>This is the first version of this registration.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="subtypes" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>DEV URN Subtypes</name>
      <section anchor="mac" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>MAC Addresses</name>
        <t>DEV URNs of the "mac" subtype are based on the EUI-64 identifier
<xref target="IEEE.EUI64" format="default"/> derived from a device with a built-in
64-bit EUI-64. The EUI-64 is formed from 24 or 36 bits of organization
identifier followed by 40 or 28 bits of device-specific extension
identifier assigned by that organization.</t>
        <t>In the DEV URN "mac" subtype, the hexstring is simply the full
EUI-64 identifier represented as a hexadecimal string. It is always
exactly 16 characters long.</t>
        <t>MAC-48 and EUI-48 identifiers are also supported by the same DEV
URN subtype.  To convert a MAC-48 address to an EUI-64 identifier, the
Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI) of the MAC-48 address (the first three octets) becomes the
organization identifier of the EUI-64 (the first three octets).  The
fourth and fifth octets of the EUI are set to the fixed value 0xffff
(hexadecimal).  The last three octets of the MAC-48 address become the
last three octets of the EUI-64. The same process is used to convert
an EUI-48 identifier, but the fixed value 0xfffe is used instead.</t>
        <t>Identifier assignment for all of these identifiers rests within the
IEEE Registration Authority.</t>
        <t>Note that where randomized MAC addresses are used, the resulting
DEV URNs cannot be expected to have uniqueness, as discussed in <xref target="assignment" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="s1wire" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>1-Wire Device Identifiers</name>

        <t>The 1-Wire system is a device communications bus system designed
by Dallas Semiconductor Corporation. (1-Wire is a registered trademark.) 1-Wire devices are identified by
a 64-bit identifier that consists of an 8-bit family code, a 48-bit
identifier unique within a family, and an 8-bit Cyclic Redundancy Check (CRC) code <xref target="OW" format="default"/>.
</t>

        <t>In DEV URNs with the "ow" subtype, the hexstring is a representation
of the full 64-bit identifier as a hexadecimal string. It is always
exactly 16 characters long. Note that the last two characters
represent the 8-bit CRC code. Implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> check the validity
of this code.</t>
        <t>Family code and identifier assignment for all 1-Wire devices rests
with the manufacturers.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="org" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Organization-Defined Identifiers</name>
        <t>Device identifiers that have only a meaning within an
  organization can also be used to represent vendor-specific or
  experimental identifiers or identifiers designed for use within the
  context of an organization.</t>
        <t>Organizations are identified by their Private Enterprise Number
  (PEN) <xref target="RFC2578" format="default"/>. These numbers can be obtained from
  IANA. Current PEN assignments can be viewed at <eref  brackets="angle" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/enterprise-numbers/"/>,
 and new assignments are requested at <eref brackets="angle" target="https://pen.iana.org/pen/PenApplication.page"/>.</t>
        <t>Note that when included in an "org" DEV URN, the number cannot
  be zero or have leading zeroes, as the ABNF requires the number to
  start with a non-zero digit.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="os" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Organization Serial Numbers</name>
        <t>The "os" subtype specifies an organization and serial
  number. Organizations are identified by their PEN. As with the
  organization-defined identifiers (<xref target="org" format="default"/>), PEN number
  assignments are maintained by IANA, and assignments for new
  organizations can be made easily.

        </t>
<aside><t>
          Historical note: The "os" subtype was originally defined
      in the Open Mobile Alliance "Lightweight Machine to Machine"
      standard <xref target="LwM2M" format="default"/> but has been incorporated here
      to collect all syntaxes associated with DEV URNs in one place.  At
      the same time, the syntax of this subtype was changed to avoid
      the possibility of characters that are not allowed in the SenML Name
      field (see <xref target="RFC8428" sectionFormat="comma" section="4.5.1"/>).</t>
        </aside>
        <t>Organization serial number DEV URNs consist of the PEN number and
  the serial number. As with other DEV URNs, for carrying additional
  information and extensibility, optional colon-separated identifiers
  and underscore-separated components may also be included. The serial
  numbers themselves are defined by the organization, and this
  specification does not specify how they are allocated.</t>
        <t>Organizations are also encouraged to select serial number formats
  that avoid the possibility of ambiguity in the form of leading zeroes
  or otherwise.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ops" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Organization Product and Serial Numbers</name>
        <t>The DEV URN "ops" subtype was originally defined in the
  LwM2M standard but has been incorporated here to collect all syntaxes
  associated with DEV URNs in one place. The "ops" subtype specifies
  an organization, product class, and a serial number. Organizations
  are identified by their PEN. Again, as with the
  organization-defined identifiers (<xref target="org" format="default"/>), PEN number
  assignments are maintained by IANA.
        </t>

<aside><t>
         Historical note: As with the "os" subtype, the "ops" subtype
    was originally defined in the Open Mobile Alliance "Lightweight Machine to Machine" standard <xref target="LwM2M" format="default"/>.
        </t></aside>
        <t>Organization product and serial number DEV URNs consist of the
  PEN number, product class, and the serial number. As with other DEV
  URNs, for carrying additional information and extensibility,
  optional colon-separated identifiers and underscore-separated
  components may also be included. Both the product class and serial
  numbers themselves are defined by the organization, and this
  specification does not specify how they are allocated.</t>
        <t>Organizations are also encouraged to select product and serial
  number formats that avoid possibility for ambiguity.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="futuresubtypes" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Future Subtypes</name>
        <t>Additional subtypes may be defined in future
  specifications. See <xref target="iana" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>The DEV URN "example" subtype is reserved for use in examples. It
  has no specific requirements beyond those expressed by the ABNF in
  <xref target="syntax" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ex" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Examples</name>
      <t>The following provides some examples of DEV URNs:
</t>
<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>URN</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>urn:dev:mac:0024beffff804ff1</td>
      <td>The MAC-48 address of 0024be804ff1, converted to EUI-64 format</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td>                                                            urn:dev:mac:0024befffe804ff1</td>
      <td>                                                                  The EUI-48 address of 0024be804ff1, converted to EUI-64 format</td>
    </tr>
 <tr>      
<td>urn:dev:mac:acde48234567019f</td> 
<td>The EUI-64 address of                                                acde48234567019f                                                        
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>      <td>                                                                    urn:dev:ow:10e2073a01080063</td> 
<td>A 1-Wire temperature                                              sensor</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
   <td>urn:dev:ow:264437f5000000ed_humidity</td>
   <td>The humidity part of a multi-sensor                                                       device                                                                     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
<td>urn:dev:ow:264437f5000000ed_temperature</td>
  <td>The temperature part of a multi-sensor device</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
<td>urn:dev:org:32473-foo</td>
  <td>An organization-specific URN in the example organization 32473 in <xref target="RFC5612"/>
</td>
    </tr>
 
       <tr>
<td>urn:dev:os:32473-123456</td>
  <td>Device 123456 in the example organization in <xref target="RFC5612"/></td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
<td>urn:dev:os:32473-12-34-56</td>
  <td>A serial number with dashes in it</td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
<td>urn:dev:ops:32473-Refrigerator-5002</td>
  <td>Refrigerator serial number 5002 in the example organization in <xref target="RFC5612"/></td>
    </tr>

    <tr>
<td>urn:dev:example:new-1-2-3_comp</td>
  <td>An example of something that is not defined today, and is not one of the mac, ow, os, or ops subtypes</td>
    </tr>

  </tbody>
</table>
      <t>The DEV URNs themselves can then appear in various contexts. A
simple example of this is the use of DEV URNs in SenML data.  This example from <xref target="RFC8428" format="default"/> shows a
measurement from a 1-Wire temperature gauge encoded in the JSON
syntax:

</t>
      <sourcecode name="" type="json"><![CDATA[
   [
     {"n":"urn:dev:ow:10e2073a01080063","u":"Cel","v":23.1}
   ]
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>On most devices, the user can display device identifiers. Depending
on circumstances, device identifiers may or may not be modified or
tampered with by the user. An implementation of the DEV URN <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> preserve
such limitations and behaviors associated with the device identifiers. In particular,
a device identifier that is intended to be immutable should not become mutable
as a part of implementing the DEV URN type. More generally, nothing in
this document should be construed to override what the relevant device
specifications have already said about the identifiers.</t>
      <section anchor="priv" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Privacy</name>
        <t>Other devices in the same network may or may not be able to
identify the device. For instance, on an Ethernet network, the MAC
address of a device is visible to all other devices.</t>
        <t>DEV URNs often represent long-term stable unique identifiers for
devices. Such identifiers may have privacy and security implications
because they may enable correlating information about a specific
device over a long period of time, location tracking, and device-specific vulnerability exploitation <xref target="RFC7721" format="default"/>. Also, in
some systems, there is no easy way to change the identifier. Therefore,
these identifiers need to be used with care, and special care should
be taken to avoid leaking identifiers outside of the system that is intended
to use them.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="valid" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Validity</name>
        <t>Information about identifiers may have significant effects in some
applications. For instance, in many sensor systems, the identifier
information is used for deciding how to use the data carried in a
measurement report. In some other systems, identifiers may be used in
policy decisions.</t>
        <t>It is important that systems be designed to take into account the
possibility of devices reporting incorrect identifiers (either
accidentally or maliciously) and the manipulation of identifiers in
communications by illegitimate entities. Integrity
protection of communications or data objects, the use of trusted
devices, and various management practices can help address these
issues. </t>
        <t>Similar to the advice in <xref target="RFC4122" sectionFormat="comma" section="6"/>:
  Do not assume that DEV URNs are hard to guess.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>Per this document, IANA has registered a new URN namespace
  for "dev", as described in <xref target="devurn" format="default"/>.</t>

      <t>IANA has created a "DEV URN Subtypes" registry under "Device Identification". The initial values in this registry are as follows:
      </t>
<table> 
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Subtype</th>   
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>         
    <tr>
      <td>mac</td>
      <td>MAC Addresses</td>
      <td>RFC 9039, <xref target="mac"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>ow</td>
      <td>1-Wire Device Identifiers</td>
      <td>RFC 9039, <xref target="s1wire"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>org</td>
      <td>Organization-Defined Identifiers</td>
      <td>RFC 9039, <xref target="org"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>os</td>
      <td>Organization Serial Numbers</td>
      <td>RFC 9039, <xref target="os"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>ops</td>
      <td>Organization Product and Serial Numbers</td>
      <td>RFC 9039, <xref target="ops"/></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>example</td>
      <td>Reserved for examples</td>
      <td>RFC 9039, <xref target="futuresubtypes"/></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      <t>Additional subtypes for DEV URNs can be defined through
  Specification Required or IESG Approval <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>. These allocations are appropriate when there is
  a new namespace of some type of device identifier that is defined in
 a stable fashion and has a publicly available specification.</t>
      <t>Note that the organization (<xref target="org" format="default"/>) device
  identifiers can also be used in some cases, at least as a temporary
  measure. It is preferable, however, that long-term usage of a
  broadly employed device identifier be registered with IETF rather
  than used through the organization device identifier type.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>

<displayreference target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory" to="CoRE-RD"/>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8141.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="IEEE.EUI64"
target="https://standards.ieee.org/content/dam/ieee-standards/standards/web/documents/tutorials/eui.pdf">
          <front>
<title>Guidelines for Use of Extended Unique Identifier (EUI), Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI), and Company ID (CID)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="2017"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OW" target="https://www.maximintegrated.com/en/design/technical-documents/tutorials/1/1796.html">
          <front>
            <title>Guide to 1-Wire Communication</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Maxim</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="June" year="2008"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4122.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5612.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7540.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7721.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8259.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="W3C.REC-xml-19980210" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/1998/REC-xml-19980210">
          <front>
            <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0</title>
            <author initials="C." surname="Sperberg-McQueen" fullname="C. M. Sperberg-McQueen">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="T." surname="Bray" fullname="Tim Bray">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Paoli" fullname="Jean Paoli">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="1998"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="W3C" value="Recommendation"/>
        </reference>

       <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7252.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8428.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6920.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7254.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7405.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8464.xml"/>

<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory'>
<front>
<title>CoRE Resource Directory</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Amsüss' fullname='Christian Amsüss' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Z' surname='Shelby' fullname='Zach Shelby'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Koster' fullname='Michael Koster'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Bormann' fullname='Carsten Bormann'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='van der Stok' fullname='Peter van der Stok'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month="March" day="7" year="2021"/>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-core-resource-directory-28' />

</reference>

        <reference anchor="LwM2M" target="https://www.openmobilealliance.org/release/LightweightM2M/V1_2-20190124-C/OMA-RD-LightweightM2M-V1_2-20190124-C.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>OMA Lightweight Machine to Machine Requirements</title>
            <author fullname="Open Mobile Alliance"/>
            <date year="2019" month="January"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="OMA Standard" value="Candidate Version 1.2"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Ari Keränen"/>, <contact fullname="Stephen Farrell"/>,
  <contact fullname="Christer Holmberg"/>, <contact fullname="Peter Saint-Andre"/>, <contact fullname="Wouter Cloetens"/>, <contact fullname="Jaime
  Jimenez"/>, <contact fullname="Joseph Knapp"/>, <contact fullname="Padmakumar Subramani"/>, <contact fullname="Mert Ocak"/>, <contact fullname="Hannes
  Tschofenig"/>, <contact fullname="Jim Schaad"/>, <contact fullname="Thomas Fossati"/>, <contact fullname="Carsten Bormann"/>, <contact fullname="Marco
  Tiloca"/>, <contact fullname="Barry Leiba"/>, <contact fullname="Amanda Baber"/>, <contact fullname="Juha Hakala"/>, <contact fullname="Dale Worley"/>, <contact fullname="Warren
  Kumari"/>, <contact fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/>, <contact fullname="Brian Weis"/>, <contact fullname="John Klensin"/>, <contact fullname="Dave Thaler"/>, <contact fullname="Russ
  Housley"/>, <contact fullname="Dan Romascanu"/>, <contact fullname="Éric Vyncke"/>, <contact fullname="Roman Danyliw"/>, and <contact fullname="Ahmad
  Muhanna"/> for their feedback and interesting discussions in this problem
  space. We would also like to note prior documents that focused on
  specific device identifiers, such as <xref target="RFC7254" format="default"/> and
  <xref target="RFC8464" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
