<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="exp" docName="draft-crocker-email-author-04" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="independent" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="2" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3" number="9057">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.7.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Email Author Header Field">Email Author Header Field</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9057"/>
    <author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." surname="Crocker">
      <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2021"/>
    <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>
    <keyword>domain</keyword>
    <keyword>email</keyword>
    <keyword>security</keyword>
    <keyword>messaging</keyword>
    <keyword>dkim</keyword>
    <keyword>spf</keyword>
    <keyword>authentication</keyword>
    <keyword>reporting</keyword>
    <keyword>conformance</keyword>
    <keyword>author</keyword>
    <keyword>origination</keyword>
    <keyword>original</keyword>
    <keyword>from</keyword>
    <keyword>sender</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Internet mail defines the From: header field to indicate the
                author of the message's content and the Sender: field to
                indicate who initially handled the message on the author's
                behalf. The Sender: field is optional if it has the same
                information as the From: field. This was not a problem until
                development of stringent protections on use of the From: field.
                It has prompted Mediators, such as mailing lists, to modify the
                From: field to circumvent mail rejection caused by those
                protections. In effect, the From: field has become dominated by
                its role as a handling identifier.</t>
      
            <t> The current specification augments the altered use of the From:
                field by specifying the Author: field, which ensures
                identification of the original author of the message and is not
                subject to modification by Mediators. This document is published
                as an Experimental RFC to assess community interest, functional
                efficacy, and technical adequacy.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section toc="default" numbered="true">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Internet mail conducts asynchronous communication from an author
                to one or more recipients and is used for ongoing dialog
                amongst them. Email has a long history of serving a wide range
                of human uses and styles, within that simple framework, and the
                mechanisms for making email robust and safe serve that sole
                purpose.</t>
      <t> Internet mail defines the content header's From: field to
                indicate the author of the message and the Sender: field to
                indicate who initially handled the message on the author's
                behalf <xref target="RFC5322" format="default"/>. The Sender: field is optional
                if it has the same information as the From: field. That is, when
                the Sender: field is absent, the From: field has conflated
                semantics as both a handling identifier and a content creator
                identifier. These fields were initially defined in <xref target="RFC0733" format="default"/>, and making the redundant Sender: field
                optional was a small, obvious optimization in the days of
                slower communications, expensive storage, and less powerful
      computers.</t>
      
      <t>The dual semantics were not a problem until development of
                stringent protections on use of the From: field. It has prompted
                Mediators, such as mailing lists, to modify the From: field to
                circumvent receiver mail rejection caused by those protections.
                This affects end-to-end usability of email between the author
                and the final recipients, because mail received from the same
                author is treated differently by the recipient's software,
                depending on what path the message followed. </t>
             <t>By way of example, mail originating with: </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
From:  Example User <user@example.com>
]]></artwork>
            <t> which is sent directly to a recipient, will show the
                author's display name correctly and can correctly analyze,
                filter, and aggregate mail from the author based on their email
                address. However, if the author sends through a mailing list and
                the mailing list conducts a common form of From: modification
                needed to bypass enforcement of stringent authentication
                policies, then the received message might instead have a From:
                field showing: </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
From: Example User via Example List <listname@list.example.org>
]]></artwork>
      <t> The change inserts an operational address, for the
                Mediator, into the From: field and distorts the field's
                display name as a means of recording the modification.</t>
      <t>In terms of email identification semantics, this is a profound
                    change:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The result is that the recipient's software will see the
                        message as being from an entirely different author and
                        will handle it separately, such as for sorting or
                        filtering.
                        In effect, the recipient's software will see
                        the same person's email as being from a different
                        address; this includes the person's actual address and each of the
                        mailing lists that person's mail transits.</li>
	
        <li>Mediators might create a Reply-To: field with the
                        original From: field email address. This facilitates
                        getting replies back to the original author, but it does
                        nothing to aid other processing or presentation done by
                        the recipient's Mail User Agent (MUA) based on what it
                        believes is the author's address or original
                        display name.
			This Reply-To action represents another
                        knock-on effect (e.g., collateral damage) by
			distorting the meaning
                        of that header field, as well as creating an issue if
                        the field already exists.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>In effect, the From: field has become dominated by its role as a
                handling identifier. The current specification augments this
                altered use of the From: field by specifying the Author: field,
                which identifies the original author of the message and is not
                subject to modification by Mediators.</t>
      <t>While it might be cleanest to move towards more reliable use of
                the Sender: field and then to target it as the focus of
                authentication concerns, enhancement of existing standards works
                best with incremental additions, rather than with efforts at
                replacement. To that end, this specification provides a means of
                supplying author information that is not subject to modification
                by processes seeking to enforce stringent authentication.</t>
      <t>This version is published as an Experimental RFC to assess community
                interest, functional efficacy, and technical adequacy. See <xref target="experiment" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>Terminology and architectural details in this document are
                incorporated from <xref target="RFC5598" format="default"/>.</t>
		<t>
  Normative language, per <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/>:
		</t>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
	</section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Author Header Field</name>
      <t>Author: is a new message header field being defined. It has the same
                syntax as the From: header field <xref target="RFC5322" format="default"/>. As
                with the original and primary intent for the From: field, the
                Author: field is intended to contain the email address of the author of
                the message content. It also can contain the displayable human
                name of the author.</t>
      <t>The <xref target="RFC5234" format="default"/> for the field's syntax is: </t>
<sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
author = "Author:" mailbox-list CRLF
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>which echos the syntax for the From: header field. </t>
      <t> This header field can be added as part of the original message
                creation process, or it can be added later, by a Mediator, to
                preserve the original author information from the From:
                field.</t>
      <t> The goal of the Author: field is to reflect information about
                the original author. However, it is possible that the author's
                MUA or Mail Submission Agent (MSA) will not create it but that
                a Mediator might know it will be modifying the From: field and
                wish to preserve the author information. Hence, it needs to be
                allowed to create the Author: field for this if the field does
                not already exist.</t>
      <t>Processing of the Author: field follows these rules:</t>

      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>If an Author: field already exists, a new one <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be
                        created, and the existing one <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be modified.</li>
        <li>An author's MUA or MSA <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> create an Author: field, and
                        its value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be identical to the value in the From:
                        field.</li>
        <li>A Mediator <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> create an Author: field if one does not
                        already exist, and this new field's value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
                        identical to the value of the From: field at the time
                        the Mediator received the message (and before the
                        Mediator causes any changes to the From: field).</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Discussion</name>
      <t>The Author: header field, here, is intended for creation during
                message generation or during mediation. It is intended for use
                by recipient MUAs, as they typically use the From: field. In
                that regard, it would be reasonable for an MUA that would
                normally organize, filter, or display information based on the
                From: field to give the Author: header field preference.</t>
      
      <t>Original-From: is a similar header field referenced in <xref target="RFC5703" format="default"/>. It is registered with IANA, which cites
                <xref target="RFC5703" format="default"/> as the controlling source for the entry. However, that
                document only has a minimal definition for the field. Also, the
                field is solely intended for use by Mediators to preserve
                information from a modified From: field. The current specification can
      be used during either origination or mediation.</t>
      
      <t>While the basic model of email header fields is highly
                extensible, there well might be implementation and usability
                considerations for carrying this field through to end users,
      such as via <xref target="RFC3501" format="default"/>. </t>
      
      <t>Obviously, any security-related processing of a message needs to
                distinguish the From: field from the Author: field and treat their information
                accordingly.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>Any header field containing identification information is a
                source of security and privacy concerns, especially when the
                information pertains to content authorship. Generally, the
                handling of the Author: header field needs to receive scrutiny
                and care, comparable to that given to the From: header field,
      but preferably not in a way that defeats its utility.</t>
      
      <t>Given the semantics of the Author: header field, it is easy to believe that use
                of this field will create a new attack vector for tricking
                end users. However (and perhaps surprisingly), for all of the
                real and serious demonstrations of users being tricked by
                deceptive or false content in a message, there is no evidence
                that problematic content in a header field, which is providing
                information about message's author, directly contributes to
                differential and problematic behavior by the end user. (The
                presents an obvious exercise for the reader to find credible,
                documented evidence.)</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana_considerations" toc="default" numbered="true">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has registered the Author: header field, per
                    <xref target="RFC3864" format="default"/>, in the "Provisional Message
                Header Field Names" registry: </t>

      <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
        <dt>Header field name:</dt> 
	<dd>Author</dd>
        <dt>Applicable protocol:</dt> 
	<dd>mail</dd>
        <dt>Status:</dt>
	<dd>Provisional</dd>
        <dt>Author/Change controller:</dt>
	<dd>Dave Crocker
                        &lt;dcrocker@bbiw.net&gt;</dd>
        <dt>Specification document(s):</dt>
	<dd>RFC 9057</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section anchor="experiment" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Experimental Goals</name>
      <t>Given that the semantics of this field echo the long-standing
                From: header field, the basic mechanics of the field's creation
                and use are well understood. Points of concern, therefore, are
                with possible interactions with the existing From: field,
                anti-abuse systems, and MUA behavior, along with basic
                market acceptance. So the questions to answer while the header
                field has experimental status are:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Is there demonstrated interest by MUA developers?</li>
        <li>If MUA developers add this capability, is it used by
                        authors?</li>
        <li>Does the presence of the Author: field, in combination
                        with the From: field, create any operational problems,
                        especially for recipients?</li>
        <li>Does the presence of the Author: field demonstrate
                        additional security issues?</li>
        <li>Does the presence of the Author: field engender
                        problematic behavior by anti-abuse software, such as
                        defeating its utility?</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
<displayreference target="RFC3501" to="IMAP"/>
<displayreference target="RFC5322" to="Mail-Fmt"/>
<displayreference target="RFC5598" to="Mail-Arch"/>
<displayreference target="RFC5234" to="ABNF"/>
<displayreference target="RFC0733" to="RFC733"/>

    <references>

      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3864.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5598.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>


        </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0733.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3501.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5703.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The idea for this field was prompted by discussions in the IETF's
                DMARC Working Group, with participation from: <contact 
		fullname="Benny Lyne Amorsen"/>, <contact fullname="Kurt Anderson"/>, 
		<contact fullname="Laura Atkins"/>, <contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/>, 
		<contact fullname="Murray S. Kucherawy"/>, <contact fullname="Mike Hammer"/>,
		<contact fullname="John Levine"/>, <contact fullname="Alexey Melnikov"/>, 
		<contact fullname="Jesse Thompson"/>, and <contact fullname="Alessandro
		Vesely"/>.</t>
    </section>
    
  </back>
</rfc>
